<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Obesity on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Obesity/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Obesity on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Obesity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Weight doesn’t matter</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/30/weight-doesnt-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/30/weight-doesnt-matter/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The majority of people on a diet will tell you that they’re dieting because they want to lose weight.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you ask them &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they want to lose weight, you’ll hear things like “I don’t want to have a heart attack at 50” or “I have some extra flab” or “I want to get rid of my spare tire” or “I want a six pack.” So people want to be healthy, or they want to look good naked, or both. Importantly, though, none of these goals have much to do with weight &lt;em&gt;per se.&lt;/em&gt; What people are actually concerned with is excess fat. And we generally know this, of course. We know that when we say somebody is overweight we really mean the person is overfat. Yet, in day-to-day practice, we don’t use the word “overfat,” we keep saying “overweight.” And as a result, we keep confusing weight and fat, and more importantly, we use the wrong metrics to keep track of our dieting success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask anybody on a diet how they’re keeping track of their progress, and the answer you’ll hear most frequently is going to be “I weigh myself regularly.” There we have a major problem. People want to lose fat, but they keep track of their progress using a metric that inherently cannot distinguish between desirable (i.e., lean) and undesirable (i.e., fat) mass. As a consequence, they’re setting themselves up for failure. They may indeed lose weight but this weight loss may not be accompanied by the desired improvements in physique and health.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flawed metric of weight leads to such terrible TV shows as “The biggest loser,” which promote awful dieting advice. If you make it your goal to lose as much weight as possible in as little time as possible, you’ll inevitably burn off a lot of muscle mass. And that’s terribly sad, in my mind. The one thing every obese person has going for them is that they have a substantial amount of muscle under their layer of fat, from all the extra weight they’re carrying around all the time. Strip away the fat and keep the muscle, and you’ll have a strong, healthy person. But burn the muscle alongside the fat, and you’ll end up with a skinny-fat person. This person would now have to embark on a process of regaining (lean) mass, which will be psychologically terrifying and will usually not happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I should probably demonstrate that there is indeed a substantive difference between losing fat and losing weight. Enter one of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://crossfitnewengland.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/fat-vs-muscle.jpg&#34;&gt;favorite pictures&lt;/a&gt; on the internet. (&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; mildly NSFW, woman in underwear.) It shows how the same person can look visibly slimmer and more toned after gaining a substantial amount of weight, if that weight comes in the form of lean mass not fat. The reason for this dramatic difference is that muscle is substantially more dense than fat. You need &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of muscle to fill a decent volume of space, and that muscle is going to weigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If weight is a bad metric for fat-loss progress, how can you know whether you’re on track with your diet? Let’s first go over all the other commonly used methods that also don’t work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assessing body-fat bia bio-electrical impedance analysis (BIA). Many scales these days have BIA built in as well. When you step on the scales, they show you not only how much you weigh but also what your body-fat percentage is. Only that this number can be quite inaccurate. BIA results depend on numerous factors, not the least of which is your hydration status which may change daily. You can find a more detailed discussion of this issue &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bioelectrical_impedance_analysis&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; The one-sentence summary is that you shouldn’t track your fat-loss progress with a BIA device, and in particular not with regular scales that have BIA built in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at your abs in the mirror. This doesn’t work because it’s easy to trick yourself into thinking you’re doing great when actually you’re not. Even more likely is the opposite, though: You may think nothing much is happening when actually you have changed a lot. Fundamentally, this method is not sufficiently quantitative. You can never really be sure whether things have actually changed and by how much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pinching your belly fat. This method is also surprisingly unreliable, in particular when you’re getting lean. As you’re leaning out, your skin gets looser and you can pinch from a larger area, seemingly being able to pinch more at a time. This effect is particularly pronounced when you’re pinching from top and bottom. Try pinching your belly fat right underneath your navel, either from top and bottom or from left and right. Do you see the difference? Also, sometimes we can have a substantial layer of fat but can’t pinch it. For example, try to pinch the fat on top of your thigh. Can you do that? Chances are, if you can you’re pretty lean. For most people, the fat on the thighs doesn’t really separate from the muscles, and as they lean out it separates more easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One method that works reasonably well is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edb.utexas.edu/fit/bodycompfit.php&#34;&gt;dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA),&lt;/a&gt; basically a low-dose X ray. It’s the same method that is used to measure bone density. While it’s a great way to keep track of your body composition over time, it’s also cumbersome, expensive, requires professional equipment, and exposes your body to unnecessary X rays. Not something you want to do once a week.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other method that works is super cheap, easy, and reliable: get a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/AccuFitness-MT05-MyoTape-Body-Measure/dp/B000G7YW7Y/&#34;&gt;$5 tape measure&lt;/a&gt; and measure your waist circumference (just at the height of the belly button). That measurement should go down over time if you’re progressing successfully. How do you know you’re not losing lean mass at the same time? Your strength should stay the same or go up. If you’re increasingly &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/1/why-i-lift-weights-and-so-should-you&#34;&gt;lifting heavier weights&lt;/a&gt; while your waistline is slimming, you can be pretty certain that everything is on track. And if you happen to keep track of your weight at the same time, you may notice that your weight is going up even as your waist circumference is going down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the future, don’t plan to lose weight, plan to lose fat. And lose that fat while keeping as much of your weight as you can, maybe even increase your weight by a few pounds!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As incredulous as it may sound, there are indeed some people who are on a diet to &lt;em&gt;gain&lt;/em&gt; weight. There are entire online communities dedicated to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/gainit/wiki/index&#34;&gt;gaining weight.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s important to realize that people can weigh little and nevertheless have poor metabolic health. See e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/dr-mark-hyman/skinny-fat_b_1799797.html&#34;&gt;this article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It probably also isn’t sensitive enough to measure changes week by week. But doing a DEXA scan once a year might not be a bad idea.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year without breakfast</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/04/a-year-without-breakfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/04/a-year-without-breakfast/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, I gave up breakfast. The truth is, I’ve never liked breakfast. When I wake up, I’m not hungry. Why should I eat? However, breakfast is important, right? Everybody knows, breakfast is the most important meal of the day. Not eating breakfast is associated with all sorts of ills.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It will &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21448130&#34;&gt;make you fat.&lt;/a&gt; It will give you &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23031568&#34;&gt;heart disease.&lt;/a&gt; Why would anybody in their right mind not have breakfast?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, two things happened about a year ago that made me change my mind. First, I learned about the recent trend of intermittent fasting, which basically amounts to not eating for extended periods of time on a somewhat regular schedule. One of the most popular schedules for intermittent fasting is 16 / 8, which means that every day you fast for 16 hours and then you have an 8 hour window in which you’re allowed to eat. If you do the math, if you skip breakfast, have lunch at noon, and finish dinner before 8pm, you’re on a 16 / 8 intermittent fasting schedule. So 16 / 8 intermittent fasting is really just a fancy term for “skipping breakfast.” Second, and more importantly, I read this life-changing article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leangains.com/2012/06/why-does-breakfast-make-me-hungry.html&#34;&gt;“Why does breakfast make me hungry?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This article, written by one of the leading intermittent fasting proponents, explains in detail the hormonal reasons that cause some people to get really hungry shortly after breakfast. In fact, I had always noticed that I got really hungry about an hour or so after having had breakfast. And it didn’t seem to matter much what I ate, or how much I ate, for breakfast. I would be reliably hungry around 10am–11am. (I’m not an early riser.) So clearly, what was written in this article held true for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, between having a solid scientific explanation for why breakfast seemed to make me more not less hungry and a cool name for my new habit of not eating breakfast, I decided to take the plunge with 16 / 8 intermittent fasting. I haven’t had more than maybe 5–10 breakfasts, total, over the last year. Well, technically, my &lt;em&gt;break fast&lt;/em&gt; is the first meal I eat after fasting, regardless of the time. So to be more precise, I haven’t eaten before noon more than maybe 5–10 times, total, over the last year. When I started out, I would have coffee with some cream in the morning, so I had a small caloric intake shortly after waking up. But lately I’ve given that up as well. I now take my coffee black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been the outcome of this experiment? If you google “intermittent fasting,” you can read about all sorts of demonstrated or plausible health benefits, such as increased insulin sensitivity, improved body composition, or neuroprotection. But I don’t want to talk about that here. Instead, I want to talk about how it has affected me, personally, in my day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, my dependency on regular feeding has gone way down. Do you ever have the sense of “I’m starving; my brain is going to stop functioning unless I get food right now?” I used to have these sensations all the time. But if you think about it, it can’t be true. Unless you’re anorexic, if you live in the civilized world you’re not about to starve. You’re not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a day. Realistically, you’re not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a week. You’re certainly not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a few hours. So why would your body tell you so? Because after years of around-the-clock feeding, after rarely if ever experiencing more than a few hours in the non-fed state, your body has forgotten how to make effective use of its energy reserves. The required genes are not turned on. You can’t burn the layer of fat on your belly, even though it’s there. So your body screams for food. I know mine used to. Now, after a year of intermittent fasting, I don’t usually have this issue anymore. I’m certainly not hungry during my regular fasting window. And even if I have to fast longer, for example because I really have to get something done and can’t eat at my regular lunch hour, it doesn’t really matter to me. I just keep going, and I eat when I can. I also don’t usually snack anymore. Why should I need a snack if I’ve just eaten a few hours earlier? My body isn’t even done digesting yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other huge benefit is all the extra time I now have that I’m not spending on thinking about getting food, procuring food, preparing food, eating food. After getting out of bed, I usually have at least six waking hours before I first seriously think about eating. That’s a lot of productive time. Once you start cutting meals, you start realizing how much time and effort they require. Now mind you, I like to eat, and I like to prepare food. But once or twice a day is plenty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also don’t really experience afternoon slumps anymore. I feel overall much more awake. I have to add the caveat, though, that concomitantly with intermittent fasting I’ve also reduced my carb intake, a lot. Metabolically, the fasted state and the state on a low-carb, high-fat diet are very similar, so it’s hard to distinguish which intervention has caused what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But intermittent fasting is not all unicorns and rainbows. There are a few clear downsides that need to be mentioned. First, it took me probably 6 months to get really comfortable with extended fasts (16+ hours). Initially, there were days when I felt quite hungry, when I was literally looking at the clock waiting for my feeding window to open up. Second, on an intermittent fasting protocol, when you eat, you need to EAT. I usually have two meals a day; hence, each meal needs to be around 1100 Cals or so. (I don’t really keep track, but I estimate that I eat around 2200 Cals a day. Definitely not less, maybe more.) I rarely worry about excess calories when I eat, but I frequently worry about not getting sufficiently many calories. As a regular faster, when you go out to eat with your friends and family, you may find that they think you’ve gone nuts. While they barely finish their chicken breast, you order a couple of appetizers, extra butter for your steak, and some extra sides. And still you leave the restaurant hungry. Third, if you have business or social meal events during your fasting window, you have to decide whether you want to be weird and watch your company eating or rather break your fast. I’ve gotten quite good with just having a black coffee during breakfast events, but depending on your job and social demands, it could be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, has skipping breakfast made me fat and given me heart disease? Well, I have to admit that I’ve gained about eight pounds over the last year. And I’ve also lost about an inch around my waist. That’s what they mean when they say “improved body composition.” As to heart disease, so far I’m alive and kicking. Of course I can’t promise you that I won’t drop dead from a heart attack tomorrow. I’ll take my chances, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s the kind of nonsense that frequently passes for science in the field of nutrition. Not eating breakfast is &lt;em&gt;associated&lt;/em&gt; with all sorts of ills, mostly because both skipping breakfast and the associated ills are indicators of a stressful lifestyle and of poor eating habits. There’s absolutely no evidence that skipping breakfast in the context of a well-formulated diet and otherwise healthy lifestyle is harmful. Controlled studies generally find the opposite. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23672851&#34;&gt;skipping breakfast is a simple method to control overall caloric intake.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The author of this article is quite a character. But the science is solid.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
