<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Critical need on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Critical-need/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Critical need on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Critical-need/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Use fine-grained sectioning in your grant proposals</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have noticed lately that many scientists write grant proposals with little document structure. Their proposals may have separate sections for background, for specific aims, and so on, but each of these sections is basically a long wall of text. The problem with this approach is that most reviewers will not carefully read all this text, and as a consequence they will miss important elements of the proposal. All else equal, a poorly structured proposal will be much less competitive than a well-structured proposal with many sub-sections and titled paragraphs. Because grant-writing remains one of the most important skills to be acquired by junior scientists, I see a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application&#34;&gt;critical need&lt;/a&gt; to highlight the importance of fine-grained sectioning in grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two specific aims for this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 1. Demonstrate effective sectioning by writing this blog post in the form of a grant proposal.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By giving a clear example, I will allow my readers to quickly recognize the value of extensive document structure.&lt;/em&gt; I will write the entire blog post as if it were a proposal, and I will use an informative title for each individual paragraph and subsection. I will use short paragraphs that get straight to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 2. Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By providing useful and interesting content, I will attract more readers to my blog, who in turn will benefit from my advice.&lt;/em&gt; I will shamelessly promote this post on twitter and elsewhere, to the maximum extent allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;significance&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Significance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grant-proposal writing is a crucial skill for the modern scientist.&lt;/strong&gt; These days, being a scientist is as much about writing grants as it is about doing actual science. While we cannot be successful without doing good science and writing interesting papers, our success will be short-lived unless we can also successfully request funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the reader.&lt;/strong&gt; There is really only one type of reader for a grant proposal: a reviewer. And reviewers are notoriously pressed for time. Imagine having to evaluate 20 grant proposals in an afternoon. The last thing you want to see is a huge wall of text without structure and with no indication where the important pieces are located. You want short, clear paragraphs and sufficient structure, so that you can quickly jump to the relevant sections of the proposal and look up specific issues you want clarification on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the writer.&lt;/strong&gt; As a writer, you’ll actually have a much easier time writing the proposal if you have a clear structure in mind. If you don’t know what the specific purpose of a particular paragraph is, you’re more likely to blather on and not make a clear point. On the flip side, once you’ve written the paragraph heading, all you need to do is write a few sentences that make the appropriate statement and you are done. In fact, when I write proposals (and when I wrote this post) I usually write out all the paragraph headings first and then fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice is only useful to the extent that people see it.&lt;/strong&gt; If my blog has few readers, then I’m not making much of a difference in this world, regardless of how good my advice actually is. Each well-promoted post on this blog increases the visibility of the blog as a whole, which will increase in turn the visibility of each individual post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-1-write-this-blog-post-in-the-form-of-a-grant-proposal&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 1: Write this blog post in the form of a grant proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Most people tend to benefit more from concrete examples than from theoretical expositions on a topic. One could read a thousand words on effective sectioning and not have any idea of how to apply these ideas in practice. Or, one could see a simple example and immediately recognize how to apply its principles in one’s own writing. For this reason, in this post I emphasize demonstration over exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; I will write the entire blog post in the form of a grant proposal. I will have specific aims, which have hypotheses, approach, expected results, and so on. Each individual paragraph in this post will have a paragraph heading that states what the paragraph is about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I hope that at least some scientist somewhere on this planet will write a better grant proposal after reading this post. I particularly hope that this post will be useful for junior scientists who may not yet have seen many successful grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; First, it is possible that there are aspects to this post that are unclear or confusing. As a result, some readers may get an incorrect impression of what I’m saying. For example, someone could think that they absolutely have to provide a heading for every single paragraph, when sometimes it’s perfectly fine to have two or even three short paragraphs under one heading. To the extent that any readers express such misconceptions in the comments section, I will respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if nobody sees my post, then all my efforts are for nothing. I will address visibility in Aim 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-2-use-this-post-to-promote-my-blog-as-a-whole.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 2: Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Even the most well-reasoned and helpful blog posts are useless unless they are actually read. The visibility of individual blog posts is directly proportional to the overall reach of a blog. Therefore, I have to promote both this post in particular and the blog as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; Upon posting, I will tweet about this post. I will also tell colleagues and students about it. If somebody tweets about this post I will retweet their tweet, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_proof&#34;&gt;added social proof.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I expect to see a spike in web traffic when my tweet posts. I further expect that at least one or two of my followers will favorite my post, and that somebody will retweet it. Finally, I hope to pick up at least one new follower on twitter as a consequence of writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; If timing of my original tweet is poor few of my followers may notice my blog post. If I notice poor incoming traffic, I can consider tweeting about this post a second time. Further, if none of my followers tweet about my post then I have nothing to retweet. In this case, I may have to ask a student or friend to write a tweet for me. If all else fails, I can promote my post on facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The critical need in a grant application</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s surprising how many grant applications do not clearly spell out a critical need. A critical need is the fundamental reason why a grant should exist. Without it, there’s really not much of a point to the grant. And yet, a critical need is frequently not stated. The common mistake that people make is that they confuse a gap in knowledge with a critical need. They clearly spell out what gap in knowledge they plan to address. And mind you, that’s an important component of a grant proposal. But if you stop there, if you never explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; there is a critical need to bridge the gap in knowledge, then your application is going to fall short. Unless the reviewers really like you for other reasons, they will probably not be impressed with your grant application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain the difference between a gap in knowledge and a critical need by way of an example. Assume you go out Saturday night and get drunk. In the morning, you wake up and have no recollection of how you made your way home. This is clearly a gap in knowledge. But there’s no critical need attached to that gap. I couldn’t care less whether you stumbled home, took a cab, or hitched a ride with a friend. Your grant on “The modes of transportation by which I found my way home last Saturday” is not going to be selected for funding by my agency. Now, instead, consider the following scenario. You go out Saturday night and get drunk. You wake up Sunday morning, not remembering how you got home. Upon looking into the mirror, you find that you’re battered and bruised. You’re also covered in blood. And your husband is nowhere to be found and doesn’t answer his cell phone. In this scenario, I think most people would think that there is a critical need to figure out what happened, to fill the gap in knowledge. Your grant on “Why I am innocent and didn’t kill my husband. Honestly!” would probably fare much better than the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is: there are all sorts of gaps in knowledge that aren’t attached to a critical need. Grants to fill those knowledge gaps will generally not fare that well in review. Therefore, think carefully about the critical need your research will fill. If you can’t think of one right now, think harder. I’m sure you can immediately name the gap of knowledge you’re working on. The critical need should be just as obvious to you. Note: If you’re a junior scientist working on questions that your adviser has funding for, then your work almost certainly satisfies some critical need. If you’re not sure what it is, ask your adviser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where in a grant application should you express the critical need? It has to come early, so your reviewers don’t waste a lot of time being bored or disinterested. Also, it needs to be in a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position&#34;&gt;position of stress,&lt;/a&gt; so your reviewers correctly perceive its importance. Consequently, there’s only a single place in a grant proposal where it fits: the last sentence of the first paragraph. The entire first paragraph should build up to the critical need, which justifies why you’re writing your grant in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate this idea with the first paragraph of a grant I recently wrote:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparative sequence analysis is a cornerstone of modern biology, with applications ranging from determining the evolutionary history of species, to tracking pathogens, to identifying sites in a protein under positive or purifying selection. For protein-coding genes, comparative analysis has shown that protein structure strongly influences sequence variability: buried sites tend to be more conserved, and exposed sites—more variable. Deviations from this expectation can suggest functional importance. For example, a &lt;em&gt;rapidly evolving buried site&lt;/em&gt; in a viral enzyme might be near the binding pocket and contribute to the evolution of drug resistance. A &lt;em&gt;conserved exposed site&lt;/em&gt; might be involved in important protein–protein interactions. Yet conventional tools for comparative sequence analysis ignore protein structure and operate on sequence data alone. &lt;strong&gt;We, therefore, see a critical need to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first paragraph of the Aims page, arguably the first piece of text in the grant that the reviewers read. As you can see, the entire paragraph builds up to the critical need, which is to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data. This is a critical need only because we believe—and have some preliminary data to demonstrate—that sequence analysis in a structural context will be more informative for important applications than sequence analysis in the absence of structural information can be. If there weren’t any important applications, or if the structural information made little difference to the outcome of the analysis, then the critical need would evaporate. There’d still be a gap in knowledge around sequence analysis in a structural context, but there wouldn’t be a critical need to bridge that gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For full disclosure, I should say that this grant wasn’t funded. However, it was scored in the top third of applications (26% percentile). From my reading of the reviews, I would say that the reviewers believed our critical need. We just weren’t sufficiently competitive with the actual work we were proposing. Specifically, we didn’t have sufficient preliminary results to &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/which-grants-get-funded-at-single-digit-funding-rates&#34;&gt;give our proposal that aura of magic.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
