<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/categories/Writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/Writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Move over Strunk and White</title>
      <link>/blog/2017/11/12/move-over-strunk-and-white/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2017/11/12/move-over-strunk-and-white/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;“Read Strunk and White” is the near universal recommendation any student receives who needs to improve their writing. I have only two explanations for this frequent recommendation: 1. People have never actually read Strunk and White or don’t remember anything about it.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 2. People have never read any book on writing other than Strunk and White and hence have nothing better to recommend. To provide an alternative, here I would like to present my all-time favorite books on writing, covering three distinct topics: storytelling, copy editing, and writing productively. My recommendations are made from the perspective of the scientist as a writer. Nevertheless, the books I recommend are written for a broad audience and will likely be useful for anybody who is writing non-fiction documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;storytelling&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storytelling is probably the most important and least appreciated aspect of scientific writing. Every time you’re writing a scientific paper or a research grant, you need to tell a compelling story. Yet not many books on the market cover this aspect of writing. The one book that I’m aware of that does an outstanding job is &lt;em&gt;Writing Science&lt;/em&gt; by Schimel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joshua Schimel. &lt;em&gt;Writing Science: How to Write Papers That Get Cited and Proposals That Get Funded.&lt;/em&gt; Oxford University Press, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schimel explains what makes a story exciting and interesting, how to turn your scientific findings into a compelling story without compromising scientific accuracy, and how to structure sentences, paragraphs, sections, and entire documents such that your readers remain interested and engaged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;copy-editing&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Copy editing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best story arc doesn’t get you very far if your individual sentences are incoherent, awkward, or confusing. There are many books on the market that teach you how to write grammatically correct and clear English sentences. Most of them are quite good. My all-time favorite among them is &lt;em&gt;Line by Line&lt;/em&gt; by Cook:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Claire Kehrwald Cook. &lt;em&gt;Line by Line: How to Edit Your Own Writing.&lt;/em&gt; Houghton Mifflin Harcourt, 1985.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This book does an amazing job of systematically covering the grammatical and stylistic issues every writer should be aware of, and all the while the book remains quite readable. Unlike most texts with an emphasis on grammar you can actually read the book cover to cover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;writing-productively&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Writing productively&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last area where many writers struggle is productivity. Despite extensive knowledge of storytelling and grammar, your writing sessions may well consist of hours of staring at a blank piece of paper or an empty computer screen, with the occasional writing and subsequent deletion of a single awkward sentence. How to overcome this struggle is covered well in &lt;em&gt;How to Write a Lot&lt;/em&gt; by Silvia:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul J. Silvia. &lt;em&gt;How to Write a Lot: A Practical Guide to Productive Academic Writing.&lt;/em&gt; American Psychological Association, 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that there isn’t that much to be said about how to write a lot, other than that you have to write a lot. Silvia’s book makes no pretense otherwise, and that’s why I like it. Silvia covers the key concepts in a few short and highly readable chapters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;bonus&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Bonus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a bonus book, I want to recommend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richard L. Lanham. &lt;em&gt;The Longman Guide to Revising Prose.&lt;/em&gt; Person Longman, 2006.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have previously &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2015/8/26/avoiding-the-official-style&#34;&gt;blogged about this book.&lt;/a&gt; While everything it contains is in some form also covered in Cook 1985 and in Schimel 2011, Lanham’s book shines in its brevity. It will teach you some key writing skills by laying out a small number of highly effective editing techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ll challenge anybody to read Strunk and White cover-to-cover without falling asleep, and to summarize afterwards what they have learned. The book is available online &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jlakes.org/ch/web/The-elements-of-style.pdf&#34;&gt;in its entirety&lt;/a&gt;, so feel free to take this challenge right now.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When will that paper be ready?</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/12/28/when-will-that-paper-be-ready/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/12/28/when-will-that-paper-be-ready/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;No matter how experienced you are as a writer, how many papers you have written, you’ll likely never fully overcome this obstacle: Writing papers takes time. A lot of it. To get a paper submission-ready always takes longer than one would want, and it frequently takes longer than even the worst-case scenario prior projection. As writers, we need to understand what causes these delays, so that we can mitigate them (where possible) and also to simply be prepared for what lies ahead. Here I present three observations I’ve made over the years that explain why most papers take so long until they’re finally completed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;observation&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;every-senior-co-author-extends-the-writing-process-by-at-least-a-month-and-often-by-much-more&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Every senior co-author extends the writing process by at least a month, and often by much more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple factors at work that cause this delay. First, you need to have a decent draft before you can even show it to your senior co-authors, as they will probably not want to fix typos or logical flow, correct grammar, look at shoddy figures, etc. Preparing this draft takes time. Then, once you finally send them the paper draft, they’re too busy to even look at it. Then, when they’ve finally read it, they question some of your most basic assumptions, ask for additional analyses, or argue the story is wrong. Either way, they send you back to the drawing board. And then the cycle repeats, potentially for each senior author on the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the best strategy here is to limit the number of senior co-authors on your paper.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The second-best strategy, and the one you’ll have to pursue in many cases, is to simply accept that each additional co-author needs extra time and to plan accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;everything-always-takes-at-least-3-times-longer-than-expected&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Everything always takes at least 3 times longer than expected&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think something can be done in a week it will probably take a month, and if you think it can be done in a month it will probably take three. I have supervised a fair number of students and postdocs, sat on numerous PhD committees, and worked with many colleagues on a wide range on different projects, and I can’t think of many cases where things were completed in the projected time frame. Research is difficult, and there are always unexpected issues that crop up. Things break, the data look different than expected and require a change in approach, you get the flu, something else comes up that needs to get done immediately, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I’m a bit more optimistic here than &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hofstadter%27s_law&#34;&gt;Hofstadter’s law is&lt;/a&gt;, but I’ve definitely seen things take way longer than originally expected, even when the original time estimate seemed already overly generous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s one critical issue here, though, that you need to keep in mind: Don’t let this observation make you complacent and think “whatever, it’s going to take longer anyways, so I can take it easy.” If you plan to get something done in one week, it will likely take three, but if you accept three weeks from the outset it will likely take six. So plan to get things done quickly and at the same time accept that there will be delays, possibly major ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-real-work-starts-once-you-have-a-first-draft&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. The real work starts once you have a first draft&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students often think that their main work goal is the first complete draft. Once that goal is achieved, they assume, their work is basically done. In reality, the exact opposite is the case. Only once a first complete draft exists does the real work start. The first draft almost always reveals flaws in the work. Maybe there’s a gap in the logic. Or once everything is written up and put into figures and tables, the results look weak. Or your co-authors finally get to see how everything fits together and don’t like it (see &lt;a href=&#34;#observation1&#34;&gt;Observation #1&lt;/a&gt;). Or maybe different parts of the work were done inconsistently. (I see this often in simulation studies, where the code evolves as the work progresses. These kinds of studies almost always require a complete re-run of everything, from start to finish, once the paper is basically done.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give just one anecdote, I once wrote a paper with two co-authors, A and B. Me and A had done most of the writing and fleshing out the details of the paper, while B had provided the initial idea and general conceptual thought. We were all copied on all emails regarding this manuscript, and we went through at least 20 different drafts. At a point when I thought we finally had a draft ready for submission, author B suddenly said that he read the entire paper carefully the previous day and thought there was a major hole in our argument. Author A and I disagreed, but author B insisted and we spent another month fixing this perceived hole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my experience, it frequently takes 3-6 months from first complete draft to submission, and I have seen longer delays as well. For this reason, &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/8/26/when-should-you-stop-doing-science-and-start-writing-a-paper&#34;&gt;I advocate writing things up as early as possible.&lt;/a&gt; The first draft is not the goal, it’s just the beginning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The fastest I’ve ever gone from initial idea to paper submission was two weeks. That was a single-author paper.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Don’t use the passive voice?</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/12/19/dont-use-the-passive-voice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/12/19/dont-use-the-passive-voice/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I came across &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OV5J6BfToSw&#34;&gt;a talk by Steven Pinker&lt;/a&gt; on “Linguistics, Style and Writing in the 21st Century.” The talk is excellent and covers several important areas of writing advice. One of them is the topic of active and passive voice. I was pleased to see Pinker give the same advice I have been teaching for a while: The adage “don’t use the passive voice” is nonsensical. Clearly, passive voice cannot be categorically the wrong choice. If it were, then why should it even exist in the English language? There must be a valid use for this grammatical construct. Pinker provides one, and I agree with him. Here I’ll present this perspective in my own words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To fully understand when to use active or passive voice, we need to first grasp the concepts of the topic and the stress position. I have previously written a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position&#34;&gt;blog post about this topic.&lt;/a&gt; Please go ahead and read it now. I’ll wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re all on the same page, let’s proceed. The simple rule is this: Topic and stress trump active and passive. If the topic is the actor, use active voice. If the topic is being acted upon, use passive voice. Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maria read a book.&lt;br /&gt;
The book was read by Maria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first is a story about Maria. The second is a story about a book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we construct a story, it is natural to move back and forth between active and passive while keeping the story focused on one protagonist:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;John woke up with a splitting headache. Grudgingly, he got out of bed, brushed his teeth, and put on some clothes. As he walked down the stairs, he dreaded another boring day at the office. Yet, as he opened the door, he was greeted with the most amazing sight he’d ever seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how everything is active voice until we reach “he was greeted” in the last sentence. This sentence needs to be in passive voice, so that John can remain in the topic position and “the most amazing sight he’d ever seen” takes on the stress position. Any attempt to use active voice here would result in a much weaker sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, it is best not to worry too much about active or passive voice. Instead, focus on telling a clear story by placing the the correct elements into the topic and stress positions of each sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;whats-the-problem-with-passive-voice-then&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What’s the problem with passive voice, then?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If things are so simple, why do we keep hearing the advice to avoid passive voice? Because there are concrete issues that can arise when passive voice is used to excess, and I’ll briefly highlight the most important ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, passive voice doesn’t convey action as strongly as active voice does. For example, consider these two sentences:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas baked a cake.&lt;br /&gt;
The cake was baked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first evokes the image of a person being active in the kitchen, mixing ingredients together, putting serious effort into the creation of a cake. The second evokes the image of a cake sitting in the oven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, passive voice makes it easy to hide the actor. For example, compare:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a mistake.&lt;br /&gt;
Mistakes were made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first clearly assigns blame, the second doesn’t. Some writers deliberately use passive voice to hide the actor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In scientific writing, though, I think it’s more common that the actor is omitted not with ill intentions but merely due to a lack of writing skills, or maybe because of a false sense of modesty. The result, however, can be rather confusing. In particular, whenever I read an abstract written in the passive voice, I start to wonder whether the authors are providing background information from earlier work or telling me what they have done. For a recent example, consider the beginning of the abstract from &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/articles/srep18503&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fluorinated silyl functionalized zirconia was synthesized by the sol-gel method to fabricate an extremely durable superhydrophobic coating on cotton fabrics by simple immersion technique. The fabric surfaces firmly attached with the coating material through covalent bonding, possessed superhydrophobicity with high water contact angle ≈163 ± 1°, low hysteresis ≈3.5° and superoleophilicity. The coated fabrics were effective to separate oil/water mixture with a considerably high separation efficiency of 98.8 wt% through ordinary filtering. [. . .]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, passive voice encourages complex sentences with low content-to-word ratio, with long prepositional phrases, and with nouns attempting to carry the action—in a word, the &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2015/8/26/avoiding-the-official-style&#34;&gt;official style.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, pay more attention to topic and stress positions than to active and passive voice. However, in case of doubt, choose active over passive constructs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Formatting figure captions and tables</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/11/24/formatting-figure-captions-and-tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/11/24/formatting-figure-captions-and-tables/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Every scientist should know how to properly write and format figure captions and tables, yet this topic is rarely taught properly. We just hope that students and postdocs pick up this skill by osmosis. However, in my experience, this doesn’t necessarily happen or it may take a long time. To speed up this process, I gave a brief lecture on this topic in my graduate class today. Here are the slides I used. I hope you will find them useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything is unclear, please ask questions in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/jpHipDowm0Mk20&#34; width=&#34;595&#34; height=&#34;485&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; style=&#34;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slideshare.net/ClausWilke/writing-and-formatting-figure-captions-and-tables&#34;&gt;Writing and formatting figure captions and tables&lt;/a&gt; – Claus Wilke, Nov. 2015&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to not mess up your bibliographies with Bibtex</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/10/02/bibtex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/10/02/bibtex/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Bibtex is the reference manager for Latex. I have used it for 20 years, I have written over 100 papers with it, and I think it works really well. I have also rarely met anybody who could use it without messing up their bibliography in some way. Bibtex is an archaic program, written 30 years ago by a graduate student and never substantively changed or updated since. It uses an awkward database format for storing bibliographic entries and an atrocious, poorly-documented programming language for describing how bibliographic entries should be formatted. In fact, the most complete description of bibtex’s inner workings is aptly called &lt;a href=&#34;http://texdoc.net/texmf-dist/doc/bibtex/tamethebeast/ttb_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Tame the BeaST.&lt;/a&gt; (This document is well worth the read for anybody using bibtex with some regularity.) To help ordinary mortals succeed with using Bibtex, I’m providing here a set of best practices and useful guidelines that help you steer clear of the worst pitfalls of Bibtex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My guidelines are shaped by the following two insights, which I call the first and second law of Bibtex:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nobody really understands Bibtex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All bibliography managers that automatically generate Bibtex entries mess things up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A corollary of the second law is that all Bibtex entries need to be hand-curated to work correctly.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The following sections address some of the most common issues that I see in daily Bibtex use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;incorrectly-capitalized-article-titles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Incorrectly capitalized article titles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Article titles in a reference list should be capitalized in sentence case. In a nutshell, this means that all words except the first one, proper nouns, and acronyms are spelled in lower case (see e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.apastyle.org/apastyle/2012/03/title-case-and-sentence-case-capitalization-in-apa-style.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more details). Bibtex enforces this capitalization rule by automatically converting everything in the article title field to lower-case. This convention has the unfortunate side effect that proper nouns or acronyms, which should be capitalized, will be converted into lower-case as well. For example, the title “A review of HIV biology” will be typeset as “A review of hiv biology”. This conversion can be switched off by enclosing the words not to be converted into an extra pair of braces, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;title = {A review of {HIV} biology}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many reference managers simply disable Bibtex’s conversion by enclosing the entire title in braces, like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;title = {{A review of HIV biology}}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems like a smart idea, until you realize that the records that these reference managers pull are often capitalized in title case (all nouns capitalized), and this incorrect capitalization is then carried over to the bibliography. &lt;strong&gt;The only reliable solution is to manually curate all titles, enclose words with capital letters in braces, but otherwise do not use two pairs of braces around titles.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;incorrectly-abbreviated-first-names-and-missing-middle-initials&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Incorrectly abbreviated first names and missing middle initials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bibtex style files are inconsistent in how they handle author names. Most style files abbreviate author names, so that “John H. Smith” becomes “J. H. Smith” or “J H Smith” or “JH Smith”. However, some don’t. They leave the author names untouched and/or only add or remove periods. Yet we generally never want first names spelled out in a bibliography, they should always be abbreviated to initials only. Therefore, always abbreviate names in your Bibtex file, &lt;strong&gt;and leave a space between initials,&lt;/strong&gt; like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;author = {J. H. Smith}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;author = {Smith, J. H.}&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t leave a space between the initials, Bibtex will interpret the initials as a name and drop the second initial. For example, &lt;code&gt;author = {JH Smith}&lt;/code&gt; will for many style files be typeset as “J. Smith”.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I also recommend to always add periods after initials, even if some styles don’t typeset periods in the final bibliography. In general, Bibtex style files are better at removing periods when they aren’t needed than at adding them when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;mangled-author-lists&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Mangled author lists&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Bibtex’s author field, author names are separated by the key word &lt;code&gt;and&lt;/code&gt;. It is a common mistake to use a comma instead. Bibtex will then think that all the names separated by commas are actually part of one long name, and will produce a mangled author list. Usually, what it will do is turn the entire author list into middle initials for one author, so that you end up with something like “Smith, D. M. B. K. F. L. E. O. S.” Fortunately, it will produce a warning as it does so (&lt;code&gt;Too many commas in name...&lt;/code&gt;). Unfortunately, many Bibtex users ignore these warnings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ignoring warnings comes particularly easy when you use an integrated latex environment that compiles the text as you type. An example would be the online editor &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.overleaf.com/&#34; class=&#34;uri&#34;&gt;https://www.overleaf.com/&lt;/a&gt;. However, &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; Latex editors do display errors and warnings when you look for them, so make it a habit to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;inconsistent-journal-names&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Inconsistent journal names&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bibtex will not abbreviate journal names for you. So you have to do this yourself, and do so consistently. I recommend to always add periods after abbreviated parts of journal names, even if the style you’re currently using doesn’t require periods there (i.e., write &lt;code&gt;journal = {Mol. Biol. Evol.}&lt;/code&gt;, not &lt;code&gt;journal = {Mol Biol Evol}&lt;/code&gt;). At some point you’ll use the Bibtex entry with a different style file that needs periods, and things will go wrong. Again, Bibtex is better at removing periods than it is at adding them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people define Bibtex string variables for journal names to keep them consistent. This is a reasonable practice, but I personally don’t use it. If you want to learn how this works, read the &lt;a href=&#34;http://texdoc.net/texmf-dist/doc/bibtex/tamethebeast/ttb_en.pdf&#34;&gt;Tame the BeaST&lt;/a&gt; document, page 21.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;superfluous-issue-numbers-publication-months-or-other-elements&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Superfluous issue numbers, publication months, or other elements&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very few journals typeset issue numbers or publication months in their bibliographies. Yet reference managers like to populate the &lt;code&gt;number&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;month&lt;/code&gt; fields that Bibtex provides. This leads to ugly and non-standard reference entries. Moreover, it’s rare that every entry in a Bibtex file has a completed &lt;code&gt;number&lt;/code&gt; field, with the result that some entries in the final bibliography will have numbers listed and others won’t. Therefore, as a matter of principle, I always delete all &lt;code&gt;number&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;month&lt;/code&gt; fields in every Bibtex entry. I also delete all other fields that I don’t explicitly want to show up in the typeset reference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;choosing-good-bibtex-reference-keys&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Choosing good Bibtex reference keys&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to provide some thoughts regarding how to choose keys to refer to Bibtex references. (I.e., how do you choose the identifiers you use in the &lt;code&gt;\cite{}&lt;/code&gt; command in your Latex file.) Most importantly, it is a good idea to have a systematic approach to choosing keys. Ideally, you should be able to guess the key from looking at the reference. This rule protects you from accidentally duplicating a reference in the Bibtex file and referring to it under two different keys. I personally use keys that mirror a traditional author-year citation style, e.g. &lt;code&gt;SmithMiller2012&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;Jonesetal2014&lt;/code&gt;. For papers with multiple authors, I would recommend against using just the first author name and the year, such as &lt;code&gt;Jones2014&lt;/code&gt;, because in my experience it is not unusual to have multiple papers from the same year with the same first author, and at that point the keys become confusing. Which paper was &lt;code&gt;Jones2014a&lt;/code&gt; again, and which one &lt;code&gt;Jones2014b&lt;/code&gt;? By contrast, &lt;code&gt;JonesSmith2014&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;JonesMiller2014&lt;/code&gt; are much easier to keep apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;checklist&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Checklist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a final checklist you should go through every time you write a manuscript using Bibtex. (Some entries in the checklist also apply to Latex more broadly.) Most importantly, always read through the entire bibliography of your paper before submitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Capitalization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are all article titles typeset in sentence case, or do some remain in title case?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are any proper nouns or abbreviations typeset in lower case even though they should be capitalized?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author initials&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are all author first names replaced by initials?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are all middle initials present? (This may be cumbersome to check, but a warning sign would be the presence of multiple references in which no authors have middle initials. Most authors do have middle initials.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Author lists&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are author names showing up properly and completely? Warning signs would be papers that appear to be written by one or two people with way too many initials (four or more; few authors have four initials).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journal names&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are all journal names properly abbreviated?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are journals named consistently throughout the bibliography?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Superfluous items in bibliography&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do any references contain items that shouldn’t be there, such as issue numbers, months, ISSN or ISBN numbers, or article URLs?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34; style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compilation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do Latex and Bibtex run on your document without raising any errors or warnings?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, the second law applies more generally to pretty much any reference manager, including Zotero, Mendeley, Endnote, and so on, but that is a topic for another blog post. If you use one of them and don’t believe me, check if your article titles are properly capitalized, using sentence case. And if you don’t know what that means, re-read the section on incorrectly capitalized article titles.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To add insult to injury, on occasion I have encountered Bibtex style files that actually require initials to be listed &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; space. Those style files would drop the second initial when there was a space. In the end, you’ll always have to check manually that everything is working as expected, and adjust Bibtex entries as necessary.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Avoiding the official style</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/08/26/avoiding-the-official-style/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/08/26/avoiding-the-official-style/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Nobody turns into a good writer over night. Writing well takes a lot of dedicated practice, as well as mastery of many different topics, including grammar, punctuation, word choice, and document organization. However, if I had to name one single skill that likely makes the biggest difference in a person’s ability to write well, I would point to recognizing and avoiding the &lt;em&gt;official style&lt;/em&gt;. This style, named so by professor of rhetoric Richard Lanham, makes heavy use of passive voice, prepositional phrases, and complex, wordy expressions with little content. And it permeates the scientific literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a concrete example of this style, consider the following excerpt. It comes from a paper describing the function of the gene &lt;em&gt;exon0&lt;/em&gt; in a baculovirus:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The TEM results provide evidence that EXON0 is required for the efficient egress of nucleocapsids from the nucleus to the cytoplasm. The conservation of EXON0 in all lepidopteran nucleopolyhedroviruses suggests that it may play a role in facilitating a common transport pathway for nucleocapsid egress for this group of baculoviruses. However, &lt;em&gt;exon0&lt;/em&gt; is not strictly essential for the production of BV, since a few nucleocapsids in the cells transfected with &lt;em&gt;exon0&lt;/em&gt; KO virus did pass through the nuclear membrane, followed by transport through the cytoplasm and budding at the plasma membrane. Two possible explanations are that the EXON0-facilitated nucleocapsid transport process can be bypassed and that other viral and cellular proteins can replace EXON0, although extremely inefficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this excerpt, we can identify all the major elements of the official style. First, we see extensive use of passive voice, such as “EXON0 is required,” “&lt;em&gt;exon0&lt;/em&gt; is not . . . essential,” and “the . . . nucleocapsid transport process can be bypassed.” Second, we see long strings of prepositional phrases, as in “. . . required &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; the efficient egress &lt;strong&gt;of&lt;/strong&gt; nucleocapsids &lt;strong&gt;from&lt;/strong&gt; the nucleus &lt;strong&gt;to&lt;/strong&gt; the cytoplasm.” Third, we see wordy expressions with little content, as in “. . . suggests that it may play a role in facilitating. . .”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what can we do to avoid this style? A set of five simple editing guidelines provides a handy toolkit for writing more pleasant, less official-sounding prose:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Locate prepositions and &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify the action and put it into a simple verb.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get to the point quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the passage aloud—does it flow?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Vary the sentence length.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By following these guidelines, anyone can turn a dry, official-sounding document into a much more engaging piece of text. I have based these guidelines loosely on those presented in Lanham’s book,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; though none of them are particularly novel for experienced copy writers or editors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;locate-prepositions-and-is-forms&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Locate prepositions and &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; forms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official style makes heavy use of long strings of prepositional phrases. Prepositions are short words such as &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;on&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;until&lt;/em&gt; that express relationships between objects, persons, times, or places (&lt;a href=&#34;#fig1&#34;&gt;Figure 1&lt;/a&gt;). They are tremendously useful. But, when used in excess, they lead to boring, cumbersome, and frequently imprecise prose. Consider the following example. (I have highlighted the &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; form and the prepositions.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cells &lt;strong&gt;were&lt;/strong&gt; lysed &lt;strong&gt;with&lt;/strong&gt; 1% Triton X-100 &lt;strong&gt;after&lt;/strong&gt; 20 minutes incubation &lt;strong&gt;in&lt;/strong&gt; rich media prepared &lt;strong&gt;under&lt;/strong&gt; standard conditions &lt;strong&gt;with&lt;/strong&gt; continuous stirring &lt;strong&gt;of&lt;/strong&gt; the flask.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am sure you recognize this as a standard sentence you might find in the methods section of any molecular biology paper. If you have read many such papers, you may even find this sentence sufficiently clear. But is it really? Were the cells incubated or lysed in rich media? Were the cells incubated with continuous stirring of the flask, or was the stirring instead part of the media preparation? Or was maybe the flask stirred during the lysing of the cells? We don’t really know. The prepositions cannot precisely convey the relationships of the involved objects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above example contains six prepositions. In general, three prepositions in a row cause problems, and four or more prepositions usually guarantee disaster. As the first order of business, therefore, we shorten and/or remove, as much as possible, any strings of prepositional phrases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, some readers might want to defend the use of prepositional phrases. They might say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prepositional phrases are perfectly clear. A preposition connects the object, time, or place that immediately precedes it with the one that immediately follows it. As long as all the prepositional phrases are in the right order, everything is perfectly clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I disagree. Try to find the correct location for “with continuous stirring of the flask” if the flask was stirred during incubation. If you write “after 20 minutes incubation with continuous stirring of the flask in rich media,” then you are saying that the flask was in the media, when almost certainly the opposite was the case. If you write “after 20 minutes incubation in rich media with continuous stirring of the flask prepared under standard conditions,” then “prepared under standard conditions” seems to apply to the flask rather than the media. In addition, we often want to express that one thing is related to multiple others. In the above example, for instance, the authors might have meant to say that they carried out both lysing and incubation under standard conditions. The prepositions cannot unambiguously convey this meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can only eliminate strings of prepositional phrases if we can identify them. Therefore, Guideline 1 simply asks us to identify all prepositions and all &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; forms in each sentence.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The subsequent guidelines will help us with rephrasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;fig1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;across, after, at, behind, by, during, from, for, in, in front of, into, of, off, on, onto, out, out of, to, under, until&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1: Common prepositions in the English language.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;identify-the-action-and-put-it-into-a-simple-verb&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Identify the action and put it into a simple verb&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the exception of definitions—&lt;em&gt;a chair is a piece of furniture to sit on&lt;/em&gt;—most sentences convey
actions. Lots of them. Even the boring sentences in the methods sections of scientific papers. Actions are conveyed by verbs. Yet the most common verbs you will find in scientific texts are variants of &lt;em&gt;to be&lt;/em&gt;. The actions instead hide behind nouns and in prepositions. Consider the cell-lysation example. This example contains the following actions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to lyse&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to incubate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to stir&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to prepare&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet none of these verbs actually occur in their active form in the example sentence. Instead they occur as participles or gerunds, that is, in the form of adjectives or nouns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider a second example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Animals are housed on individually ventilated cages stacked in multiple layers with HEPA-filtered air provided to each cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example contains the following actions, again hidden in the form of participles or gerunds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to house&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to ventilate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to stack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to filter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;to provide&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have identified the relevant actions in a sentence, you can then express them in simple verbs. To provide you with some examples, &lt;a href=&#34;#tab1&#34;&gt;Table 1&lt;/a&gt; shows several long-winded &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; statements alongside their shorter, verb-based form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;tab1&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1: Equivalent long and short expressions of the same action.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Long expression&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Short and simple form&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is causing the removal of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;removes&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is causing the modification of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;      &lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;modifies/alters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;results in the elimination of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;eliminates&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;effects the increase of&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;increases&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is 57 words in length&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;contains 57 words&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is 100 meters long&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;spans 100 meters&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is greater than&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;exceeds&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;is resulting in&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;yields&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;get-to-the-point-quickly&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. Get to the point quickly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under Guideline 2, you have learned how to identify the action in a sentence and put it into a simple verb. Guideline 3 instructs you to get to the point quickly. Your readers have only so much attention—don’t squander it by writing long-winded phrases with little content. As an example of long-winded text, consider the following abstract of a paper investigating the inhibitory role of the protein NifL on the protein NifA:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . . we localized inhibition by NifL to its carboxy (C)-terminal domain . . . The first line of evidence for this is that internal deletions of NifL containing an intact C-terminal domain were able to inhibit transcriptional activation by NifA in a coupled transcription-translation system. The second line of evidence is that the isolated C-terminal domain of NifL (assayed as a fusion to the soluble maltose-binding protein [MBP]) was sufficient to inhibit transcriptional activation by the central domain of NifA in a purified transcription system. The final line of evidence is that an MBP fusion to the C-terminal domain of NifL inhibited transcriptional activation by NifA in vivo. (104 words)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This abstract contains the phrase “the . . . line of evidence . . . is that” three times, for a total of 23 words, 20% of the total text, with essentially no content. We can delete almost all these words without any loss of clarity or content:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;. . . we localized inhibition by NifL to its carboxy (C)-terminal domain . . . First, internal deletions of NifL containing an intact C-terminal domain were able to inhibit transcriptional activation by NifA in a coupled transcription-translation system. Second, the isolated C-terminal domain of NifL (assayed as a fusion to the soluble maltose-binding protein [MBP]) was sufficient to inhibit transcriptional activation by the central domain of NifA in a purified transcription system. Third, an MBP fusion to the C-terminal domain of NifL inhibited transcriptional activation by NifA in vivo. (84 words)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a simple editing rule, eliminate all phrases of the form “&lt;em&gt;something something&lt;/em&gt; is that” (&lt;a href=&#34;#fig2&#34;&gt;Figure 2&lt;/a&gt;). In most cases, these phrases don’t contain any content anyways. And even if they do, there will usually be better ways to provide this content. For example, consider the opening of this abstract:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements of toxicity based on individuals . . . and effects on reproduction are used extensively in determining ecological risk . . . . An underlying assumption is that individual-based toxicity metrics for one species can be directly compared with that for another species. However, this assumption overlooks the fact that different species have different life-history strategies and variables, such as lifespan, time to first reproduction, and number of offspring produced over a lifetime. Using a simple model and laboratory-derived parameter values, we tested the impact of differences in life-history traits on predicted responses to stress. (89 words)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This abstract contains the phrases “an underlying assumption is that” and “however, this assumption overlooks the fact that.” We would like to delete both. The resulting text might read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements of toxicity based on individuals . . . and effects on reproduction are used extensively in determining ecological risk . . . . Such risk assessments directly compare individual-based toxicity metrics for different species. But species differ in life-history strategies and variables, such as lifespan, time to first reproduction, and number of offspring produced over a lifetime. Using a simple model and laboratory-derived parameter values, we tested the impact of differences in life-history traits on predicted responses to stress. (73 words)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version is quite a bit shorter, but it requires the reader to understand that life-history strategies and variables may affect the toxicity metrics and therefore may confound the comparison. This information was present in the original version of the abstract, if in a somewhat indirect way (“this assumption overlooks”). Therefore, in this particular case, I would opt for a slightly longer version. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Measurements of toxicity based on individuals . . . and effects on reproduction are used extensively in determining ecological risk . . . . Such risk assessments directly compare individual-based toxicity metrics for different species. But toxicity metrics may not be directly comparable, because species differ in life-history strategies and variables, such as lifespan, time to first reproduction, and number of offspring produced over a lifetime. Here, we tested the impact of differences in life-history traits on predicted responses to stress, using a simple model and laboratory-derived parameter values. (84 words)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This version is almost as long as the original one. However, I believe it flows better and is easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&#34;fig2&#34;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact of the matter is that . . .&lt;br /&gt;
The reasoning behind this statement is that . . .&lt;br /&gt;
The general consensus is that . . .&lt;br /&gt;
What most researchers believe is that . . .&lt;br /&gt;
It is this fact that is . . .&lt;br /&gt;
The conclusion is that . . .&lt;br /&gt;
The result of this experiment was that . . .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2: Phrases of the form “&lt;em&gt;something something&lt;/em&gt; is that.”&lt;/strong&gt; These phrases generally convey no information and should be deleted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;read-the-passage-alouddoes-it-flow&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. Read the passage aloud—does it flow?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we are composing and/or editing a piece of text, we often spend so much time on small segments, inidividual sentences or phrases, that we lose track of the big picture. After half an hour of tinkering, we may have a paragraph whose every individual sentence is fine, but in combination the sentences don’t work. Fortunately, there is an easy way to identify these cases. Take a clean printout of your manuscript, sit down in a comfortable chair or sofa, and read the entire piece—aloud.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; (If you are working on a long manuscript, such as a book or a thesis, you may want to do this exercise separately for individual chapters or major sections.) While you are reading, pay special attention to the sound of your prose. Does it flow easily, or does it feel like a tongue-twister? Do the sentences connect nicely to each other? Do you always know where a sentence is going, or do you sometimes have to backtrack half a sentence because you thought it would finish differently than it actually did? Mark any issues that you see, but don’t fix them immediately. The purpose of this exercise is to get a sense of the larger structure of the text. If you immediately start tinkering with the text, you will lose that sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you have read your document carefully multiple times and marked all issues, go ahead and carry out the required edits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;vary-the-sentence-length&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. Vary the sentence length&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last guideline addresses sentence length. Consider the following paragraph from a paper on a new influenza treatment.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Read this paragraph aloud, and note what you experience while doing so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) virus H5N1 strains are currently causing major morbidity and mortality in poultry populations across Asia, Europe, and Africa and have caused 385 confirmed human infections, with a fatality rate of 63.11%. Preventive and therapeutic measures against circulating H5N1 strains have received a lot of interest and effort globally to prevent another pandemic outbreak. Influenza A virus poses a challenge because it rapidly alters its appearance to the immune system by antigenic drift (mutating) and antigenic shift (exchanging its components). The current strategies to combat influenza include vaccination and antiviral drug treatment, with vaccination being the preferred option. The annual influenza vaccine aims to stimulate the generation of anti-hemagglutinin (anti-HA) neutralizing antibodies, which confer protection against homologous strains. Current vaccines have met with various degrees of success. The facts that these strategies target the highly variable HA determinant and that predicting the major HA types that pose the next epidemic threat is difficult are significant limitations to the current antiviral strategy. In the absence of an effective vaccine, therapy is the mainstay of control of influenza virus infection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, the paragraph feels monotone. Only towards the end does it become a bit more lively. The feeling of monotonicity is created by two factors. First, most sentences contain approximately the same number of words. Second, none is very short. The one exception is sentence six, which contains only nine words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sentence&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Number of words&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Highly pathogenic avian influenza (HPAI) virus . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;36&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Preventive and therapeutic measures . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;22&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Influenza A virus poses a challenge . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;26&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The current strategies to combat influenza . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The annual influenza vaccine aims . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Current vaccines have met with . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The facts that these strategies target . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;34&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;In the absence of an effective vaccine, . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an alternative, consider this excerpt from an article on the effect of human activity on species diversity:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;8&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one denies that population size influences speciation rate. However, the direction of its effect is in doubt. At one time, many evolutionists, led by Ernst Mayr, believed that small isolated populations provide the crucible for evolution. They believed that getting speciation started is a matter of breaking up coadapted complexes of genes in geographical isolates. If that is correct, small populations would speed up speciation by enhancing statistical sampling accidents. But an alternative view exists. Called “centrifugal speciation,” it claims that large populations speed up speciation. Centrifugal speciation also begins with geographical separation of sister populations. But after separation, the larger isolates—not the smaller ones—do the changing. The small ones remain as evolutionary relicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We notice immediately that sentences in this paragraph are much shorter than they are in the previous example. And sentence length is also more varied. The shortest sentence has only five words. The third and fourth sentences are the longest. But with 19 words, they are still not overly long. And there is a good mix of short, medium, and long sentences in this paragraph. For example, after three moderately long sentences of 19, 19, and 15 words, the author placed a very short sentence of only five words:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;header&#34;&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Sentence&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;Number of words&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;No one denies that population size influences . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;However, the direction of its effect is in doubt.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;At one time, many evolutionists, led by Ernst . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;They believed that getting speciation started . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If that is correct, small populations would . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;But an alternative view exists.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Called “centrifugal speciation,” it claims that . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Centrifugal speciation also begins with . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;odd&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;But after separation, the larger isolates . . .&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr class=&#34;even&#34;&gt;
&lt;td&gt;The small ones remain as evolutionary relicts.&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td align=&#34;right&#34;&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus we arrive at our take-home message, both for this section and for the entire blog post: Be bold. Write short sentences. And then vary the sentence length. Your readers won’t mind a somewhat lengthy sentence, with multiple dependent clauses, if you wrote a few very short sentences just beforehand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. Fang, X. Dai, and D. A. Theilmann. &lt;em&gt;Autographa californica&lt;/em&gt; multiple nucleopolyhedrovirus EXON0 (ORF141) is required for efficient egress of nucleocapsids from the nucleus. &lt;em&gt;J. Virol.,&lt;/em&gt; 81:9859–9869, 2007.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;R. L. Lanham. &lt;em&gt;The Longman Guide to Revising Prose.&lt;/em&gt; Person Longman, New York, 2006.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;We identify the &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; forms because prepositions and &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; forms go hand in hand. Sentences with long strings of prepositional phrases almost invariably sport an &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; form as the main verb.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;F. Narberhaus, H. S. Lee, R. A. Schmitz, L. He, and S. Kustu. The C-terminal domain of NifL is sufficient to inhibit NifA activity. &lt;em&gt;J. Bacteriol.,&lt;/em&gt; 177:5078–5087, 1995.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;J. D. Stark, J. E. Banks, and R. Vargas. How risky is risk assessment: The role that life history strategies play in susceptibility of species to stress. &lt;em&gt;Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA,&lt;/em&gt; 101:732–736, 2004.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For a more systematic approach to text flow, take a look at my blog post on the &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position&#34;&gt;topic and stress positions&lt;/a&gt;. However, this approach doesn’t eliminate the &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/8/to-write-well-learn-how-to-read&#34;&gt;need for careful reading.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn7&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;N. Prabhu, M. Prabakaran, H.-T. Ho, S. Velumani, J. Qiang, M. Goutama, and J. Kwang. Monoclonal antibodies against the fusion peptide of hemagglutinin protect mice from lethal influenza A virus H5N1 infection. &lt;em&gt;J. Virol.,&lt;/em&gt; 83:2553–2562, 2009.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn8&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;M. L. Rosenzweig. Loss of speciation rate will impoverish future diversity. &lt;em&gt;Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA,&lt;/em&gt; 98:5404–5410, 2001.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-publication review of the PLOS ONE paper comparing MS Word and LaTeX: How not to compare document preparation</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/12/27/post-publication-review-of-the-plos-one-paper-comparing-ms-word-and-latex-how-not-to-compare-document-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/12/27/post-publication-review-of-the-plos-one-paper-comparing-ms-word-and-latex-how-not-to-compare-document-preparation/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PLOS ONE just published a paper comparing MS Word with LaTeX, which argues that LaTeX has little benefits over MS Word and should not be allowed by scientific journals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knauff M, Nejasmic J (2014) &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0115069&#34;&gt;An Efficiency Comparison of Document Preparation Systems Used in Academic Research and Development.&lt;/a&gt; PLoS ONE 9(12): e115069.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, this paper makes extremely strong claims based on a rather flawed and thin analysis. I am sure there are useful things to be said about MS Word vs. LaTeX. However, this paper does not make much of a contribution to this question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you some background: I have been using LaTeX for over 20 years, I have written tens of thousands of pages with LaTeX, and I am extremely familiar with its pros and cons. I am also using MS Word on a regular basis, and I regularly make the choice between using LaTeX or MS Word, on a document-by-document case. There are documents I’d rather write in LaTeX, and there are other documents I’d rather write in MS Word. There are also documents (increasingly many, in fact) for which I prefer entirely different approaches, such as Markdown. With that said, let me list the main objections I have to the Knauff and Nejasmic paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;apples-and-oranges&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apples and oranges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire premise of the paper is flawed: MS Word is a text editor, LaTeX is a file format. Those two things are inherently not comparable. There is no technical reason why MS Word cannot save documents to LaTeX, only the creators of MS Word chose not to implement this option. A simple work-around exists, however: Save the document as .docx and convert it to LaTeX with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. Incidentally, you can also go the other way round, write the document in LaTeX and convert to .docx. Fundamentally, file formats describing the same kind of data can be converted into each other. Therefore, people should be allowed to use the software and file formats they prefer (within reason, and preferably non-proprietary ones). Computers can sort out the differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-rigged-comparison&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A rigged comparison&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comparison the authors set up, the reproduction of three relatively simple, one-page documents, is entirely artificial and rigged to favor MS Word. This is particularly the case (and this is not really explained well in the paper) if the LaTeX users were tasked to reproduce the visual layout of the documents. LaTeX is meant to separate contents from layout, and the people who use it regularly tend to value that separation. However, this separation implies that it can sometimes be a bit difficult to achieve a particular physical layout. The correct, LaTeX way to solve this problem would be to prepare an appropriate style file. Yet I doubt the users in this test were given such a style file for the &lt;em&gt;continuous text&lt;/em&gt; example (which poses some tricky formatting issues with the title, author list, and address line).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anybody who has experience with both systems, it would be trivial to set up examples where MS Word utterly fails and LaTeX shines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set up 50 numbered equations, refer to them throughout the text, then change the equation order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have figures and their captions float to appropriate locations at the top or bottom of pages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change the order of figures in a document and fix all references to those figures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;its-not-surprising-that-latex-users-are-highly-satisfied&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s not surprising that LaTeX users are highly satisfied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the paper, the authors state (somewhat surprised, it seems to me) that LaTeX users are highly satisfied with their document preparation software. The authors seem to have no explanation for this observation, other than cognitive dissonance. In effect, the authors are saying that LaTeX is so awful that the only way to use it regularly is to convince yourself it is great even though it is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a simple alternative explanation, though: Even though LaTeX can be cumbersome and has its quirks, LaTeX is highly predictable. Once you have figured out how something works, it always works that way. LaTeX never crashes. Documents don’t suddenly change layout or font. Tables don’t jump around. By contrast, none of this can be said about MS Word. Everybody who uses MS Word knows that it sometimes does things that simply can’t be explained. Things that should work don’t. Formatting changes randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my own experience, to produce a final document, I fiddle around about as much with MS Word as I do with LaTeX, only that the issues with LaTeX are usually the same three predictable things (proper formatting of the cover page, some table issues, getting all the references into BibTeX). By contrast, with MS Word I always fight against some random, unexplainable stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;state-of-the-art-in-document-preparation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State of the art in document preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find most amazing about the Knauff and Nejasmic paper, considering that it is a study on document preparation, is that the authors seem to be completely out of touch with the state-of-the-art developments in that field. The authors barely even mention the important distinction between document structure and document layout, and they don’t discuss at all why one might want to separate the two. They also don’t consider automatic document conversions for different media (e.g. web versus print). Finally, they don’t discuss the increasingly important issue, at least for scientific documents, of integrating the text of a paper with the code used for data analysis and figure generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is plenty of room for improvement over LaTeX when it comes to document preparation. Most heavy LaTeX users would agree that the language can be cumbersome, and I haven’t met anybody who wouldn’t rather not type out all the LaTeX commands required to prepare a finished document. Extensive efforts are currently underway to address these and other issues, but these efforts are not happening in the world of MS Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most exciting current developments, in my mind, are happening with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&#34;&gt;Markdown.&lt;/a&gt; Markdown is an extremely simplified markup language that can be learned in half an hour or less. Markdown documents can be read easily in their source form (unlike LaTeX documents), and they can also be converted into HTML or PDF documents. (The PDF conversion usually goes via LaTeX as intermediate.) Moreover, through extensions such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;R Markdown,&lt;/a&gt; one can easily combine the document text, the code for data analysis and figure preparation, and the final figures, all in a single file. The result is a publication-quality document that is easy to produce, self contained, and allows for complete reproducibility of the analysis and figure generation. I bet that if the comparison in the PLOS ONE paper had been MS Word vs. LaTeX vs. Markdown, Markdown would have won hands down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;does-any-of-this-matter&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Does any of this matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why quibble over file formats and editors at all? As I said in the beginning, I use various tools, depending on the task at hand. As long as we can all agree that there are different use cases and that people can make informed decisions on which tool to use when, I’m fine. However, this is where the authors of the PLOS ONE paper go off the deep end. After presenting their relatively thin, somewhat rigged, and definitely not comprehensive comparison of one text editor to one file format, they then make incredibly strong claims, including that LaTeX users may be suffering from cognitive dissonance and that vast amounts of money could be saved if people were forced to switch over from LaTeX to MS Word. These statements are simply not warranted, they do not follow logically from the analysis presented, and they entirely disregard that the future of scientific document preparation may lay elsewhere (e.g., Markdown). If there is one thing this paper doesn’t make is a strong argument &lt;em&gt;in favor&lt;/em&gt; of MS Word, and we must be careful not to allow journal editors or other policy makers to use arguments such as the ones made in this paper to force us into a single mode of document preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Markdown, the easiest and most elegant approach to writing about data analysis with R</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/04/r-markdown-the-easiest-and-most-elegant-approach-to-writing-about-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/04/r-markdown-the-easiest-and-most-elegant-approach-to-writing-about-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend, I finally spent some time learning &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. I had been aware of its existence for a while, but I had never bothered to check it out. What a mistake. R Markdown rocks! It&amp;rsquo;s hands down the easiest and most elegant method to creating rich documents that contain data analysis, figures, mathematical formulas, and text. And it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to learn. I wager that anybody who has RStudio installed can create a useful document in 30 minutes or less. So if you use R, and you&amp;rsquo;ve never used R Markdown, give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R Markdown provides a literate programming platform for the R language. Literate programming, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;invented by Donald Knuth,&lt;/a&gt; allows users to write both a program and a document describing the program, at the same time. In the case of R, this means that you can write a document that contains R code, the output that is generated when the R code is run (including graphs), and prose describing the R code and its output. To give you an example, I started writing a tutorial for R&amp;rsquo;s ggplot2 library this weekend, and the original R Markdown file as well as the HTML output generated from that file are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wilkelab/ggplot2_cookbook/blob/master/README.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the word &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; stand for? &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is a minimalist approach to writing strutured documents. It consists of plain text with a few simple directives to mark sections, turn text bold or italics, or insert quotes. If you have ever edited a wikipedia article, you have used Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you an example, this is Markdown text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;We can make text **bold**, *italics*, or `look like code.`
We can also insert links, [e.g. to wikipedia,](http://www.wikipedia.org/)
we can quote things:  

&amp;gt; It is time to eat &amp;amp;#8212; Hungry John

or make lists:

1. Item 1
2. Item 2
3. Item 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be rendered like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can make text &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;look like code.&lt;/code&gt; We can also insert links, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikipedia.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;e.g. to wikipedia,&lt;/a&gt; we can quote things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is time to eat &amp;#8212; Hungry John&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or make lists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R Markdown works the same, only that it adds the option to insert R code  blocks. An R code block could look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r}  
# place R code here, e.g. to make a plot:  
library(ggplot2)  
x &amp;lt;- 1:10; y &amp;lt;- x^2  
qplot(x, y)  
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you convert the R Markdown file to HTML, the R code gets executed, the R output captured and inserted into the document, and you&amp;rsquo;ve got everything nicely together, with very little work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create an R Markdown document in RStudio, all you have to do is go to &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;New File&lt;/code&gt;, and then select &lt;code&gt;R Markdown&lt;/code&gt;. Accept the default settings, and R Studio will generate a new R Markdown file with a few lines of example content. To convert the file into HTML, simply click on the &amp;ldquo;Knit HTML&amp;rdquo; button. If you have previously stored your R Markdown file somewhere on your harddisk (with suffix &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt;), RStudio will automatically save the generated HTML file in the same location, with the same name and suffix &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt;. The HTML file is self-contained, including all images, so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to publish it on a web page or share it with people. RStudio also provides you with the option to publish the document online on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RPubs&lt;/a&gt; website. Just click on the &amp;ldquo;Publish&amp;rdquo; button in the HTML view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about R Markdown, go to:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No one reads your paper either</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/03/no-one-reads-your-paper-either/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/03/no-one-reads-your-paper-either/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downwithtime.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Simon Goring&lt;/a&gt; wrote an interesting post a few days ago arguing that &lt;a href=&#34;http://downwithtime.wordpress.com/2013/10/29/no-one-reads-your-blog-reflections-on-the-middling-bottom/&#34;&gt;no one reads your blog.&lt;/a&gt; In his post, he discussed reasons for why you might want to blog anyway. This post prompted me to tackle a topic I’ve been thinking about for a while: Why should you do science? Why should you publish? No one is going to read your paper either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, while I’m sure everybody agrees on the value of publishing groundbreaking, highly influential papers, most papers are neither groundbreaking nor highly influential. I have written over 100 scientific articles, and by my own modest guess at least 80 of those are completely irrelevant in the grand scheme of things, and probably more. My own measure for acceptable performance in a given year is that I publish about one paper to which I can point and say “probably more than 10 people will read this and actually care.” Over a 15-year career in science, that comes out to about 15-20 such papers, so I’m more or less on track.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Nevertheless, the vast majority of the papers I write, on average about 6 per year, are not that special and aren’t really read by anybody. So is there any reason to write them at all? Why not just write one big hit a year, or whenever it’s ready, and leave all the chaff unpublished?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality tends to correlate with quantity.&lt;/strong&gt; In your field, how many people do you know who publish one Nature or Science paper a year and not much else? I can think of maybe one or two people who have made that strategy work for them, but I’d argue that they are successful despite their publishing approach not because of it. For most people, productivity and impact tend to be correlated. The most prolific scientists also write the most widely-read papers and vice versa. It’s just like in the music business, you need to write a lot of songs to write a hit, and the people that write many hits also tend to write many many songs that aren’t hits. And, more importantly, it’s difficult to predict which song will be a hit and which will flop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate this idea with an example from my own career. In 2001 I wrote seven papers. Five of the seven have been quite successful, and have been cited over 50 times each. One of them, a Nature paper,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is still one of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ&#34;&gt;most cited papers of all times&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;user=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ:u5HHmVD_uO8C&#34;&gt;about 400 citations&lt;/a&gt; according to Google Scholar. When we wrote that paper, I was pretty sure we had a big story, so the success of the paper was somewhat expected.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The second-most cited paper of that year, however, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ:Tyk-4Ss8FVUC&#34;&gt;which at present has about 100 citations&lt;/a&gt; and is my 13th most cited paper of all time, was a total surprise. Notably, this paper was also one of my fastest ever from original idea to submission. I had a cute idea one afternoon, did a few calculations for a day or two, wrote a simulation in a few more days, and after a little over a week the entire paper was done and out the door. When I submitted this paper, I had no idea whether it was even publishable. Yet it got printed, and people really liked it. For the other papers I wrote in 2001, I also was skeptical whether anybody would ever care about them, and in the end five of the seven did really well. It would have been easy for me to be more selective in 2001 and write only 2 or 3 papers, but if I had done that I’d have missed out on writing a couple of well-received papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads me to lesson 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t know which of your papers other people will like. The more you publish, the higher the chance that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; you write is useful to somebody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequent publishing builds an audience.&lt;/strong&gt; My next point applies to scientific publishing just as it does to blogging: You need to build an audience. If you regularly publish on a topic, people start taking notice. They will make it a habit to keep an eye on your work, even if they don’t spend a lot of time actually reading your papers. Then, when you finally publish something really good, you have an audience ready and waiting. The exact same paper, published by somebody nobody has never heard of, might not get the same reception. In fact (and I’m not saying this is right, just stating how things are), it might not even make it through review the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus here is lesson 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to keep publishing regularly so people are aware of you and take you more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a limit to this, of course. If all you ever publish is useless drivel then you’ll eventually gain a reputation for publishing useless drivel. Stick to my guideline from the beginning of this post, publish at least one paper a year that is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequent publishing develops skills.&lt;/strong&gt; My next point is also just like in blogging: You need to write a lot to get good at writing. With every paper you write, you get a little better. Therefore, even the papers that don’t really have any content of consequence, where you know only three people will ever read them,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are worth writing just for the exercise. Can you imagine you make a major discovery, a real breakthrough, and then you don’t have the skill to turn your results into an excellent paper? That’d be a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, we arrive at lesson 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to publish as much as possible so you develop the writing and responding-to-reviewers skills that you will need to write your major hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson 3 applies particularly to students and young postdocs. They need all the practice they can get and hence should publish a lot, even if some of their papers turn out thin and inconsequential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing clears the mind.&lt;/strong&gt; My arguments so far can be summarized by saying that more publication quantity equals more publication quality. Some might raise the following objection: By writing fewer papers, they will say, they can put more effort into each one and hence raise the overall quality of their output. In other words, quantity can be detrimental to quality. I am not convinced by this argument. As I said earlier, one of my top-cited papers of all time took me all of two weeks to complete. At the same time, I could point you to papers that I put a huge amount of effort into and they never went anywhere. Impact doesn’t necessarily correlate with effort. More importantly, though, I believe that if one tries too hard to control quality both quality and quantity suffer. We need to publish papers so we are mentally ready to move on and write more, hopefully better, papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, ideas for papers can hurt your productivity if you get stuck on them. The most insidious ideas are the marginally good ones, the ones that aren’t so bad that they are easily dismissed out of hand but also aren’t good enough that you want to rush to publication. Those kinds of ideas can drag down your productivity for years, because they divert your attention and energy while not going anywhere. The best thing you can do with those ideas is to just publish them and move on. It’s so much easier to dismiss an idea as bad once the paper is out. I have plenty of papers on my cv where I’m the first to say they are pretty pointless.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But I don’t regret publishing them. If I hadn’t published these papers, maybe I’d still be thinking about the central ideas expressed in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the final lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to get a weak idea out of your head is to publish a paper on it. Don’t dwell on weak ideas, publish them and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have it, my reasons to keep publishing even though nobody reads (most) of my papers anyway. Now I’d like to hear from you: What are your reasons to publish or not to publish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until you realize that the argument I made was circular, because I arrived at ~80 irrelevant papers by assuming that I’m writing about 1 relevant paper a year, give or take.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;C. O. Wilke, J. L. Wang, C. Ofria, R. E. Lenski, and C. Adami (2001). Evolution of digital organisms at high mutation rate leads to survival of the flattest. Nature 412:331-333.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be honest, though, 400 citations and counting still blows me away. When we submitted the paper, I hoped that it would garner maybe 50 citations or so.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those three being the two reviewers and the editor of the journal.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, everything I published in 1998 and 1999.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use fine-grained sectioning in your grant proposals</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have noticed lately that many scientists write grant proposals with little document structure. Their proposals may have separate sections for background, for specific aims, and so on, but each of these sections is basically a long wall of text. The problem with this approach is that most reviewers will not carefully read all this text, and as a consequence they will miss important elements of the proposal. All else equal, a poorly structured proposal will be much less competitive than a well-structured proposal with many sub-sections and titled paragraphs. Because grant-writing remains one of the most important skills to be acquired by junior scientists, I see a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application&#34;&gt;critical need&lt;/a&gt; to highlight the importance of fine-grained sectioning in grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two specific aims for this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 1. Demonstrate effective sectioning by writing this blog post in the form of a grant proposal.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By giving a clear example, I will allow my readers to quickly recognize the value of extensive document structure.&lt;/em&gt; I will write the entire blog post as if it were a proposal, and I will use an informative title for each individual paragraph and subsection. I will use short paragraphs that get straight to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 2. Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By providing useful and interesting content, I will attract more readers to my blog, who in turn will benefit from my advice.&lt;/em&gt; I will shamelessly promote this post on twitter and elsewhere, to the maximum extent allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;significance&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Significance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grant-proposal writing is a crucial skill for the modern scientist.&lt;/strong&gt; These days, being a scientist is as much about writing grants as it is about doing actual science. While we cannot be successful without doing good science and writing interesting papers, our success will be short-lived unless we can also successfully request funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the reader.&lt;/strong&gt; There is really only one type of reader for a grant proposal: a reviewer. And reviewers are notoriously pressed for time. Imagine having to evaluate 20 grant proposals in an afternoon. The last thing you want to see is a huge wall of text without structure and with no indication where the important pieces are located. You want short, clear paragraphs and sufficient structure, so that you can quickly jump to the relevant sections of the proposal and look up specific issues you want clarification on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the writer.&lt;/strong&gt; As a writer, you’ll actually have a much easier time writing the proposal if you have a clear structure in mind. If you don’t know what the specific purpose of a particular paragraph is, you’re more likely to blather on and not make a clear point. On the flip side, once you’ve written the paragraph heading, all you need to do is write a few sentences that make the appropriate statement and you are done. In fact, when I write proposals (and when I wrote this post) I usually write out all the paragraph headings first and then fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice is only useful to the extent that people see it.&lt;/strong&gt; If my blog has few readers, then I’m not making much of a difference in this world, regardless of how good my advice actually is. Each well-promoted post on this blog increases the visibility of the blog as a whole, which will increase in turn the visibility of each individual post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-1-write-this-blog-post-in-the-form-of-a-grant-proposal&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 1: Write this blog post in the form of a grant proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Most people tend to benefit more from concrete examples than from theoretical expositions on a topic. One could read a thousand words on effective sectioning and not have any idea of how to apply these ideas in practice. Or, one could see a simple example and immediately recognize how to apply its principles in one’s own writing. For this reason, in this post I emphasize demonstration over exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; I will write the entire blog post in the form of a grant proposal. I will have specific aims, which have hypotheses, approach, expected results, and so on. Each individual paragraph in this post will have a paragraph heading that states what the paragraph is about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I hope that at least some scientist somewhere on this planet will write a better grant proposal after reading this post. I particularly hope that this post will be useful for junior scientists who may not yet have seen many successful grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; First, it is possible that there are aspects to this post that are unclear or confusing. As a result, some readers may get an incorrect impression of what I’m saying. For example, someone could think that they absolutely have to provide a heading for every single paragraph, when sometimes it’s perfectly fine to have two or even three short paragraphs under one heading. To the extent that any readers express such misconceptions in the comments section, I will respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if nobody sees my post, then all my efforts are for nothing. I will address visibility in Aim 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-2-use-this-post-to-promote-my-blog-as-a-whole.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 2: Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Even the most well-reasoned and helpful blog posts are useless unless they are actually read. The visibility of individual blog posts is directly proportional to the overall reach of a blog. Therefore, I have to promote both this post in particular and the blog as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; Upon posting, I will tweet about this post. I will also tell colleagues and students about it. If somebody tweets about this post I will retweet their tweet, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_proof&#34;&gt;added social proof.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I expect to see a spike in web traffic when my tweet posts. I further expect that at least one or two of my followers will favorite my post, and that somebody will retweet it. Finally, I hope to pick up at least one new follower on twitter as a consequence of writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; If timing of my original tweet is poor few of my followers may notice my blog post. If I notice poor incoming traffic, I can consider tweeting about this post a second time. Further, if none of my followers tweet about my post then I have nothing to retweet. In this case, I may have to ask a student or friend to write a tweet for me. If all else fails, I can promote my post on facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The critical need in a grant application</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s surprising how many grant applications do not clearly spell out a critical need. A critical need is the fundamental reason why a grant should exist. Without it, there’s really not much of a point to the grant. And yet, a critical need is frequently not stated. The common mistake that people make is that they confuse a gap in knowledge with a critical need. They clearly spell out what gap in knowledge they plan to address. And mind you, that’s an important component of a grant proposal. But if you stop there, if you never explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; there is a critical need to bridge the gap in knowledge, then your application is going to fall short. Unless the reviewers really like you for other reasons, they will probably not be impressed with your grant application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain the difference between a gap in knowledge and a critical need by way of an example. Assume you go out Saturday night and get drunk. In the morning, you wake up and have no recollection of how you made your way home. This is clearly a gap in knowledge. But there’s no critical need attached to that gap. I couldn’t care less whether you stumbled home, took a cab, or hitched a ride with a friend. Your grant on “The modes of transportation by which I found my way home last Saturday” is not going to be selected for funding by my agency. Now, instead, consider the following scenario. You go out Saturday night and get drunk. You wake up Sunday morning, not remembering how you got home. Upon looking into the mirror, you find that you’re battered and bruised. You’re also covered in blood. And your husband is nowhere to be found and doesn’t answer his cell phone. In this scenario, I think most people would think that there is a critical need to figure out what happened, to fill the gap in knowledge. Your grant on “Why I am innocent and didn’t kill my husband. Honestly!” would probably fare much better than the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is: there are all sorts of gaps in knowledge that aren’t attached to a critical need. Grants to fill those knowledge gaps will generally not fare that well in review. Therefore, think carefully about the critical need your research will fill. If you can’t think of one right now, think harder. I’m sure you can immediately name the gap of knowledge you’re working on. The critical need should be just as obvious to you. Note: If you’re a junior scientist working on questions that your adviser has funding for, then your work almost certainly satisfies some critical need. If you’re not sure what it is, ask your adviser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where in a grant application should you express the critical need? It has to come early, so your reviewers don’t waste a lot of time being bored or disinterested. Also, it needs to be in a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position&#34;&gt;position of stress,&lt;/a&gt; so your reviewers correctly perceive its importance. Consequently, there’s only a single place in a grant proposal where it fits: the last sentence of the first paragraph. The entire first paragraph should build up to the critical need, which justifies why you’re writing your grant in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate this idea with the first paragraph of a grant I recently wrote:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparative sequence analysis is a cornerstone of modern biology, with applications ranging from determining the evolutionary history of species, to tracking pathogens, to identifying sites in a protein under positive or purifying selection. For protein-coding genes, comparative analysis has shown that protein structure strongly influences sequence variability: buried sites tend to be more conserved, and exposed sites—more variable. Deviations from this expectation can suggest functional importance. For example, a &lt;em&gt;rapidly evolving buried site&lt;/em&gt; in a viral enzyme might be near the binding pocket and contribute to the evolution of drug resistance. A &lt;em&gt;conserved exposed site&lt;/em&gt; might be involved in important protein–protein interactions. Yet conventional tools for comparative sequence analysis ignore protein structure and operate on sequence data alone. &lt;strong&gt;We, therefore, see a critical need to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first paragraph of the Aims page, arguably the first piece of text in the grant that the reviewers read. As you can see, the entire paragraph builds up to the critical need, which is to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data. This is a critical need only because we believe—and have some preliminary data to demonstrate—that sequence analysis in a structural context will be more informative for important applications than sequence analysis in the absence of structural information can be. If there weren’t any important applications, or if the structural information made little difference to the outcome of the analysis, then the critical need would evaporate. There’d still be a gap in knowledge around sequence analysis in a structural context, but there wouldn’t be a critical need to bridge that gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For full disclosure, I should say that this grant wasn’t funded. However, it was scored in the top third of applications (26% percentile). From my reading of the reviews, I would say that the reviewers believed our critical need. We just weren’t sufficiently competitive with the actual work we were proposing. Specifically, we didn’t have sufficient preliminary results to &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/which-grants-get-funded-at-single-digit-funding-rates&#34;&gt;give our proposal that aura of magic.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To write well, learn how to read</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/08/to-write-well-learn-how-to-read/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/08/to-write-well-learn-how-to-read/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, one of the major impediments to writing well is an inability to read. I’m not talking about basic illiteracy here. I’m talking about the following tendency that I have seen in many literate people: reading what one thinks was written rather than what was actually written. If you have this tendency, you may subconsciously fix grammatical errors, insert words that aren’t actually on the page, or even fill in larger logical gaps. You may also subconsciously delete words that shouldn’t be there in the first place. You probably do this when you read other people’s prose, and you’ll do it even more so when you read your own prose. As a result, you won’t notice when your writing has issues. And hence you won’t fix the issues. Your readers, however, may notice them, or they may simply not understand what you’re trying to say. If you are interested in writing clear and understandable prose, make sure that you’re actually reading what you wrote, not what you think you wrote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;can-you-read&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Can you read?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, how do you know whether you’re reading sufficiently well? To a first approximation, I’d assume that nobody can read. I know that’s not true, but in my experience it’s an approximation that matches reality reasonably well. However, to be more constructive, let me offer some specific self-assessments for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, in my previous blog post I purposefully introduced a few grammatical mistakes, as a pun. I pointed out the respective paragraph to a couple of students. Some got my pun immediately, but others didn’t notice that anything was wrong. Even when specifically searching for issues they couldn’t find them. Why don’t you &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/1/articles&#34;&gt;check out that post right now and see if you notice anything?&lt;/a&gt; The specific sentence I’m talking about is in the second paragraph. What’s wrong with it is explained in the notes.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, read the present paragraph carefully.There are several typographic mistakes here. Do you notice them?. It’s very important  to  pay close attention to even the most minute details. You may think it doesn’t matter much, but some of your readers will pay close attention, and they will notice almost anything. For them, too many little mistakes and issues will make your writing unpalatable. Again, you can find an explanation of what’s wrong with this paragraph in the notes.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, let’s consider situations where grammatical mistakes actually alter the meaning of a sentence. For example, consider this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Painted in exquisite detail, you can sell this painting for a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this sentence tell you? Did you understand that you have a painting that is painted in exquisite detail, and that therefore you can sell it at a high price? If that’s what you read, I’ve got bad news for you: You need to work on your reading comprehension. That’s not what the sentence says at all. The sentence says that &lt;em&gt;you,&lt;/em&gt; the reader, have been painted in exquisite detail, and that therefore you can sell this painting (about which we know nothing) for a high price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s consider a different example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that lions do not generally like to eat ice cream which agrees with our prior expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did this sentence tell you? Did you understand that we had a prior expectation that lions don’t eat ice cream, and that this expectation was confirmed in our experiment feeding ice cream to lions? If that’s what you got from this sentence then you have to pay closer attention to what is actually written. What the sentence actually says is that certain ice creams agree with our prior expectations. (Whatever they are. We are not told.) &lt;em&gt;Those&lt;/em&gt; specific ice creams are not palatable to lions. Other ice creams, those that don’t agree with our prior expectations, may well be palatable to lions, but we are not told anything about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might think that there is a punctuation mistake, that a comma is needed after “ice cream.” Unfortunately, even with that comma, the sentence still doesn’t make sense. It just doesn’t make sense in a different way.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-improve&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to improve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of simple techniques and exercises that you can do to improve your reading. First, get a good book or two about the intricacies of the English language.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Go through the examples in these books, in particular the examples of how one should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; write, and try to figure out what’s wrong with them and how you could fix them. With practice, you’ll get quite good at recognizing problematic writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, it’s really important that you slow down your reading speed. If you frequently read over grammatical mistakes or logical gaps then you’re reading too fast. It’s Ok to read fast when you’re reading somebody else’s words, but when you proof-read your own you need to be slow. A simple way to slow down your reading speed is to sit down and read your text aloud. It’s really difficult to do that and not notice missing pieces or logical gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, to assess overall flow and sentence connections, it’s important to read larger units of text. If you constantly go back and forth between reading and editing, you may be so focused on individual sentences that you’ll never notice larger issues that may exist in your prose. Make sure that when you proof-read you read larger chunks of text at once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourth, I find it important to read a document multiple times exactly in the same format in which it will be seen by my readers. I can’t exactly pinpoint why it makes a difference but I know it does. For example, when I write scientific papers or grant proposals, I tend to do most of my proof-reading on printouts. On printouts, I always find issues that I didn’t see while editing. In these days of high-resolution screens and tablets, maybe you feel that printing documents shouldn’t be necessary anymore. And maybe you’re right. However, at a minimum, export the document from your word processor and read it on the screen just how your readers would. For example, create a pdf, open it on your tablet, and proof-read there. Make comments in longhand onto the pdf. (There are excellent apps for this purpose.) I proof-read all my blog posts on the web site, in the final format. I always find many minor issues that I didn’t see when I was composing the post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students frequently hand me documents that look like they have never been proof-read. And when I ask the students whether they printed out the document and went over it slowly with a pen, the answer is usually “no.” Don’t be that student. Proof-read your documents carefully before giving them to somebody else. Don’t rely on others to find your writing mistakes, find them yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last sentence is missing three articles. It should have read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But make one non-native mistake, such as not using &lt;strong&gt;an&lt;/strong&gt; article when &lt;strong&gt;an&lt;/strong&gt; article is needed, and you’ll immediately sound like &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; person with poor English skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought that native English speakers would immediately notice the missing articles and get the impression that this sentence was written by a foreigner. Well, some did and some didn’t.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Issues in this paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Missing space after “carefully.” (1st sentence)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extra period in “Do you notice them?.” (3rd sentence)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Excessive space around “to” (before and after) in “It’s very important  to  pay” (4th sentence)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;With the comma, the sentence says that lions don’t like to eat ice cream, and that ice cream typically doesn’t agree with our prior expectations. If you don’t see that, consider the following modification of the sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found that lions do not generally like to eat ice cream, which is cold and full of sugar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple of good ones are: Lyn Dupre, &lt;em&gt;BUGS in writing;&lt;/em&gt; Claire Kehrwald Cook, &lt;em&gt;Line by line;&lt;/em&gt; Lynne Truss, &lt;em&gt;Eats, shoots &amp;amp; leaves;&lt;/em&gt; Patricia T. O’Conner; &lt;em&gt;Woe is I.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I compose my posts in google docs and upload them once they’re done. Then I spend another hour or so copy-editing in the final format.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Articles!</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/01/articles/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/01/articles/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After having authored thousands of printed pages and having taught writing at the graduate level, all in English (my third language), I’ve come to this conclusion: We non-native speakers have a major advantage over native speakers when it comes to writing in the English language. We may not know how to write properly, but at least &lt;em&gt;we know&lt;/em&gt; that we don’t know. Most native English speakers don’t know how to write properly either, but they &lt;em&gt;don’t know that they don’t know.&lt;/em&gt; Because we’re acutely aware of our language deficiencies, we non-native speakers will generally put much more effort into learning proper English than native speakers will.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I’ve often seen non-native speakers worry about grammatical subtleties that no (untrained) native speaker could discern while at the same time making mistakes that no native speaker would ever make. This can lead to the curious situation where a non-native speaker may actually have a pretty good command of the English grammar and yet his writing will be considered as “poor” and “full of errors.” I’ve thus concluded that it may not matter so much that we truly understand English grammar in all its subtleties.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; What matters most is that we don’t make the mistakes native English speakers &lt;em&gt;wouldn’t make.&lt;/em&gt; We can use dangling participles, missing antecedents, and comma splices all day long, and most people won’t hold it against us. But make one non-native mistake, such as not using article when article is needed, and you’ll immediately sound like person with poor English skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the following atrocity of a sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a native speaker, writing grammatically correct sentences is difficult for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most native speakers would happily accept this sentence as correct, even though it has a glaring grammatical error.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Now consider this sentence:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As non-native speaker, I can write difficult sentence with only few minor errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most native speakers would recoil in horror, yet all the second author is guilty of is omission of a few articles. Fix the articles, and the sentence is perfectly fine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; non-native speaker, I can write &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; difficult sentence with only &lt;strong&gt;a&lt;/strong&gt; few minor errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple example shows how important it is that you master proper use of articles. In particular, if you’re from Eastern Europe or from Asia and your mother tongue doesn’t have the concept of articles, you will have to put in some serious effort into understanding articles. Otherwise, your prose will always sound like it was written by a foreigner, regardless of how grammatically correct everything else is. So let me give you a brief primer on proper use of articles in the English language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;definite-vs-indefinite-articles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Definite vs indefinite articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;definite article,&lt;/em&gt; which in English is “the”, refers to a particular member of a group. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cat is on the roof.&lt;br /&gt;
I have to feed the dogs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author is talking about one specific cat, one specific roof, one specific dog. By contrast, the &lt;em&gt;indefinite article,&lt;/em&gt; which in English can be “a,” “an,” or no article, refers to any member of a group. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cat is a fierce predator.&lt;br /&gt;
An elephant eats foliage.&lt;br /&gt;
Dogs give us unconditional love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author is now talking about any possible cat, any possible predator, any possible elephant, and any possible dogs. Note that the words “foliage” and “unconditional love” fall under the rule of “things that can’t be counted,” which I’ll discuss in the next subsection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing that may be confusing is that in two subsequent sentences, the same word may need an indefinite and a definite article. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I saw a black cat. The cat crossed the street from left to right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first occurrence of the cat requires “a,” because we haven’t heard about the cat before. Thus, at this point in the story, we can only be talking about any arbitrary cat. By the second sentence, though, the cat has been defined. It’s the one that is black and that I saw. Hence, now I have to refer to it as “the cat.” Similarly, I wrote “the cat” throughout this paragraph because I kept referring to that same, black cat defined in the first sentence of the example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your native language doesn’t distinguish between definite and indefinite articles it may be difficult for you to get an intuitive sense of what it means to be talking about a specific member of a group or about any arbitrary member of a group. If you experience this problem, you will have to practice deliberately. Don’t think that you’ll just intuitively get it one day, because you won’t. You will have to analyze properly written sentences and for every noun in every sentence figure out exactly why it has the article it does. Then, in your own writing, you will have to go over every noun and determine whether it represents a specific member of a group or any arbitrary member of a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;names-countries-things-that-cant-be-counted&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Names, countries, things that can’t be counted&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Names, countries, and things that can’t be counted generally don’t have articles. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Martin likes ice cream.&lt;br /&gt;
England borders Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Martin” is a name, “ice cream” cannot be counted, and “England” and “Europe” are countries. However, don’t get confused by country names that include an article, such as “The Netherlands.” The article is part of the name because the name originally referred to a geographic location, such as “the Alps” or “the Sierra Nevada.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;places-with-distinct-sets-of-social-behaviors&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Places with distinct sets of social behaviors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, here comes my favorite rule about articles. This rule is so awesome it needs to be printed in italics:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We don’t use articles in preprositional phrases referring to places that require a distinct set of social behaviors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is such a mouthful, most people cannot even repeat it without error. Yet we all use it instinctively, when we say things like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where do you go to school?&lt;br /&gt;
Hannah goes to college.&lt;br /&gt;
I’ll see you in court.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, “school,” “college,” and “court” are all places that require a distinct set of social behaviors. When you want to refer to the specific building, you might say “the school down the road,” but when you want to refer to the social construct of “school” you would always say that you “go to school down the road.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;concluding-thoughts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concluding thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re a non-native speaker and your mother tongue doesn’t use articles, you’ll almost certainly have difficulty with using articles properly. Invest some time and energy into getting articles right, because incorrect or missing articles will make your writing stick out like a sore thumb. Any native speaker will immediately notice issues with articles and will conclude that the text she’s reading is written poorly. (Even if, by absolute standards of grammatical correctness, that’s not the case.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d also recommend that you, if you have any issues with articles, always do a proof-reading step dedicated specifically to articles. Read your entire document from cover to cover and verify that every single noun has whatever article it may need. It’s generally a good habit to do multiple proof-reading passes. Each pass should check for one specific mistake you tend to make. Just add that one more pass and check for articles. When following this recommendation, I expect that you’ll write documents in which all articles are right all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, I’d still recommend that you write sentences that are largely free of grammatical errors. Just aim first for eliminating errors native speakers wouldn’t make. Then eliminate the errors that native speakers make all the time.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know what the error is you’re just demonstrating my point.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing paragraphs that make sense—the topic and the stress position</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;When you write a scientific article, you should lay out your ideas in such a way that your readers can follow them easily. Every new concept should flow directly from the previous material. Yet more often than not, scientific prose can be difficult to understand. What is going on? Readers expect certain pieces of information in certain positions in a sentence. Satisfy these expectations, and your readers will find your writing clear and convincing. Violate them, and your readers will be confused. All readers expect more or less the same things in the same places. And writers commonly violate these expectations. The two most important expectations readers have concern the kind of material that is presented at the beginning of a sentence, in the &lt;em&gt;topic position,&lt;/em&gt; and at the end, in the &lt;em&gt;stress position&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Here I present my take on how to make the best use of these positions to produce clear and coherent prose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-topic-position&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The topic position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of a sentence defines the topic the sentence will cover. Therefore, we refer to the beginning of a sentence as the &lt;em&gt;topic position.&lt;/em&gt; Your reader expects two things from the beginning of a sentence: (i) to get a sense of where the sentence (or paragraph, section, entire document) is heading; and (ii) to find a connection to something she knows already. The latter of the two expectations is the more important one. Fail to establish a good connection and you will almost certainly lose your reader’s interest and attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the middle of a paragraph, you shouldn’t find it difficult to (re-)establish connection with new every sentence. Just start every sentence with a concept, thing, or person you have already mentioned. At the beginning of a paragraph, however, it can be much harder to get the topic position right. You have to make assumptions about what kinds of concepts, things, or persons your reader will likely be familiar with. Then, you can begin your sentence with one of those things. Don’t start off with something you don’t expect your reader to know. In case of doubt, assume your reader doesn’t know much about anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of poor management of readers’ expectations, consider the opening sentence of an article on an alternative power source:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First proposed more than 30 years ago, systems to harvest utility-scale electrical power from ocean waves have recently been gaining momentum as a viable technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The very first phrase you read, “First proposed more than 30 years ago,” is a participle phrase referring to a noun (“systems to harvest […] power”) that we haven’t seen yet. Thus, as you start reading the sentence, you have absolutely no context into which to place the participle phrase. I suspect you were confused when you read this sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can try to fix this problem by moving the participle phrase to a different location:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Systems to harvest utility-scale electrical power from ocean waves, first proposed more than 30 years ago, have recently been gaining momentum as a viable technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The revised version is better but still has problems. First, by moving the participle phrase, we have created a new problem, the long distance between the subject (“systems to harvest […] power) and the predicate (“have […] been gaining momentum”). I will ignore this problem here because it doesn’t relate to the topic at hand. Second, the sentence has now in its topic position a relatively obscure technology that will not be familiar to the majority of readers. If the article had been written for a trade journal aimed at experts in wave-energy harvesting, this opening would be fine. But the article appeared in the journal &lt;em&gt;Science,&lt;/em&gt; and its diverse audience needs a different starting point. To find the right starting point, we have to determine which part of the sentence will be most familiar to the reader. At the same time, we have to decide which part of the sentence should receive the most emphasis, because the revised sentence should flow naturally from familiar material to important material. I haven’t yet discussed how we can write sentences that emphasize the right piece of information. So let me do this first, and then I’ll come back to this example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-stress-position&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The stress position&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The end of a sentence is perceived as the position of most emphasis. Therefore, we refer to it as the &lt;em&gt;stress position.&lt;/em&gt; The end of a self-contained part of a sentence, such as a clause, will also be perceived as having more emphasis, and we may refer to it as a stress position as well. You achieve maximum impact in your writing when you place the most important part of your sentence into the stress position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following two sentences demonstrate how meaning can change depending on what is put into the stress position:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bears eat salmon in the summer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the summer, bears eat salmon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first sentence emphasizes “summer.” This sentence tells us that while bears eat salmon in the summer they probably don’t do so during the rest of the year.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Further, the sentence doesn’t tell us how much salmon the bears eat. If all you have is this sentence, you don’t know whether bears eat salmon only occasionally or as a staple. The second sentence, on the other hand, emphasizes “salmon.” It tells us that in the summer, bears eat primarily salmon and not something else. Yet this sentence does not make a strong statement about other times of the year. In spring, bears might well be eating the occasional salmon as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seemingly minor differences in word order will make a huge difference in how your sentences are interpreted. Even if your readers don’t notice these differences consciously, they will be affected by them. If you place the least important part of a sentence into the stress position, your readers will probably perceive your sentence as weak and not convincing. For example, does the following sentence convey big news?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul finally won after buying over 100 lottery tickets at the store.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When reading this sentence, you probably wondered what is so special about the store where Paul bought the tickets. Now consider an alternative version:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul had to buy over 100 lottery tickets before he finally won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sentence has two stress positions. The primary one is at the end of the sentence and contains the most important piece of information, “finally won.” The second one is right before the “before” phrase and contains the second-most important piece of information, “over 100 lottery tickets.” The store is not even mentioned, because it doesn’t contribute anything useful to the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s go back to our example from the previous section:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First proposed more than 30 years ago, systems to harvest utility-scale electrical power from ocean waves have recently been gaining momentum as a viable technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sentence has two stress positions. They are occupied by “30 years ago” and by “viable technology.” The phrase “30 years ago” doesn’t seem to deserve much emphasis at all and is thus misplaced. The phrase “viable technology” deserves emphasis. Unfortunately, in this sentence it pushes the energy-harvesting technology into the background. For a reader who has never heard of this technology, that it exists at all might be more important than its increasing viability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I propose the following revision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thirty-year old technology is gaining momentum as a viable source of alternative energy. This technology harvests utility-scale electrical power from ocean waves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This revision places reasonable elements into both topic and stress positions. “A thirty-year old technology” in the topic position of the first sentence prepares the reader to learn something new about an old technology. Any reader with a broad interest in science and technology can relate to this opening. In the stress position of the first sentence, we have “a viable source of alternative energy.” This choice indicates to the reader that the article contains exciting news about alternative energy sources. The topic position of the second sentence repeats the topic of the first sentence, thus establishing connection. In the stress position of the second sentence, the reader learns about the nature of the technology. Somebody who has never before heard of energy harvesting from ocean waves will be surprised to learn that such a technology even exists. The stress position strengthens this experience of surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;making-paragraphs-flow&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Making paragraphs flow&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When students hear about the topic and stress positions for the first time, they sometimes conclude that in a series of sentences the topic position of every sentence should contain what was in the stress position of the previous sentence. This is a misconception. The topic position should contain something that is familiar to the reader. Anything that has been mentioned in previous sentences will be familiar to the reader and can fill the topic position. So how do you decide what to put into the topic position? Think about which concept, thing, or person best defines the context of the sentence you intend to write and is most likely going to be familiar to the reader. That concept, thing, or person should be in the topic position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, multiple subsequent sentences in a paragraph will have the same topic. In this case, the same person, thing, or concept will occupy the topic position of all these sentences. Consider the following two sentences from a news article on a research paper:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shiqiang Wan and his collaborators at the Chinese Academy of Sciences’ Institute of Botany in Beijing set up 36 experimental plots on an Inner Mongolian steppe. They warmed some plots only during the day, others during night-time hours only, and yet others around the clock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both sentences tell us about the research S. Wan and his colleagues carried out. Therefore, both sentences have the researchers in the topic position, once by name and once in the form of a pronoun (“they”).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the stress position of the first sentence, we have “experimental plots on an Inner Mongolian steppe.” Notice that these plots are mentioned again in the next sentence, but neither in the topic nor in the stress position. The stress position of the second sentence contains the various experimental treatments used. These treatments and their resulting consequences are the topic of the entire next paragraph:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plots warmed only at night turned the steppe from a net carbon source to a net carbon sink; the extra warming overnight stimulated respiration rates, boosting the plants’ daytime rate of photosynthesis and so their uptake of carbon dioxide. The effects of separate day- or night-time warming did not add up to equal the effects observed at constantly warmed plots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how in this paragraph, experimental treatments (and their effects) are in the topic position of every sentence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other cases, the topic of each sentence varies as the paragraph unfolds. In this case, the topic positions should be occupied either by something mentioned previously or by something the reader can be expected to be familiar with. Consider this opening paragraph from a &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; Editorial:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the 30th anniversary of the first description of AIDS, there is much progress to celebrate, but still much work to be done. Research breakthroughs continue to improve treatments and to provide evidence for newer, better strategies that could help people to protect themselves from infection and prevent those infected from spreading the virus. Just last month, researchers reported a study […] showing that when patients are treated early it reduces the chance that they will pass the virus on to uninfected partners by 96% […]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the first sentence sets the stage for the entire paragraph: “the 30th anniversary of the first description of AIDS.” In the topic position of the second sentence, the author put “research breakthroughs.” This term implicitly links back to the phrase “much progress to celebrate” in the previous sentence. The third sentence begins with “just last month, researchers reported.” This phrase links back to “research breakthroughs” and prepares the reader to expect that the third sentence will give specific details about one of these breakthroughs. As you can see, each sentence has a different topic, but all sentences are logically connected to each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The concepts of topic and stress positions apply not only to individual sentences but also to larger syntactical units. For example, consider two sentences separated by a semicolon; the end of the first sentence serves as a secondary stress position while the end of the second sentence receives most emphasis. Similarly, the first sentence in a paragraph defines the topic for the entire paragraph, and the last sentence in the paragraph receives the most stress. The concept remains valid for even larger units of discourse. The first paragraph in a section should set the stage for the topic of the section, and, even though there will be many positions of emphasis throughout the section, the last paragraph in the section will hold the most emphasis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;one-paragraph-one-topic&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;One paragraph, one topic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because the material in the topic position defines the context of what is to come, it is important that each unit of discourse address only a single topic. At the level of individual sentences, most writers get this intuitively right. It is unlikely that anybody would write a single sentence about two separate topics. However, at the level of paragraphs, it is surprisingly common to see this principle violated. We have all read paragraphs that seem to have no clear point, or that just go on and on drifting from one topic to the next. In your own writing, make sure that every paragraph talks about exactly one specific topic. If you have written a paragraph and you wonder whether it might talk about more than one topic, split the paragraph in two. Repeat as necessary. Short and clear paragraphs are better than long and rambling ones. Likewise, subsections, sections, and chapters should also talk about a single, clearly defined topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This blog post is my personal take on the material presented in: Gopen and Swan. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.americanscientist.org/issues/pub/the-science-of-scientific-writing&#34;&gt;The Science of Scientific Writing.&lt;/a&gt; American Scientist Nov. 1990.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;J. Scruggs and P. Jacob. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencemag.org/content/323/5918/1176.full&#34;&gt;Harvesting Ocean Wave Energy.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 323:1176-1178, 2009.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note that I don’t actually know anything about the natural history of bears except that they hibernate in winter. I assume they eat salmon in the summer, but I may very well be wrong.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Research Highlight, August 12. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v460/n7257/full/460783c.html&#34;&gt;Soil ecology: As different as day and night.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 460:783, 2009.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Editorial, June 1. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v474/n7349/full/474005a.html&#34;&gt;A big disease with a little name.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 474:5, 2011.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Silence your inner critic</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/22/silence-your-inner-critic/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/22/silence-your-inner-critic/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I wrote two blog posts recently that addressed the widespread issue of writer’s block. In the first, I suggested that &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/16/warm-up-before-you-write&#34;&gt;warming up before writing is a good idea to get you into the zone.&lt;/a&gt; In the second, I argued that &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/18/its-easier-to-write-when-you-know-what-you-want-to-say&#34;&gt;you need to figure out what the story is before you can write productively.&lt;/a&gt; There’s a third element to writing productively. Even if you have figured out your story and have warmed up properly, you may still find yourself staring at a blank page for extended periods of time. If this is the case, you are almost certainly operating with an inner critic that holds you back the moment you want to commit words to paper. You need to silence your inner critic to write effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I discuss the inner critic in more detail, I want to frame this discussion within the concept of &lt;em&gt;writing modes.&lt;/em&gt; It is important to realize that there are two distinct writing modes, &lt;em&gt;contents generation&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;copy-editing.&lt;/em&gt; They have distinct goals, and it is best to not muddle the waters between them. Every time you sit in front of a word processor, you should know exactly which mode you’re operating under. If I asked you “Sally, are you generating content or are you copy-editing?” you should answer immediately, without hesitation.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In the next two paragraphs I give a brief description of each of these two writing modes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contents generation.&lt;/strong&gt; The sole purpose of contents generation is to get words onto the page. As quickly as possible, and as many words as possible. During contents generation, you should not worry too much about word choice, grammar, or even connection between sentences. Just create material to copy-edit later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Copy-editing.&lt;/strong&gt; The purpose of copy-editing is to polish your text. Fix all the grammatical mistakes you made. Make sure each sentence connects properly to the previous one. Fix all the awkward word choices you have made and eliminate all colloquialisms. Verify all punctuation. Copy-editing can be hard, and it is usually slow. I sometimes agonize 5–10 minutes over a single sentence I need to fix. Importantly, however, copy-editing is not about contents generation. As you copy-edit, you only work with the material you already have. You don’t try to add entire paragraphs of new material.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The inner critic is that inner voice that wants you to copy edit as you’re trying to generate contents. You have in your mind a picture of all these sentences you need to say, but the moment you try to commit them to paper the inner critic comes along and says: “Well, that doesn’t sound too smart. And it doesn’t connect to what you’ve written before. And anyway, who uses words like ‘fun’ in formal writing?” And there you go, switching from contents generation to copy-editing, trying to fix this one sentence you need to write before you can proceed to the next.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem with trying to copy-edit as you’re generating contents is that you’re constantly keeping yourself from getting into the zone where writing just flows effortlessly. This severely limits your overall productivity. You might think that it comes out the same either way, since yes you’re generating slower but you’re also writing higher-quality sentences. Unfortunately, that’s usually not the case. The secret about writing in the zone is that most sentences are spectacularly useful. With just a little copy-editing, they can generally be brought into a sufficiently decent shape that they can be published. The carefully copy-edited sentences your inner critic makes you write, on the other hand, may be beautiful by themselves but they tend to be poorly connected with their surrounding context. Because these sentences were not written quickly, your mind started to wander from topic to topic as you were writing, and hence the sentences don’t hang together. The latter sentences seem to be telling a totally different story than the earlier sentences. To fix this mess, you’ll need more copy-editing than you would have needed had you written quickly in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do you silence your inner critic? You just ignore it. When you know that you’re in contents generation mode, you cannot afford staring at blank paper for extended periods of time. Any time you detect yourself doing so, just write down the first sentence that comes to mind and then move on. Remember, you can always go back and copy-edit. In fact, you should do so anyway.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When you’re in contents-generation mode, get comfortable with writing half-baked sentences. Just write it down how it is on your mind. If you can’t find the right word, write “that thing.” If you can’t find the correct phrasing, write a sentence that describes the actual sentence that should be there instead, such as “here I need to place a sentence that explains how the inner critic prevents me from writing effectively.” If you want, you can mark the sentence in italics or in a different color to indicate that it urgently needs revision. Either way, do everything you can to generate contents and to not be stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you a frame of reference: It usually takes me about an hour to generate all the contents for a typical blog post such as this one and then another hour to copy-edit it. In practice, though, I don’t write the whole post before I do any copy-editing. I usually write about a paragraph, copy-edit it, write another paragraph, copy-edit that one, and so on. At the end, I copy-edit the whole post a couple more times before I publish it. During copy-editing, I end up modifying maybe 10% of the text. So you can see that the amount of writing I actually do during copy-editing is minimal compared to the amount of writing done during contents generation. Also, keep in mind that I don’t copy-edit posts on my blog as much as I would any formal writing. I want a raw and direct voice on my blog, more like a conversation than like formal writing, and so I leave copy-editing to a minimum. For example, this post contains a few instances of a dangling “this”—as in “This severely limits your overall productivity”—that I would edit out if this were a scientific paper and not a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your name is not Sally it’s Ok to hesitate a bit and wonder who I might be talking to.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Please promise me that you won’t ever hand over your writing to anybody else unless you have gone through at least one serious round of copy-editing &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; you had generated all the contents.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It’s easier to write when you know what you want to say</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/18/its-easier-to-write-when-you-know-what-you-want-to-say/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/18/its-easier-to-write-when-you-know-what-you-want-to-say/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s easier to write when you know what you want to say. “Duh,” you may say, “I could have told you that, Claus.” Yes, it’s a pretty obvious statement. But I wouldn’t dismiss its value so easily. When you’re trying to write something, and you get stuck, you need to know why you’re stuck. There may be two reasons: First, you can be stuck because you don’t know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; you want to say. Second, you can be stuck because even though you do know what you want to say, you don’t know &lt;em&gt;how to say it.&lt;/em&gt; Those two are very distinct scenarios, and they require different courses of action. Can you tell when you find yourself in either? And if so, do you know how to deal with the situation effectively?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;how-to-tell&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to tell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may require some experience and careful introspection to figure out which scenario you’re in. However, there are a few tell-tale signs. For example, do you have a clear idea of what the overarching story is? And if not, do you at least know exactly what the specific paragraph is about that you’re presently writing? I find that it happens quite frequently to me that I do know exactly what the story is, and I even know exactly what ideas I want to express in the present paragraph, and yet I can’t get the right sentences together. That’s a scenario of not knowing how to say it. On the flip side, if you’re not clear on the overarching story, and if you couldn’t express in a single, short sentence what the current paragraph is about, then you’re still at the stage where you don’t know what to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, I would like to take a moment to explain the idea of “having a story.” Every time you write something, there needs to be a story. Even if you’re writing the most boring review article on the latest changes in accounting law, your article needs to have a story line. There needs to be a clear beginning, a clear development, and a clear end. If you can’t express the story of the piece you’re writing in a sentence or two, you probably haven’t figured out yet what it actually is that you want to say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-to-do-when-you-dont-know-what-to-say&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do when you don’t know &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to say&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more difficult case arises when you don’t know what to say. The action that needs to be taken is relatively straightforward, however. If you don’t know what to say, if you don’t have a story yet, then you should probably not be writing at this time. Instead, you should be working on developing a story. There are many techniques, such as freewriting, mind-mapping, outlining, talking to friends, taking psychedelic mushrooms. (On further reflection, strike the latter one.) Some of these activities involve you putting words on paper, others don’t. Importantly, none of them involve you writing publication-quality prose. So don’t even try. If you don’t have a story, don’t waste your time trying to write one down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s one exception to this advice: Sometimes you don’t know the overarching story but you do have an idea what the specific paragraph or subsection should be about. In this case, it’s fine to write just that part of the text without worrying about the overall story. To give a concrete example, I think it’s fine to &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/8/26/when-should-you-stop-doing-science-and-start-writing-a-paper&#34;&gt;start writing up the results of a scientific study before the study is even completed.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;what-to-do-when-you-dont-know-how-to-say-it&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What to do when you don’t know &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to say it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re only dealing with a problem of not knowing how to best say something, the situation is much easier to resolve. If you know what you want to say in principle, you just have to say it whichever way it comes out. You derive absolutely no benefit from staring at a blank page and agonizing over a single word or a single sentence. It’s much better to just write something down, no matter how awful, and move on. You can always come back later and fix the problematic sentence, after you’ve written all of the surrounding text. I often find that when I revisit the problematic sentence later on, what I wrote the first time round isn’t so awful after all, or even if it is, I can easily find an appropriate fix.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, I have now made it a habit that whenever I find myself staring at a blank page for more than a few minutes, I force myself to write down the first thing that comes to my mind, and then I move on. It has made a big difference in my overall writing output and my sense of happiness while writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Warm up before you write</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/16/2013-09-16-warm-up-before-you-write/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/16/2013-09-16-warm-up-before-you-write/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In most pursuits of an artistic or physical nature, warming up is standard operating procedure. An opera singer wouldn’t go out on stage without first singing some arias in the dressing room. An olympic gymnast doesn’t step on the balance beam without some serious stretching, as well as a dry-run of her routine on the ground. A sprinter will do some light jogs, stretches, and maybe jumping jacks before the big race. But writers routinely fire up the word processor (or, like in the olden days, take out pen and paper) and attempt to write award-winning prose without any sort of warm up. I don’t think that’s very smart. I believe warming up is as important for writing as it is for singing, gymnastics, or track-and-field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do your best writing when you’re in the zone, when the words just flow out of your mind onto the paper. When you’re writing without pause for an hour or more, and then, when you finally take a break and look at what you’ve just done, you see that you’ve finished two pages of excellent, coherent material. How often do you, my reader, experience this state of flow? If this is your normal state of writing, then keep doing what you’re doing, you’re doing fine. My experience, though, from having talked to numerous students, and having taught a writing class for a couple of semesters, is that most people do not describe their regular writing experience in those terms. Much more common descriptions are: “I agonize over every word.” “I stare at a blank page/screen for hours.” “I write a sentence, only to immediately delete it and write it again, over and over.” “Writing is like drawing blood with a blunt needle.” If these latter sentences describe your experience while writing, then try to incorporate some warm-up exercises into your writing routine.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I bet you it’s going to help.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you warm up? It’s easy. Just take an empty sheet of paper and a pen (or open a new document on your computer) and write down any thought that comes to your mind, for about 10-15 minutes. In this exercise, it doesn’t matter so much that you formulate complete sentences, or anything coherent at all. The only thing that matters is that you put words on paper, period. You might think: “But what if I have nothing to say? What if I run out of ideas?” The truth is your mind is never completely empty. However, there may be thoughts you may feel uncomfortable putting on paper, thoughts that are too incoherent, too embarrassing, too silly, to inappropriate. For the purpose of the warm-up, none of this matters. Just write it down anyway. You can always plan to burn the piece of paper afterwards, or to close the document without saving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you truly don’t know what to write, just write that. It is fine to just write “I really have no idea what to write now. I’m supposed to write without pause, but my mind is empty. What can I write when I have nothing to write? I guess I have to write nothing then. Nothing is also words, though. Just words that say nothing.” and so on. &lt;strong&gt;The one thing you must not do is stop.&lt;/strong&gt; The goal of the exercise is to become familiar with the state of flow while writing. The more you experience the flow when writing inconsequential things, the more you’ll be able to recreate the same experience while writing something useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does it matter whether you warm up on a computer or with pen and paper? It depends on your typing and thinking speed. I find that I can type faster than I can think. The result is that when I write on a computer, my hands frequently have to wait for my brain to catch up. This is not good for flow. If I write in longhand on paper, by contrast, my writing is slower than my thinking, and I never have to interrupt the constant flow of writing. I think that’s the better approach. It is much easier to reach a state of flow if you’re engaging in an activity that has absolutely no interruption. One that just hums along for 15-20 minutes. However, if you’re a slower typist, or if you can think faster than I can, then warming up on a computer may work for you. Also, if you’re less than 30 years old, you may never have written much in longhand in the first place, and doing so may feel so awkward that it disrupts the flow. I would say try it out and see what works best for you. There isn’t necessarily a one-size-fits-all solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re already warming up before writing, or if you are going to try it out after reading about it here, please share your experience with me in the comments. I’d like to hear about how warming up for writing works for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a writing routine, that’s a serious issue in itself. A topic for another post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Warming-up by itself may not be sufficient, if you’re a severe case. There are other important techniques, such as silencing your inner critic. I’ll blog about that at some point in the future.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a scientific paper in four easy steps</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/29/writing-a-scientific-paper-in-four-easy-steps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/29/writing-a-scientific-paper-in-four-easy-steps/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Writing is hard. But writing a scientific paper? Much less so. That’s because nearly all scientific papers follow a simple, four-section outline: Introduction, Methods, Results, Discussion. Just put the required information into those four sections and you’re done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Introduction sets the stage. It explains the scientific question, why the question is interesting, and what you have done to address the question. Many papers have never-ending Introductions, but frankly I doubt anybody actually wants to read a paper with a long Introduction. In my mind, an introduction requires only three paragraphs: A first paragraph introducing the broad topic and explaining why it is interesting. A second paragraph describing a specific gap in knowledge or unsolved problem. And a third paragraph explaining how your work attempts to close the gap or solve the problem. Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The methods need to describe in detail what experiments you have done, what analyses you carried out, and so on. There’s little to be said about Methods, other than that most Methods are actually too short. It’s a lot of work to describe everything you’ve done in exquisite detail, so most people get lazy at some point and leave something out. I’d encourage you to be as detailed as possible with your Methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of actually writing and structuring the methods, it’s a good idea to group related methods into subsections. An example could be: Experimental protocol; Sequencing; Data analysis; Modeling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Results are the heart of the paper. There’s no research paper without Results. I like to approach Results from the figures and tables. Think about which figures and tables you want to present, then write a paragraph for each. Each paragraph should start with a brief explanation of what you did and why, and then it should present the actual results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a Results paragraph could read:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To determine whether lions can thrive on a vegetarian diet, we raised 10 captive-bred lion cubs on tofu burgers. As control, we raised a second group of 10 cubs on raw beef. We monitored body weight and size, activity level, fur shininess, and health of each cub for a time period of three months. We found that vegetarian-raised cubs grew slower and had a lower overall weight increase over three months (t-test, &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.002). Surprisingly, diet did not affect fur shininess (t-test, &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt; = 0.15).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice how the first three sentences describe the question and briefly outline the experiment, while the subsequent two sentences describe the actual results. The next following paragraph in the Results should now raise another question and answer it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;discussion&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Discussion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Discussion will generally need at least 4-5 paragraphs, and will likely grow a few paragraphs after you have addressed the referee reports. While the Discussion is probably the hardest part to write, there’s a simple structure to a typical Discussion that makes things easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first paragraph in the Discussion should summarize the Results. Most readers will read the Abstract, maybe the Introduction, and then the Discussion. Write the Discussion as if it were the first thing your readers saw.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then you need 2-3 paragraphs placing your results into a broader context. What does your work mean for the major question described in the Introduction? Also, how does your work relate to other work in the field? What specifically are the similarities and differences?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you need at least 1-2 paragraphs pointing out some potential drawbacks of your work. Every work has potential drawbacks, or at least limiting assumptions. List specific conditions under which your conclusions might be invalid, or assumptions you made that may not be true. As reviewers read your paper, they will assemble in their mind a list of potential drawbacks they’re going to call you out on. To the extent that you’ve already addressed their concerns in your manuscript, you’ll have an easier time in review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, and this is somewhat optional, you can write another paragraph that summarizes all your findings once more. Many papers have such a concluding paragraph, but it can feel redundant if you opened the Discussion with a strong summary paragraph, in particular if your Discussion isn’t that long. I’d say use good judgement on whether you need the closing paragraph or not. In case of doubt, write it, and see how the paper flows with or without this paragraph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;results-methods-discussion-introduction&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Results, Methods, Discussion, Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the order of the sections in the paper is going to be Introduction, Methods, Results, Discussion (or possibly Introduction, Results, Discussion, Methods), you shouldn’t write the paper in that order. That would be backwards. There’s no paper without Results, therefore you should write Results first, possibly in parallel with Methods. Once you have Results and Methods, you can start writing the Discussion. Only once you have a pretty good draft of Results through Discussion should you start working on the Introduction. If the Introduction is the last major section that is missing, it will write itself, I promise. In particular if you keep it to three paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven’t talked about the abstract yet. The abstract should be a mix of the first two paragraphs of the Introduction and the first paragraph of the Discussion. Write the abstract at the very end, when everything else is done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;length&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Length&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no minimum length to a scientific paper. In general, I’d say scientists are more likely to write papers that are too long than papers that are too short. I would recommend not to worry about insufficient length at all (but do worry about excessive length). If you’ve got all the elements I’ve discussed here, and your paper is 3 pages long, great. Send it out! Also, 3-6 figures and tables total is a good number. If you’re way beyond 10, you need to cut or move stuff to the supplement. A paper that is too long will not be read, regardless of how good it is. Honestly. Just cut it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When should you stop doing science and start writing a paper?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/26/when-should-you-stop-doing-science-and-start-writing-a-paper/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/26/when-should-you-stop-doing-science-and-start-writing-a-paper/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In my experience, most graduate students and many postdocs think of science as a two-step process: First, you do science. You do experiments, collect data, write code, carry out statistical analyses. Then, once you’re done doing science, you sit down and write up your results for publication. Within this mental model, an important question arises: How do you know that you have done enough science? When should you stop collecting data and start writing a paper?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve seen plenty of graduate students struggle with getting papers out because they can’t convince themselves that they have done enough science and are ready to start writing. There’s always another experiment to be done, another analysis to be run. In my opinion, the fundamental issue here is not that these students have difficulty judging when they have done sufficient work. The real issue is that the mental model of science as a two-step process is flawed. Realistically, you will never have done so much science that there is nothing else to do. And at the same time, even if you think you have a complete story, you almost never do. Anybody who has written at least a few papers will have experienced the situation where, as you’re making your case for one conclusion or another, you realize that you could make this case that much stronger with another experiment, or at least another analysis. What happens then is that you go back into the lab, do the work, and subsequently use the additional results to write an improved manuscript draft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, in my mind, the question “when should you stop doing science and start writing a paper” is ill-conceived. Doing science and writing about it are two sides of the same coin. They should happen at the same time. In my mind, there is an obvious simpler question, and it has a simple answer. The simpler question is “when should you start writing a paper?” The answer to this question, in my mind, is “as soon as you have at least one result.” As soon as you have a result, you can write it up. Make a figure, add a caption, write an explanatory paragraph or two, and put it into a document section titled “Results.” Place a brief outline of the methods used into an accompanying section titled “Methods.” As you keep doing more science, keep adding your results to the document, and see how the story unfolds. If there are obvious gaps, think about the work you need to do to fill them. Once you think that you have a reasonable story, all you have to do is add an introduction and a discussion and you’re done writing your paper. Submit.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why not write a book?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/17/a-blog-seriously/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/17/a-blog-seriously/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I’ve always wanted to write a book. For years, I have considered possible topics, thought about detailed contents, even drafted a first chapter or two. Yet I have never followed through. I’m right there with the millions of people who fantasize about being a great author but never do anything about it. However, unlike most of these people, I actually am an author. Writing is a major part of my job. I have published thousands of pages, mostly in the form of scientific papers. I have written winning grant proposals. I have edited journal articles and conference proceedings. I have even taught university-level classes on how to be a successful writer. Surely, if I seriously wanted to write a book, I could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why haven’t I? The simple truth is that I have a short attention span and get bored easily. I would find it quite difficult to stay engaged with a single topic for as long as it would take to write the book. Chances are, I’d write a few chapters and then I’d lose interest. At that point, there’d be two possibilities: (i) I abandon the project. (ii) I push through regardless. Of course, of those two possibilities, only the latter would result in a finished book. And the latter possibility is also the much more unpleasant one. At some point in my life, I may still embark on this book project, but for now I admit defeat. I have yet to find a book idea for which pushing through regardless seems worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here I am. I enjoy writing. I enjoy writing things other than just scientific papers. In my humble opinion, I’m quite good at writing, or at least not entirely terrible. So let’s try this blogging thing. Maybe my short attention span is better matched to blogging than to writing books. I know I can stay focused for long enough to complete one blog post, and maybe even a series of blog posts about the same topic. Who knows, over time I might even collect enough material on this blog that eventually I can collate parts of it into a coherent book of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So with this post, I open this blog. I make no promises about specific topics I’ll blog about, nor about post frequency or longevity of this project. I might be too lazy to update this blog on a regular schedule. I might get bored of blogging entirely, regardless of subject matter. Either way, for now I’ll try this out and see where it goes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
