<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Markdown on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Markdown/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Markdown on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Markdown/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Writing a blogdown post for the ages</title>
      <link>/blog/2020/09/08/a-blogdown-post-for-the-ages/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2020/09/08/a-blogdown-post-for-the-ages/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The R package &lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; has become a widely popular solution to setting up personal blogs. It makes it super easy to set up quite elaborate websites, and to write posts that contain R code, generated output and figures, footnotes, figure references, and math.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; However, one problem with blogdown is that it likes to re-knit &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; files.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This may be fine if you’re just starting out with your site or if your posts generally don’t contain any sophisticated R code, but in a long-standing blog you’ll eventually run into trouble. First, re-knitting hundreds of posts may be quite slow. And second, if you’ve got a bunch of old posts chances are some will not knit anymore, and then you may have got a serious problem with no simple solution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This problem has been recognized for a while, and the proposed solution is usually to knit only on demand. See e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;https://yutani.rbind.io/post/2017-10-25-blogdown-custom/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The experimental &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/r-lib/hugodown&#34;&gt;hugodown package&lt;/a&gt; likewise aims to limit any unnecessary re-knitting. Here, I’m taking a different approach. My perspective is that I want to be able to re-knit any time without worrying that I’ll destroy anything of value, and I also want to be able to add code and output to posts containing prior code that doesn’t run anymore today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My approach is to copy the knitted markdown code and output back into the &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; file. This requires some amount of manual work, but it’s not that bad, and I value the benefits I get from this approach. Maybe at some point somebody will write a package that can automate this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do not necessarily recommend the approach I’m taking here. This post is mostly for my own purposes, so I can retrace my steps in the future. If you want to see the source code resulting from this process, you can check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/clauswilke/clauswilke.github.io/blob/master/content/blog/2020-09-08-a-blogdown-post-for-the-ages/index.Rmd&#34;&gt;source for this post&lt;/a&gt; on github.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To provide an example scenario, I include here one chunk of R code that generates a figure. This code has various features that will likely generate issues in the future or in a blog with many posts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It depends on a bunch of packages, including one only available from github.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It uses various fonts that need to be installed locally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is slow to render.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it is critical that we can capture the output and don’t ever have to re-render it again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(cowplot)
library(colorspace)
library(sf) 
library(ggtext)

# attach data set, requires practicalgg package
# remotes::install_github(&amp;quot;wilkelab/practicalgg&amp;quot;)
data(texas_income, package = &amp;quot;practicalgg&amp;quot;)

ggplot(texas_income, aes(fill = estimate)) + 
  geom_sf(color = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;) +
  coord_sf(xlim = c(538250, 2125629), crs = 3083) +
  scale_fill_continuous_sequential(
    palette = &amp;quot;Blues&amp;quot;, rev = TRUE,
    na.value = &amp;quot;grey60&amp;quot;,
    name = &amp;quot;annual median income (USD)&amp;quot;,
    limits = c(18000, 90000),
    breaks = 20000*c(1:4),
    labels = c(&amp;quot;$20,000&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;$40,000&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;$60,000&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;$80,000&amp;quot;),
    guide = guide_colorbar(
      direction = &amp;quot;horizontal&amp;quot;,
      label.position = &amp;quot;bottom&amp;quot;,
      title.position = &amp;quot;top&amp;quot;,
      barwidth = grid::unit(3.0, &amp;quot;in&amp;quot;),
      barheight = grid::unit(0.2, &amp;quot;in&amp;quot;)
    )
  ) +
  labs(caption = &amp;quot;
&amp;lt;span style=&amp;#39;font-family: \&amp;quot;Font Awesome 5 Brands\&amp;quot;&amp;#39;&amp;gt;&amp;amp;#xf099;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
@clauswilke&amp;lt;br&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;span style=&amp;#39;font-family: \&amp;quot;Font Awesome 5 Free Solid\&amp;quot;&amp;#39;&amp;gt;&amp;amp;#xf781;&amp;lt;/span&amp;gt;
clauswilke.com
&amp;quot;) +
  theme_map(12, font_family = &amp;quot;Myriad Pro&amp;quot;) +
  theme(
    legend.title.align = 0.5,
    legend.text.align = 0.5,
    legend.justification = c(0, 0),
    legend.position = c(0.02, 0.1),
    plot.caption = element_markdown()
  )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:map-Texas-income&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;figure-html/map-Texas-income-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Median annual income in Texas counties. Figure redrawn from: Wilke (2019) Fundamentals of Data Visualization, Chapter 4.&#34; width=&#34;576&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Median annual income in Texas counties. Figure redrawn from: Wilke (2019) Fundamentals of Data Visualization, &lt;a href=&#34;https://clauswilke.com/dataviz/color-basics.html&#34;&gt;Chapter 4.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I’ll provide the exact recipe I follow to capture the output from such code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the top of your &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; file, add an R chunk containing the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r echo = FALSE}
knitr::opts_chunk$set(fig.retina = 2)
```&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will ensure that figures are rendered in high quality. Set &lt;code&gt;echo = FALSE&lt;/code&gt; for this chunk so the code isn’t included in the rendered output.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stop the blogdown server with &lt;code&gt;blogdown::stop_server()&lt;/code&gt;. We don’t want the server to try to create blog posts out of the intermediate files we’ll be creating.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the following to the yaml section of your post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;output:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;html_document:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;keep_md: yes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to use bookdown-style automated figure references, use this snippet instead:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;output:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;bookdown::html_document2:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;keep_md: yes
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This requires the bookdown package to be installed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Knit your post. You will end up with a new file &lt;code&gt;index.md&lt;/code&gt; and a new folder called &lt;code&gt;index_files&lt;/code&gt;. The former contains the markdown code that knitr has generated and the latter contains any generated figures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now you want to copy the generated code and output chunks from &lt;code&gt;index.md&lt;/code&gt; back into &lt;code&gt;index.Rmd&lt;/code&gt;. For each code chunk in your &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; file, there will be one or more markdown chunks, which are fenced with &lt;code&gt;```r ...```&lt;/code&gt;. There will also be markdown or HTML code to include any generated figures. Place all of this material after the respective code chunk from which it originated, but &lt;strong&gt;do not delete&lt;/strong&gt; the original code chunk. We want to keep the original code chunks around in case we do want to re-run some of the R code again in the future, e.g. if the post needs an update.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Next, you need to move the generated figures into a safe location. This ensures that they won’t be deleted when blogdown rebuilds the site the next time. I simply move the folder &lt;code&gt;index_files/figure-html&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;figure-html&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Edit figure links to reflect the move from the previous step. Figure links may be included either as markdown links, such as &lt;code&gt;![](index_files/figure-html/map-Texas-income-1.png)&lt;/code&gt;, or as html links, such as &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;img src=&#34;/blog/2020-09-08-a-blogdown-post-for-the-ages/index_files/figure-html/map-Texas-income-1.png&#34; ...&lt;/code&gt;. Which is the case depends on the exact chunk options you used to generate the figure. In either case, delete &lt;code&gt;index_files/&lt;/code&gt; from all figure links.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Delete the file &lt;code&gt;index.md&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remove or comment out the &lt;code&gt;output:&lt;/code&gt; block you added under step 3.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Add the following line to the code chunk added under step 1:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;knitr::opts_chunk$set(echo = FALSE, eval = FALSE)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This turns off all the R Markdown chunks in your post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Restart the blogdown server with &lt;code&gt;blogdown::serve_site()&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This may seem like a lot of steps and a lot of fiddling, but it’s really not that bad once you get the hang of it. Most blog posts, even elaborate ones, don’t have that many code chunks or figures, and manually copying and adjusting the markdown code takes much less time than writing the blog post in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the future, if you need to update your post, you can either re-run all code by commenting out the line you added in step 10, or you can selectively turn on individual R chunks by setting their &lt;code&gt;echo&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;eval&lt;/code&gt; options to &lt;code&gt;TRUE&lt;/code&gt;. Then you repeat steps 1 through 11, but copying only whichever output needs to be newly copied over. At the end make sure you disable all R chunks once again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This post has one figure, Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:map-Texas-income&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;. It also has one equation, &lt;span class=&#34;math inline&#34;&gt;\(a^2 + b^2 = c^2\)&lt;/span&gt;. The equation serves no purpose here.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Throughout, I’m assuming you’re using &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt; files. Everything I say should be valid for &lt;code&gt;.Rmarkdown&lt;/code&gt; as well, though I haven’t tested this.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Post-publication review of the PLOS ONE paper comparing MS Word and LaTeX: How not to compare document preparation</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/12/27/post-publication-review-of-the-plos-one-paper-comparing-ms-word-and-latex-how-not-to-compare-document-preparation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/12/27/post-publication-review-of-the-plos-one-paper-comparing-ms-word-and-latex-how-not-to-compare-document-preparation/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PLOS ONE just published a paper comparing MS Word with LaTeX, which argues that LaTeX has little benefits over MS Word and should not be allowed by scientific journals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knauff M, Nejasmic J (2014) &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0115069&#34;&gt;An Efficiency Comparison of Document Preparation Systems Used in Academic Research and Development.&lt;/a&gt; PLoS ONE 9(12): e115069.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my mind, this paper makes extremely strong claims based on a rather flawed and thin analysis. I am sure there are useful things to be said about MS Word vs. LaTeX. However, this paper does not make much of a contribution to this question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you some background: I have been using LaTeX for over 20 years, I have written tens of thousands of pages with LaTeX, and I am extremely familiar with its pros and cons. I am also using MS Word on a regular basis, and I regularly make the choice between using LaTeX or MS Word, on a document-by-document case. There are documents I’d rather write in LaTeX, and there are other documents I’d rather write in MS Word. There are also documents (increasingly many, in fact) for which I prefer entirely different approaches, such as Markdown. With that said, let me list the main objections I have to the Knauff and Nejasmic paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;apples-and-oranges&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apples and oranges&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire premise of the paper is flawed: MS Word is a text editor, LaTeX is a file format. Those two things are inherently not comparable. There is no technical reason why MS Word cannot save documents to LaTeX, only the creators of MS Word chose not to implement this option. A simple work-around exists, however: Save the document as .docx and convert it to LaTeX with &lt;a href=&#34;https://pandoc.org/&#34;&gt;pandoc&lt;/a&gt;. Incidentally, you can also go the other way round, write the document in LaTeX and convert to .docx. Fundamentally, file formats describing the same kind of data can be converted into each other. Therefore, people should be allowed to use the software and file formats they prefer (within reason, and preferably non-proprietary ones). Computers can sort out the differences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;a-rigged-comparison&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;A rigged comparison&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The comparison the authors set up, the reproduction of three relatively simple, one-page documents, is entirely artificial and rigged to favor MS Word. This is particularly the case (and this is not really explained well in the paper) if the LaTeX users were tasked to reproduce the visual layout of the documents. LaTeX is meant to separate contents from layout, and the people who use it regularly tend to value that separation. However, this separation implies that it can sometimes be a bit difficult to achieve a particular physical layout. The correct, LaTeX way to solve this problem would be to prepare an appropriate style file. Yet I doubt the users in this test were given such a style file for the &lt;em&gt;continuous text&lt;/em&gt; example (which poses some tricky formatting issues with the title, author list, and address line).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anybody who has experience with both systems, it would be trivial to set up examples where MS Word utterly fails and LaTeX shines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Set up 50 numbered equations, refer to them throughout the text, then change the equation order.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have figures and their captions float to appropriate locations at the top or bottom of pages.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Change the order of figures in a document and fix all references to those figures.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;its-not-surprising-that-latex-users-are-highly-satisfied&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It’s not surprising that LaTeX users are highly satisfied&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the paper, the authors state (somewhat surprised, it seems to me) that LaTeX users are highly satisfied with their document preparation software. The authors seem to have no explanation for this observation, other than cognitive dissonance. In effect, the authors are saying that LaTeX is so awful that the only way to use it regularly is to convince yourself it is great even though it is not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a simple alternative explanation, though: Even though LaTeX can be cumbersome and has its quirks, LaTeX is highly predictable. Once you have figured out how something works, it always works that way. LaTeX never crashes. Documents don’t suddenly change layout or font. Tables don’t jump around. By contrast, none of this can be said about MS Word. Everybody who uses MS Word knows that it sometimes does things that simply can’t be explained. Things that should work don’t. Formatting changes randomly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my own experience, to produce a final document, I fiddle around about as much with MS Word as I do with LaTeX, only that the issues with LaTeX are usually the same three predictable things (proper formatting of the cover page, some table issues, getting all the references into BibTeX). By contrast, with MS Word I always fight against some random, unexplainable stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;state-of-the-art-in-document-preparation&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;State of the art in document preparation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I find most amazing about the Knauff and Nejasmic paper, considering that it is a study on document preparation, is that the authors seem to be completely out of touch with the state-of-the-art developments in that field. The authors barely even mention the important distinction between document structure and document layout, and they don’t discuss at all why one might want to separate the two. They also don’t consider automatic document conversions for different media (e.g. web versus print). Finally, they don’t discuss the increasingly important issue, at least for scientific documents, of integrating the text of a paper with the code used for data analysis and figure generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there is plenty of room for improvement over LaTeX when it comes to document preparation. Most heavy LaTeX users would agree that the language can be cumbersome, and I haven’t met anybody who wouldn’t rather not type out all the LaTeX commands required to prepare a finished document. Extensive efforts are currently underway to address these and other issues, but these efforts are not happening in the world of MS Word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most exciting current developments, in my mind, are happening with &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&#34;&gt;Markdown.&lt;/a&gt; Markdown is an extremely simplified markup language that can be learned in half an hour or less. Markdown documents can be read easily in their source form (unlike LaTeX documents), and they can also be converted into HTML or PDF documents. (The PDF conversion usually goes via LaTeX as intermediate.) Moreover, through extensions such as &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34;&gt;R Markdown,&lt;/a&gt; one can easily combine the document text, the code for data analysis and figure preparation, and the final figures, all in a single file. The result is a publication-quality document that is easy to produce, self contained, and allows for complete reproducibility of the analysis and figure generation. I bet that if the comparison in the PLOS ONE paper had been MS Word vs. LaTeX vs. Markdown, Markdown would have won hands down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;does-any-of-this-matter&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Does any of this matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why quibble over file formats and editors at all? As I said in the beginning, I use various tools, depending on the task at hand. As long as we can all agree that there are different use cases and that people can make informed decisions on which tool to use when, I’m fine. However, this is where the authors of the PLOS ONE paper go off the deep end. After presenting their relatively thin, somewhat rigged, and definitely not comprehensive comparison of one text editor to one file format, they then make incredibly strong claims, including that LaTeX users may be suffering from cognitive dissonance and that vast amounts of money could be saved if people were forced to switch over from LaTeX to MS Word. These statements are simply not warranted, they do not follow logically from the analysis presented, and they entirely disregard that the future of scientific document preparation may lay elsewhere (e.g., Markdown). If there is one thing this paper doesn’t make is a strong argument &lt;em&gt;in favor&lt;/em&gt; of MS Word, and we must be careful not to allow journal editors or other policy makers to use arguments such as the ones made in this paper to force us into a single mode of document preparation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Markdown, the easiest and most elegant approach to writing about data analysis with R</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/04/r-markdown-the-easiest-and-most-elegant-approach-to-writing-about-data-analysis-with-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/04/r-markdown-the-easiest-and-most-elegant-approach-to-writing-about-data-analysis-with-r/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This weekend, I finally spent some time learning &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;R Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. I had been aware of its existence for a while, but I had never bothered to check it out. What a mistake. R Markdown rocks! It&amp;rsquo;s hands down the easiest and most elegant method to creating rich documents that contain data analysis, figures, mathematical formulas, and text. And it&amp;rsquo;s super easy to learn. I wager that anybody who has RStudio installed can create a useful document in 30 minutes or less. So if you use R, and you&amp;rsquo;ve never used R Markdown, give it a try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R Markdown provides a literate programming platform for the R language. Literate programming, &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;invented by Donald Knuth,&lt;/a&gt; allows users to write both a program and a document describing the program, at the same time. In the case of R, this means that you can write a document that contains R code, the output that is generated when the R code is run (including graphs), and prose describing the R code and its output. To give you an example, I started writing a tutorial for R&amp;rsquo;s ggplot2 library this weekend, and the original R Markdown file as well as the HTML output generated from that file are &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/wilkelab/ggplot2_cookbook/blob/master/README.md&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does the word &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; stand for? &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; is a minimalist approach to writing strutured documents. It consists of plain text with a few simple directives to mark sections, turn text bold or italics, or insert quotes. If you have ever edited a wikipedia article, you have used Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you an example, this is Markdown text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;We can make text **bold**, *italics*, or `look like code.`
We can also insert links, [e.g. to wikipedia,](http://www.wikipedia.org/)
we can quote things:  

&amp;gt; It is time to eat &amp;amp;#8212; Hungry John

or make lists:

1. Item 1
2. Item 2
3. Item 3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be rendered like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can make text &lt;strong&gt;bold&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;em&gt;italics&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;code&gt;look like code.&lt;/code&gt; We can also insert links, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wikipedia.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;e.g. to wikipedia,&lt;/a&gt; we can quote things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is time to eat &amp;#8212; Hungry John&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or make lists:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Item 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R Markdown works the same, only that it adds the option to insert R code  blocks. An R code block could look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;```{r}  
# place R code here, e.g. to make a plot:  
library(ggplot2)  
x &amp;lt;- 1:10; y &amp;lt;- x^2  
qplot(x, y)  
```
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you convert the R Markdown file to HTML, the R code gets executed, the R output captured and inserted into the document, and you&amp;rsquo;ve got everything nicely together, with very little work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create an R Markdown document in RStudio, all you have to do is go to &lt;code&gt;File&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;New File&lt;/code&gt;, and then select &lt;code&gt;R Markdown&lt;/code&gt;. Accept the default settings, and R Studio will generate a new R Markdown file with a few lines of example content. To convert the file into HTML, simply click on the &amp;ldquo;Knit HTML&amp;rdquo; button. If you have previously stored your R Markdown file somewhere on your harddisk (with suffix &lt;code&gt;.Rmd&lt;/code&gt;), RStudio will automatically save the generated HTML file in the same location, with the same name and suffix &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt;. The HTML file is self-contained, including all images, so it&amp;rsquo;s easy to publish it on a web page or share it with people. RStudio also provides you with the option to publish the document online on the &lt;a href=&#34;http://rpubs.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;RPubs&lt;/a&gt; website. Just click on the &amp;ldquo;Publish&amp;rdquo; button in the HTML view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about R Markdown, go to:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
