<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Editing on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Editing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Editing on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Editing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Double Jeopardy</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/09/13/double-jeopardy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/09/13/double-jeopardy/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Lately it keeps happening to me that I try to invite somebody to review a paper and they decline, giving as reason that they have reviewed the paper already for a different journal&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and reviewing the paper again would put the authors into a situation of double jeopardy. This got me thinking. Should reviewers really decline for that reason? As reviewer, I’ve always thought the opposite. For a paper I have reviewed already, if the authors have made a reasonable effort to address my comments and have now chosen a more adequate journal, I can keep my review short and recommend acceptance. Thus, I’m actually preventing a situation of double jeopardy. I keep the authors from facing yet another reviewer with new opinions and requests. So, which is right? Should reviewers recuse themselves if they are asked to review again for a different journal, or should they instead leap at the opportunity and give the authors a break? I’d be interested in your thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where the paper was rejected, presumably.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
