<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Grants on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Grants/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Grants on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Grants/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PLOS ONE publishes analysis of grant writing costs and benefits</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/03/24/plos-one-publishes-analysis-of-grant-writing-costs-and-benefitssafety-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/03/24/plos-one-publishes-analysis-of-grant-writing-costs-and-benefitssafety-projects/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;PLOS ONE just published an article providing a cost-benefit analysis of grant writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;von Hippel T, von Hippel C (2015) &lt;a href=&#34;http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0118494&#34;&gt;To Apply or Not to Apply: A Survey Analysis of Grant Writing Costs and Benefits.&lt;/a&gt; PLoS ONE 10(3): e0118494.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main take-home messages: If you write more grants you will get more funding. Also, at current funding rates, unless you’re writing 2-3 proposals a year, you have a reasonable chance of going unfunded over a three-year period. The authors suggest that investigators should avoid programs with funding rates at 20% or less unless they are willing to write multiple proposals a year and/or have a particularly compelling research program. However, in biology practically all funding rates are 20% or less these days, so that advice isn’t very helpful. Instead, we just need to keep writing proposals. If you’re after NIH funding, you should probably write at least one proposal per cycle, unless you’ve been recently funded. If you’re primarily after NSF funding, with yearly cycles, you’ll have to diversify and find at least two programs to which you can send your proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should peer-review be double-blind?</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/18/should-peer-review-be-double-blind/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/18/should-peer-review-be-double-blind/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;As part of the &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2014/10/12/in-defense-of-anonymous-peer-review&#34;&gt;recent discussion on anonymous peer review,&lt;/a&gt; several people spoke out in favor of double-blind peer review, where neither the authors nor the reviewers know who the others are. I have thought a lot about double-blind peer review, and I’m not entirely convinced, in particular when it comes to grant applications. While double-blind review might solve certain problems and remove certain biases, it would almost certainly amplify other issues, and whether the net effect would be good or bad is unclear. It would also give more power to people such as editors and program managers who operate outside the blinded process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s discuss. I’ll first cover journal articles and then grant proposals. The two are very different, and what applies to one does not necessarily apply to the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;journal-articles&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Journal articles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the face of it, double-blind peer review for journal articles seems like a no-brainer. It allows junior scientists to be judged on the merit of their work alone, and it prevents senior scientists from coasting through peer review on the basis of their good name. However, as always, the devil is in the detail. There are at least three reasons I can think of why double-blind review may not be such a great idea after all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the real power is with the editors, not the reviewers. It’s the editors who make the final decisions. And this power tends to increase with the perceived rank of the journal; editors of more prestigious journals are more likely to reject papers without review or because of a perceived lack of interest. We all know that you won’t publish in &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; if the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; editors don’t like your work. And we also know that you can survive quite harsh reviewer criticisms if the &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; editors really want to publish your work.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Thus, one could make an argument that author names should be blinded to both reviewers and editors. But how would the editors invite unbiased reviewers if they don’t know who has a potential conflict of interest? The only practical way would be to have one editor invite the reviewers and another make the decision. This would be an interesting experiment, but I doubt any journal will go for it any time soon. Thus, as long as author names remain known to the handling editor, I doubt that double-blind review will make much of a difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, blinding the authors of an article is incredibly hard. Just removing the author names from the first page of a paper will frequently not do. If the authors work on a unique study system, or make extensive use of their prior work, or have developed a specific software package, or have posted their data on a public repository, reviewers will likely be able to find out who they are. I once reviewed a paper where the authors had not only removed their names from the title page but also from citations to their own work in the reference list. I’m still amazed that somebody would (i) go to these lengths to conceal their identity and (ii) not realize that this action completely obliterated any anonymity they might otherwise have had. Double-blinding may create an illusion of anonymity where none actually exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, double-blind review gives more power to scientists who are intent on submitting fraudulent work, because it is going to be harder for reviewers to identify patterns in the perpetrators’ activities. For example, I have my list of crooks with a solid portfolio on &lt;a href=&#34;http://retractionwatch.com/&#34;&gt;Retraction Watch,&lt;/a&gt; and when I get to review one of their papers I’ll be extra careful. These are usually scientists whose activities slipped by me the first time I reviewed one of their papers, because everything looked fine on the surface. If I regularly had to review their papers in a double-blind fashion, they would probably manage to slip by me more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One benefit of double-blind peer review, however, could be that even if the reviewers have a sense of which lab(s) may have been involved in a given study, they still won’t be able to guess the exact author list. For example, I don’t know to what extent reviewers are biased by the gender of the first author if a paper comes from an established lab, but if they are, that bias would likely disappear in double-blind review. Reviewers may guess correctly that the paper comes out of my lab, but they won’t know which of my students wrote it. Evidence in favor of this notion comes from one experiment in which double-blind peer review &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.nature.com/peer-to-peer/2008/01/doubleblind_peer_review_reveal.html&#34;&gt;increased the number of female first authors.&lt;/a&gt; Similarly, when junior PIs continue working on research they begun in an established person’s lab, reviewers won’t be able to tell whether the paper comes from the established lab or the junior PI. This could work to the advantage of junior PIs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the positive and the negative aspects of double-blind review are about even, in my opinion. I have no major concerns about double-blind review, as long as I as an author am not expected to do anything more than remove my name from the author list. I’m not interested in going through my entire paper and making sure not a single sentence (e.g. “We have previously investigated…”) could give a hint at who I am. Also, we now frequently make all our data and code available in a github repository, and I’m not going to go through extra effort to conceal who I am there. Other than that, I’d be happy to support more experiments in double-blind peer review, and I’ll also be happy to support double-blind peer review more strongly if evidence in its favor continues to accumulate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;grant-proposals&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Grant proposals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Grant proposals are an entirely different beast than journal articles, and I do not think that double-blind proposal review is a good idea. There is a fundamental difference between a journal article and a proposal. An article is the finished product. A grant proposal, by contrast, is only the promise of a future product. If one scientist writes ten times more high-profile papers than another, then she should publish ten times more frequently in high-profile journals, without question. However, just because one scientist is ten times better at writing grant proposals than another doesn’t mean he deserves ten times the funds. In fact, only if that scientist can write ten times as many papers or write papers that are ten times as important (however measured) would he deserve ten times the grant funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that the track record of past performance needs to be considered in proposal review. If you had to hand one person a check over a million dollars, would you rather give the money to somebody who consistently delivers interesting results, even if that person’s grant application doesn’t sound overly exciting, or would you prefer to give the money to somebody who can tell a great story but about whom you know nothing beyond that story. This thought is related to the idea (&lt;a href=&#34;http://loop.nigms.nih.gov/2014/07/comment-on-proposed-pilot-to-support-nigms-investigators-overall-research-programs/&#34;&gt;which is slowly sinking in with the NIH as well&lt;/a&gt;) that it is generally better to fund people than projects, or at least to have a healthy mix of people-based and project-based funding. By definition, if you’re evaluating people, you cannot blind the evaluators to their identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you could argue that the scientific review should be done blinded and the final funding decision be made by the program officer, who can take into account all the other relevant factors, such as track record, current funding of the applicant, etc. However, this would simply put more power into the hands of program officers, who might or might not use that power wisely. It’s certainly not unheard of for program officers in some agencies to preferentially fund their good buddies. The more power a program officer has to override a panel decision the more likely those situations are going to arise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Double-blind grant review is also open to several sorts of manipulation by applicants. First, it would be easier than it already is to base an application on dubious, sketchy, or even entirely made-up data, because nobody would ever know.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Second, applicants could pack their proposals with prior results obtained by the biggest shot in the field, causing the reviewers to think they’re reviewing an application by that lab and rank it higher because of that. You might say that that’s exactly the point, only ideas matter, but I’ve seen too many scientists with great ideas and poor execution to feel comfortable with funding decisions based exclusively on ideas.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I don’t think that double-blind grant applications are the way to go. There are other ways to minimize biases in the review process. For example, panels could be given statistics on how many women and junior scientists submitted applications to a given competition, and if the composition of the top-ranked applicants deviates substantially from the overall composition of applicants then the panel could be asked to reconsider their rankings. In general, just paying attention to these kinds of biases and monitoring whether certain groups of applicants are disproportionally affected by either positive or negative decisions should prevent the most egregious biases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (10/19/2014):&lt;/strong&gt; The article I quoted &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.nature.com/peer-to-peer/2008/01/doubleblind_peer_review_reveal.html&#34;&gt;claiming an increased number of female first authors&lt;/a&gt; under double-blind review has later &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nature.com/news/2008/080604/full/453711c.html&#34;&gt;been called into question,&lt;/a&gt; as comparable journals have similarly seen an increase in the number of female first authors during the same time period, without instituting double-blind review. Thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/mattjhodgkinson&#34;&gt;Matt Hodgkinson&lt;/a&gt; for pointing this out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update #2 (10/19/2014):&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/asi.22784/full&#34;&gt;This paper,&lt;/a&gt; pointed out to me by Matt Hodgkinson, provides a thorough review of what is currently known about biases in peer review. It shows mixed evidence on gender bias. In particular with respect to journal articles, current evidence suggests bias isn’t that pronounced (female and male authors have comparable acceptance rates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I certainly have reviewed papers for &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; that I thought should not be published there and the editors overruled me. And this is fine; editors should have the ultimate decision power. I’m an editor myself, and on occasion I accept papers that reviewers say should be rejected. The point remains, though, that an editor who really wants to publish a paper will rarely be deterred by negative reviews, in particular if the reviews don’t call out egregious errors in the work.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even under the current system of non-blinded review, grant applicants can include sketchy or made-up data with little risk to their career or reputation. While such activity is obviously fraudulent and will have severe consequences if discovered, the likelihood of discovery is low. First, only three to five other scientists ever see the application, and only for a short period of time. So if an applicant, for example, reuses the same data set in subsequent applications but labels the resulting figure differently, it’s very unlikely anybody would notice. Similarly, if an applicant claims preliminary data support one hypothesis and later publishes a paper supporting a different hypothesis, he could always argue that that is indeed how discovery went: first things looked one way but after more careful study it became clear the other way was right. Only the most blatantly obvious fraud, such as publishing fraudulent data in a paper and then using that paper as preliminary results in an application, has any likelihood of being discovered. For these reasons, a colleague of mine here at UT thinks that results that aren’t published or maybe at least deposited on a public archive should not be allowed in grant applications at all.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As with everything in life, I think some balance is required here. Grant applicants should have to demonstrate some amount of prior expertise in the work they propose, but they should also be given the benefit of the doubt that some things can be worked out as the research is done.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surviving the pre-tenure years at an R1 university</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/07/12/surviving-the-pre-tenure-years-at-an-r1-university/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/07/12/surviving-the-pre-tenure-years-at-an-r1-university/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, Pröf-like Substance &lt;a href=&#34;http://scientopia.org/blogs/proflikesubstance/2014/07/02/blog-carnival-surviving-the-pre-tenure-years/&#34;&gt;asked for posts with suggestions on how to survive the pre-tenure years.&lt;/a&gt; I went over my blogging history and realized that I hadn’t really written anything on this topic yet. Most of my advice to date is targeted at more junior scientists. So here is my attempt at giving some suggestions on how to make the most out of your years on the tenure track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The below applies to a tenure-track position at an R1 university, where your promotion will largely depend on your research productivity. I’m assuming that you’re teaching one course a semester or less, you have limited requirements in terms of departmental service, and you have access to a pool of capable graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;relax-youre-not-going-to-die&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relax, you’re not going to die&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you are, but likely not any time soon. Being a fresh Assistant Professor on the tenure track is a pretty sweet deal. You have 5-7 years of guaranteed job security, during which nobody is going to tell you what to do. Your teaching load is pretty light. You get to spend most of your time doing stuff you really enjoy. Also, unless you’ve signed up with a place known for not tenuring their junior faculty members, such as Harvard, odds are in your favor. As long as you perform reasonably, you will probably get tenure. And, even if you are denied tenure, you’ll likely land on your feet and find a good job elsewhere. I can think of only a handful of people I know who were denied tenure, and all of them have done Ok. In fact, the vast majority of them are now in permanent academic positions at different (or even the same&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) universities, or at national labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stressing over tenure will only make you perform worse. To be successful, you need to be original, you need to be productive, and you need to inspire the students and postdocs in your lab to perform at their best. Worrying about tenure will interfere with all of this. So you might as well forget that there is such a thing as tenure, do your day-to-day job as best you can, and enjoy the ride.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;carefully-evaluate-any-advice-you-receive&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Carefully evaluate any advice you receive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll receive tons of advice on how to get tenure, including this piece you’re reading right now. Chances are, some of the advice you hear will not jibe with you. Some of it may even conflict with other advice you’re hearing. If you try to follow all this advice to the letter, you may feel dragged back and forth, and you may be doing all sorts of things that aren’t really you. Being an academic is all about being original and independent, doing things differently than other people have done, swimming against the stream. For any piece of advice somebody gives you, I’ll be able to point to a person who ignored it and got tenure anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this shouldn’t be a license to behave like a complete idiot. You will need to show some productivity, you will likely need some external funding, and you need to behave reasonably towards your colleagues and your students. But beyond that, there’s many ways to skin a cat, and you’ll have to find your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;write-at-least-two-papers-a-year&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Write at least two papers a year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minimum of two papers a year will provide insurance against any potential claims of poor productivity somewhere up the chain in the promotion process. These claims are usually brought up when applicants have on their cv one or more years without any papers, in particular in succession. One paper a year might be sufficient, but two is safer. It protects against the vagaries of the review process, which may overly delay some of your papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you’re working at a place that emphasizes research, writing two papers a year should be eminently doable, even if you’re doing difficult experimental work that progresses slowly. Let’s do the math. Over a five-year period, that’s about 10 papers. Three of them can be review papers, which you can write without needing any new data. Two of them should be major contributions. Let’s say one is a piece of work you started as a postdoc. That’s a paper for which you should have most or all of the data already, and you should be able to write that quickly. The other should be the first major, independent piece from your own lab, which you may submit late in year three or early in year four so it comes out in time for your tenure review. Surely your research isn’t so complicated that you can’t generate enough data for a solid paper in three years. (If it is, maybe you should reevaluate your research program.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves five more papers to write. Those can be small, “least publishable unit” (LPU) papers. You should be able to write one of those each year. Write something about a method you developed. Re-analyze a previously published data set. Publish some of the partial results that will eventually lead to your big paper, three years down the line. Honestly, if you can’t write at least one LPU paper a year, you have to take a hard look at your standards and ask yourself whether they’re too high.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;publish-the-same-idea-multiple-times&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Publish the same idea multiple times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not asking you to self-plagiarize, I’m just encouraging you to keep beating the horse even though you may think you have slain it already. If you’ve shown something once, show it again in a different way. Or in a different system. Or write a follow-up paper showing something that may be totally obvious to you given your earlier results. Then write a review paper about all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this approach will help you with productivity. Second, and more importantly, it will associate your name with the particular effect you’re investigating. As part of the promotion process, letter writers will be asked whether you’re a leader in your field. One of the best ways to become known and recognized as a leader is to say the same thing, over and over, until it’s been heard in even the last corner of every ivory tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;say-yes-to-as-many-conference-and-seminar-invitations-as-possible&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Say “yes” to as many conference and seminar invitations as possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said in the previous point, being known helps tremendously with getting tenure. And traveling around the country giving talks at departmental seminars and conferences helps tremendously with being known. Thus, if you’re invited to speak somewhere, try to say “yes.” For some, this advice is a no-brainer. But if you don’t enjoy traveling, or if you have health concerns, or if you have teaching or family obligations that make it difficult to travel, you may be inclined to say “no.” Of course there are perfectly valid reasons to decline a travel invitation, and in the end you have to weigh the various priorities and make your own decision. My advice, if you have a tendency to say “no,” is to make an honest assessment of how much travel you can realistically accommodate into your life, and then plan accordingly. For example, you might decide that you can travel &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; times a year, or that you need at least &lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt; weeks between trips, or that you can never travel in the spring. If you have a clear system like that, then it’ll be easy for you to take advantage of the opportunities that come your way. And you’ll also feel more comfortable saying “no” if you have a straightforward reason to decline, e.g.: “I’m sorry, this would be my second trip in August, and I never make more than one trip a month.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;apply-for-funding-early-often-and-widely&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apply for funding early, often, and widely&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll probably need funding to receive tenure. Even if your university doesn’t make funding a requirement, you’ll probably need funding to keep your lab going/productive, and you’ll definitely need a productive lab to get tenure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to publishing a paper, getting a grant is much harder. Most papers I write get published; most grants I write get rejected. However, the good thing about grants is that you don’t need to obtain that many. If you’re receiving one medium-sized grant every other year or so you’re doing pretty good. To maximize your chances of receiving funding, apply often and widely. You should probably write 3-5 grants a year. Most importantly, don’t just try one funding agency or one program. Even if you’re told you need the R01 to get tenure, I doubt your colleagues will be upset with you if you’re getting a nice grant from the Navy instead. Also, don’t write all of these grants entirely by yourself. Build some collaborations, and try to be part of some larger research teams. Again, even if you’re told you need the single-investigator grant, your promotion committee will certainly rank collaborative funding higher than no funding at all. And, any funding you manage to secure helps you to hire people and pay for experiments which may be preliminary results in your next single-investigator grant application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;make-sure-you-recruit-graduate-students-as-soon-as-possible&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make sure you recruit graduate students as soon as possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate students are the lifeblood of a new lab. Attempt to recruit one or two good ones as early as possible. The moment you receive your offer letter, find out how graduate recruitment works, and make sure you’re in the system and prospective students know about you. If possible, attend events for prospective graduate students even if you haven’t actually started your position yet. Ask your (prospective) department to add you to their web site as soon as possible. If your department has a rotation system, make sure you’re on the rotation schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate student recruitment happens only once a year, and if you miss the first year, you’ll risk sitting in an empty lab for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;be-careful-with-your-postdoc-hires&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be careful with your postdoc hires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring a postdoc can be tricky for a young faculty member, unless you’re at Harvard or similar, where postdocs are willing to join any lab just for the overall reputation of the university. Most really good postdocs prefer to go to large, established labs with a proven track record. I’ve heard lots of stories from young faculty members about the postdoc woes they have gone through. This doesn’t mean you shouldn’t hire a postdoc at all. It just means you should focus on getting someone really good and vet them well. One option that may work is hiring a student from a past adviser, possibly somebody you worked with when you were a postdoc yourself. In case of doubt, recruit graduate students rather than postdocs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;teaching-may-hurt-you-but-it-is-unlikely-to-help-you&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teaching may hurt you but it is unlikely to help you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your teaching is atrocious, you may be denied tenure even if your research is stellar. However, if your teaching is stellar and your research weak, chances are nobody will care about your teaching performance. So plan accordingly. Put enough effort into your teaching so that nobody can say you are a bad teacher, but don’t sacrifice your research program for the goal of becoming the best teacher in the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;do-things-that-make-you-happy&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do things that make you happy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how much you enjoy being an academic, there will be elements to your job that you don’t enjoy. It’s a job after all. Therefore, it is important that you find a balance between doing the things that you do enjoy and those that you don’t. When you’re under pressure to perform, such as with tenure looming, it is easy to get dragged down into doing mostly the things that you don’t enjoy but that must get done. You need to be aware of this dynamic and consciously work against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, assume you have successfully set up lab, and you now have a couple of grad students and a technician. They are all reasonably capable and they produce results. What your lab now needs is papers and grants. And you’re the only one in the lab who can write them. So, clearly, you should be spending all your time writing and none of your time doing experiments, right? This is only true if you really enjoy writing papers and grants. Let’s say you don’t. Let’s say what you really enjoy is standing at the bench doing experiments. In this case you need to find a balance such that you sometimes get to do the things that made you become an academic in the first place. Maybe you write in the morning and work at the bench in the afternoon. Or you work at the bench one day a week. Even though theoretically your productivity would be higher if you spent all your time doing the things only you can do, in practice your productivity will only stay high if you’re happy. If standing in front of a bench makes you happy, then absolutely do so, without any regrets.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not getting tenure the first time round but eventually getting it anyway seems to be somewhat common at UT. I can think of at least four cases since I’ve been here.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/2013/07/21/the-awesomest-7-year-postdoc-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-the-tenure-track-faculty-life/&#34;&gt;The Awesomest 7-Year Postdoc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the topic of whether it is worth it to write low-impact papers, see also &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/11/3/no-one-reads-your-paper-either&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote a while back.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same concept applies to balancing your job with the rest of your life. You need to do things that make you happy. Go exercise, watch a play, learn how to juggle, write a blog, write a novel. Anything that gives you joy deserves some of your time.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use fine-grained sectioning in your grant proposals</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/28/use-fine-grained-sectioning-in-your-grant-proposals/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I have noticed lately that many scientists write grant proposals with little document structure. Their proposals may have separate sections for background, for specific aims, and so on, but each of these sections is basically a long wall of text. The problem with this approach is that most reviewers will not carefully read all this text, and as a consequence they will miss important elements of the proposal. All else equal, a poorly structured proposal will be much less competitive than a well-structured proposal with many sub-sections and titled paragraphs. Because grant-writing remains one of the most important skills to be acquired by junior scientists, I see a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application&#34;&gt;critical need&lt;/a&gt; to highlight the importance of fine-grained sectioning in grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two specific aims for this post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 1. Demonstrate effective sectioning by writing this blog post in the form of a grant proposal.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By giving a clear example, I will allow my readers to quickly recognize the value of extensive document structure.&lt;/em&gt; I will write the entire blog post as if it were a proposal, and I will use an informative title for each individual paragraph and subsection. I will use short paragraphs that get straight to the point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aim 2. Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hypothesis: By providing useful and interesting content, I will attract more readers to my blog, who in turn will benefit from my advice.&lt;/em&gt; I will shamelessly promote this post on twitter and elsewhere, to the maximum extent allowed by law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;significance&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Significance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grant-proposal writing is a crucial skill for the modern scientist.&lt;/strong&gt; These days, being a scientist is as much about writing grants as it is about doing actual science. While we cannot be successful without doing good science and writing interesting papers, our success will be short-lived unless we can also successfully request funding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the reader.&lt;/strong&gt; There is really only one type of reader for a grant proposal: a reviewer. And reviewers are notoriously pressed for time. Imagine having to evaluate 20 grant proposals in an afternoon. The last thing you want to see is a huge wall of text without structure and with no indication where the important pieces are located. You want short, clear paragraphs and sufficient structure, so that you can quickly jump to the relevant sections of the proposal and look up specific issues you want clarification on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear structure helps the writer.&lt;/strong&gt; As a writer, you’ll actually have a much easier time writing the proposal if you have a clear structure in mind. If you don’t know what the specific purpose of a particular paragraph is, you’re more likely to blather on and not make a clear point. On the flip side, once you’ve written the paragraph heading, all you need to do is write a few sentences that make the appropriate statement and you are done. In fact, when I write proposals (and when I wrote this post) I usually write out all the paragraph headings first and then fill in the blanks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice is only useful to the extent that people see it.&lt;/strong&gt; If my blog has few readers, then I’m not making much of a difference in this world, regardless of how good my advice actually is. Each well-promoted post on this blog increases the visibility of the blog as a whole, which will increase in turn the visibility of each individual post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-1-write-this-blog-post-in-the-form-of-a-grant-proposal&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 1: Write this blog post in the form of a grant proposal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Most people tend to benefit more from concrete examples than from theoretical expositions on a topic. One could read a thousand words on effective sectioning and not have any idea of how to apply these ideas in practice. Or, one could see a simple example and immediately recognize how to apply its principles in one’s own writing. For this reason, in this post I emphasize demonstration over exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; I will write the entire blog post in the form of a grant proposal. I will have specific aims, which have hypotheses, approach, expected results, and so on. Each individual paragraph in this post will have a paragraph heading that states what the paragraph is about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I hope that at least some scientist somewhere on this planet will write a better grant proposal after reading this post. I particularly hope that this post will be useful for junior scientists who may not yet have seen many successful grant proposals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; First, it is possible that there are aspects to this post that are unclear or confusing. As a result, some readers may get an incorrect impression of what I’m saying. For example, someone could think that they absolutely have to provide a heading for every single paragraph, when sometimes it’s perfectly fine to have two or even three short paragraphs under one heading. To the extent that any readers express such misconceptions in the comments section, I will respond to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if nobody sees my post, then all my efforts are for nothing. I will address visibility in Aim 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;aim-2-use-this-post-to-promote-my-blog-as-a-whole.&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Aim 2: Use this post to promote my blog as a whole.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rationale.&lt;/strong&gt; Even the most well-reasoned and helpful blog posts are useless unless they are actually read. The visibility of individual blog posts is directly proportional to the overall reach of a blog. Therefore, I have to promote both this post in particular and the blog as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approach.&lt;/strong&gt; Upon posting, I will tweet about this post. I will also tell colleagues and students about it. If somebody tweets about this post I will retweet their tweet, for &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_proof&#34;&gt;added social proof.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expected results.&lt;/strong&gt; I expect to see a spike in web traffic when my tweet posts. I further expect that at least one or two of my followers will favorite my post, and that somebody will retweet it. Finally, I hope to pick up at least one new follower on twitter as a consequence of writing this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential problems and solutions.&lt;/strong&gt; If timing of my original tweet is poor few of my followers may notice my blog post. If I notice poor incoming traffic, I can consider tweeting about this post a second time. Further, if none of my followers tweet about my post then I have nothing to retweet. In this case, I may have to ask a student or friend to write a tweet for me. If all else fails, I can promote my post on facebook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The critical need in a grant application</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/17/the-critical-need-in-a-grant-application/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s surprising how many grant applications do not clearly spell out a critical need. A critical need is the fundamental reason why a grant should exist. Without it, there’s really not much of a point to the grant. And yet, a critical need is frequently not stated. The common mistake that people make is that they confuse a gap in knowledge with a critical need. They clearly spell out what gap in knowledge they plan to address. And mind you, that’s an important component of a grant proposal. But if you stop there, if you never explain &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; there is a critical need to bridge the gap in knowledge, then your application is going to fall short. Unless the reviewers really like you for other reasons, they will probably not be impressed with your grant application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me explain the difference between a gap in knowledge and a critical need by way of an example. Assume you go out Saturday night and get drunk. In the morning, you wake up and have no recollection of how you made your way home. This is clearly a gap in knowledge. But there’s no critical need attached to that gap. I couldn’t care less whether you stumbled home, took a cab, or hitched a ride with a friend. Your grant on “The modes of transportation by which I found my way home last Saturday” is not going to be selected for funding by my agency. Now, instead, consider the following scenario. You go out Saturday night and get drunk. You wake up Sunday morning, not remembering how you got home. Upon looking into the mirror, you find that you’re battered and bruised. You’re also covered in blood. And your husband is nowhere to be found and doesn’t answer his cell phone. In this scenario, I think most people would think that there is a critical need to figure out what happened, to fill the gap in knowledge. Your grant on “Why I am innocent and didn’t kill my husband. Honestly!” would probably fare much better than the previous one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is: there are all sorts of gaps in knowledge that aren’t attached to a critical need. Grants to fill those knowledge gaps will generally not fare that well in review. Therefore, think carefully about the critical need your research will fill. If you can’t think of one right now, think harder. I’m sure you can immediately name the gap of knowledge you’re working on. The critical need should be just as obvious to you. Note: If you’re a junior scientist working on questions that your adviser has funding for, then your work almost certainly satisfies some critical need. If you’re not sure what it is, ask your adviser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where in a grant application should you express the critical need? It has to come early, so your reviewers don’t waste a lot of time being bored or disinterested. Also, it needs to be in a &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/26/writing-paragraphs-that-make-sensethe-topic-and-the-stress-position&#34;&gt;position of stress,&lt;/a&gt; so your reviewers correctly perceive its importance. Consequently, there’s only a single place in a grant proposal where it fits: the last sentence of the first paragraph. The entire first paragraph should build up to the critical need, which justifies why you’re writing your grant in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate this idea with the first paragraph of a grant I recently wrote:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comparative sequence analysis is a cornerstone of modern biology, with applications ranging from determining the evolutionary history of species, to tracking pathogens, to identifying sites in a protein under positive or purifying selection. For protein-coding genes, comparative analysis has shown that protein structure strongly influences sequence variability: buried sites tend to be more conserved, and exposed sites—more variable. Deviations from this expectation can suggest functional importance. For example, a &lt;em&gt;rapidly evolving buried site&lt;/em&gt; in a viral enzyme might be near the binding pocket and contribute to the evolution of drug resistance. A &lt;em&gt;conserved exposed site&lt;/em&gt; might be involved in important protein–protein interactions. Yet conventional tools for comparative sequence analysis ignore protein structure and operate on sequence data alone. &lt;strong&gt;We, therefore, see a critical need to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first paragraph of the Aims page, arguably the first piece of text in the grant that the reviewers read. As you can see, the entire paragraph builds up to the critical need, which is to develop comparative methods that can jointly analyze sequence and structural data. This is a critical need only because we believe—and have some preliminary data to demonstrate—that sequence analysis in a structural context will be more informative for important applications than sequence analysis in the absence of structural information can be. If there weren’t any important applications, or if the structural information made little difference to the outcome of the analysis, then the critical need would evaporate. There’d still be a gap in knowledge around sequence analysis in a structural context, but there wouldn’t be a critical need to bridge that gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For full disclosure, I should say that this grant wasn’t funded. However, it was scored in the top third of applications (26% percentile). From my reading of the reviews, I would say that the reviewers believed our critical need. We just weren’t sufficiently competitive with the actual work we were proposing. Specifically, we didn’t have sufficient preliminary results to &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/17/which-grants-get-funded-at-single-digit-funding-rates&#34;&gt;give our proposal that aura of magic.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Which grants get funded at single-digit funding rates?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/17/which-grants-get-funded-at-single-digit-funding-rates/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/17/which-grants-get-funded-at-single-digit-funding-rates/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Throughout the last decade, funding rates at most US funding bodies have kept declining, and they have now reached awfully low levels. These days, single-digit success rates are pretty common. At the NSF, in some competitions I’ve seen success rates of 5% or less. As a result, most US scientists are struggling to figure out how to make the best of this abysmal situation. One could view the entire granting process as a lottery, and say that at a funding rate of 5% it takes an average of 20 submissions to get one project funded. And certainly some scientists operate this way and just write grant after grant after grant. However, I’m not convinced that that’s a viable strategy. While there is certainly an aspect of randomness to grant review, and sometimes a mediocre grant gets rated much higher than it should while an excellent grant gets triaged, I don’t think that this randomness matters much at the top end. If funding rates were around 30–40% then yes, one could probably write 3–4 grants and expect one to be funded just by chance. But I will argue that the top 5–10% of grants, the ones in the currently fundable range, are fundamentally different. If your grant isn’t like one of them, it probably has a near-zero chance of being funded. And if it is, it may well have a 50% or higher chance. The trick to being funded is hence to only write grants that can score in the top 10%. Easy. (Yes, I’m being sarcastic here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news is that I think it’s relatively straightforward to recognize grants that can score in the top 10%. The bad news is that I don’t know how to write them. Or rather, I don’t know how make all the necessary things come together such that I can reliably write grants that will score in the top 10%. All I can do is write a grant and then evaluate whether it’ll be good enough. Usually—but not always—the answer is “no.” In those cases, I probably might just as well not even submit. For the small number of grants where the answer has been “yes,” my success rate hasn’t been all that bad in recent years.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how do 10th-percentile-and-up grants differ from lower-scoring grants? I like to think of them as magical. They have all the required pieces coming together in just the right way. They address an important question, use a sexy study system, have just the right combination of theory and experiment, and have extensive preliminary results demonstrating feasibility. They also are well written and easy to understand even by people outside the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, some of these elements are not under your control. For example, if you’re a theoretician like me, you may not be able to add experiments to your proposal. You could gang up with an experimentalist, but then the two of you may not have any convincing joint preliminary data. More generally, you may have a great idea, but it may require three years of work to demonstrate feasibility and you won’t get it funded until you’ve put in those three years. Also, the study system you chose to work on, for whatever reason, may just not be as sexy as other systems. If you’re studying virus evolution using bacteriophages and somebody else is doing more or less the same work with some deadly human virus, chances are your proposal will be considered less competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some things are under your control. You definitely can improve your writing and your grantmanship. If you’re not regularly scoring in at least the top 30%, then either the science you’re doing is absolutely no good (possible, but not probable) or you just don’t know how to write a competitive grant (more likely). In the latter case, there are resources that you can take advantage of. For example, the seminars and books offered by &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.grantcentral.com/&#34;&gt;these people&lt;/a&gt; are pretty good.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The NIH has a page with &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.niaid.nih.gov/researchfunding/grant/pages/appsamples.aspx&#34;&gt;annotated examples of high-scoring grants.&lt;/a&gt; I will probably also write a few blog posts about grant writing in the future, so stay tuned.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, as an individual investigator, in particular if you’re a junior one, it will always be difficult to jump over the bar separating the top 10% from the bottom 90%. Unless you’re literally the best in the world at doing whatever it is you are doing, your individual track record and preliminary results may not be good enough to compete at the highest level. In general, I think it’s easier to be successful as a team, competing for larger pots of money. If a funding body wants to establish a center or make a large collaborative grant on a certain topic, and you pull together the best people in the nation working on that topic, then your proposal will be hard to beat. This doesn’t mean that the single investigator grant is dead. It just means that you should evaluate carefully (and realistically!) where your work falls. And don’t waste your time on proposals that are not going to be fundable. If, however, you can see that you have all the right pieces in place, that you can write that magical proposal where everything comes together beautifully, then by all means go for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last 5 years, about 2–3 grants that I thought were good enough to be funded did actually get funded. That’s good enough to run a lab on. Over that same time period, I’ve probably written only 2–3 grants that I thought &lt;em&gt;had a realistic chance of being funded.&lt;/em&gt; So that’s a near 100% success rate among the really good grants. I’ve of course also written many grants that didn’t get funded. But for all of those, by submission time I could have listed reasons why they likely wouldn’t make it into the top 10%, and they didn’t.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have no affiliation with them. I just took their training once and found it helpful.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I just put myself on the same level with the leading grant coaches and the NIH. I’m still trying to figure out how this modesty things works.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
