<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Academic career on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Academic-career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Academic career on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Academic-career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI, and 6 reasons not to</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the eternal questions of graduate schools is whether you should work with a junior or a senior PI. I have commented on this question before &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school&#34;&gt;and argued that either decision can be the right one.&lt;/a&gt; Here, I present a more comprehensive list of arguments for and against. As you’ll see, there are plenty of arguments going both ways. You may assign more weight to some than others and thus arrive at a decision that is best for you. Ultimately, I think it doesn’t matter too much; there are other factors that are more important, such as whether you enjoy and fit in with the lab’s culture and approach to research, collaboration, publication, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is my list. If you can think of something I forgot, please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the early students in the lab of a rising star, you can rise to prominence with your PI. You may end up as the first author in one or more of your PI’s key publications, and this in turn may secure your own faculty position and seniority in the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may have more time to supervise you. The lab is likely relatively small and you’re not competing with 10 other lab members for your PI’s attention. Also, your PI may not yet be that involved with university service and other non-research obligations, and thus have more time to interact with the lab (i.e., you).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A young lab may be doing some really novel, cutting-edge work. An older lab is more likely to work on the stuff they’ve always worked on, stuff that was real innovative 10 years ago but is an old hat now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your PI is not that established, there’s less risk that once you graduate your adviser is such a towering influence in the field that you can’t establish yourself as distinct from him/her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a large, established lab, you might find yourself working on a small part of a larger project. Even if you do excellent work, your name might in the end not get associated with the big paper that comes out of that work. (I’m not saying you won’t be a coauthor. I’m saying you might be one of 20 coauthors and nobody will think you were the person who made it happen.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The younger your adviser, the less likely it is that he or she come down with a debilitating disease or die a sudden death. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3298961/figure/fig2/&#34;&gt;the risk of death of a 60-year old man is 10 times higher than that of a 35-year old man.&lt;/a&gt; Just avoid younger PIs with a passion for BASE jumping, cave diving, or motorcycle racing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-senior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a senior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI is untested. It is less clear how sustainable the PI’s research program is, how likely the PI will be able to attract funding, and how good his/her research ideas are. If the junior PI is on a bad trajectory, it is likely that your PhD won’t be that great either. (Keep in mind, though, that your PI’s success depends to some extent on you!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the field. The two of you may find yourselves fighting uphill battles with reviewers, journal editors, and other labs in the field. The exact same work might be lauded as the world’s greatest invention since sliced bread when coming from an established, senior lab or derided as inconsequential, boring, or wrong when coming from a junior lab. Having a junior adviser can also make it harder to find an academic job after you graduate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the university. This may put you at a disadvantage when it comes to TA positions, university fellowships, and other dealings with university administration. In particular, if something unexpected happens, e.g. the class you were supposed to TA for gets cancelled, a senior PI is more likely going to have resources to deal with the situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lab of a junior PI may not have the resources you will need to carry out outstanding research. In particular, if you join a lab in its first or second year, you may find yourself spending a year or longer just setting up lab infrastructure. By contrast, a large, established lab will likely have everything you need to do ground-breaking work the moment you walk into the door.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since your PI is new, he or she still has to prove himself/herself. As a result, your PI might end up competing with you. For example, a junior PI might insist on being the one presenting your work at a conference where a senior PI might let you present your work yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you join the lab of an untenured professor, you risk that your PI won’t get tenure while you’re in the lab. That experience is likely going to be as disruptive to you as it will be to your PI. The worst-case scenario is an upcoming tenure decision 2-4 years out from when you start your PhD. If you’re only in your first year when your PI doesn’t get tenure, you should be able to just join another lab, without having wasted much time and effort. And if you’re in your fifth year or later, you should be able to finish up your dissertation work even if your PI has to close down his/her lab and move on. But if you’re right in the middle of your thesis work, you may have to throw away 2-3 years of work and start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>No one reads your paper either</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/11/03/no-one-reads-your-paper-either/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/11/03/no-one-reads-your-paper-either/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://downwithtime.wordpress.com/&#34;&gt;Simon Goring&lt;/a&gt; wrote an interesting post a few days ago arguing that &lt;a href=&#34;http://downwithtime.wordpress.com/2013/10/29/no-one-reads-your-blog-reflections-on-the-middling-bottom/&#34;&gt;no one reads your blog.&lt;/a&gt; In his post, he discussed reasons for why you might want to blog anyway. This post prompted me to tackle a topic I’ve been thinking about for a while: Why should you do science? Why should you publish? No one is going to read your paper either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, while I’m sure everybody agrees on the value of publishing groundbreaking, highly influential papers, most papers are neither groundbreaking nor highly influential. I have written over 100 scientific articles, and by my own modest guess at least 80 of those are completely irrelevant in the grand scheme of things, and probably more. My own measure for acceptable performance in a given year is that I publish about one paper to which I can point and say “probably more than 10 people will read this and actually care.” Over a 15-year career in science, that comes out to about 15-20 such papers, so I’m more or less on track.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Nevertheless, the vast majority of the papers I write, on average about 6 per year, are not that special and aren’t really read by anybody. So is there any reason to write them at all? Why not just write one big hit a year, or whenever it’s ready, and leave all the chaff unpublished?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality tends to correlate with quantity.&lt;/strong&gt; In your field, how many people do you know who publish one Nature or Science paper a year and not much else? I can think of maybe one or two people who have made that strategy work for them, but I’d argue that they are successful despite their publishing approach not because of it. For most people, productivity and impact tend to be correlated. The most prolific scientists also write the most widely-read papers and vice versa. It’s just like in the music business, you need to write a lot of songs to write a hit, and the people that write many hits also tend to write many many songs that aren’t hits. And, more importantly, it’s difficult to predict which song will be a hit and which will flop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me illustrate this idea with an example from my own career. In 2001 I wrote seven papers. Five of the seven have been quite successful, and have been cited over 50 times each. One of them, a Nature paper,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; is still one of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ&#34;&gt;most cited papers of all times&lt;/a&gt;, with &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;user=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ:u5HHmVD_uO8C&#34;&gt;about 400 citations&lt;/a&gt; according to Google Scholar. When we wrote that paper, I was pretty sure we had a big story, so the success of the paper was somewhat expected.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The second-most cited paper of that year, however, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scholar.google.com/citations?view_op=view_citation&amp;amp;citation_for_view=Nc8U6E4AAAAJ:Tyk-4Ss8FVUC&#34;&gt;which at present has about 100 citations&lt;/a&gt; and is my 13th most cited paper of all time, was a total surprise. Notably, this paper was also one of my fastest ever from original idea to submission. I had a cute idea one afternoon, did a few calculations for a day or two, wrote a simulation in a few more days, and after a little over a week the entire paper was done and out the door. When I submitted this paper, I had no idea whether it was even publishable. Yet it got printed, and people really liked it. For the other papers I wrote in 2001, I also was skeptical whether anybody would ever care about them, and in the end five of the seven did really well. It would have been easy for me to be more selective in 2001 and write only 2 or 3 papers, but if I had done that I’d have missed out on writing a couple of well-received papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leads me to lesson 1:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t know which of your papers other people will like. The more you publish, the higher the chance that &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; you write is useful to somebody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequent publishing builds an audience.&lt;/strong&gt; My next point applies to scientific publishing just as it does to blogging: You need to build an audience. If you regularly publish on a topic, people start taking notice. They will make it a habit to keep an eye on your work, even if they don’t spend a lot of time actually reading your papers. Then, when you finally publish something really good, you have an audience ready and waiting. The exact same paper, published by somebody nobody has never heard of, might not get the same reception. In fact (and I’m not saying this is right, just stating how things are), it might not even make it through review the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus here is lesson 2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to keep publishing regularly so people are aware of you and take you more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a limit to this, of course. If all you ever publish is useless drivel then you’ll eventually gain a reputation for publishing useless drivel. Stick to my guideline from the beginning of this post, publish at least one paper a year that is actually good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequent publishing develops skills.&lt;/strong&gt; My next point is also just like in blogging: You need to write a lot to get good at writing. With every paper you write, you get a little better. Therefore, even the papers that don’t really have any content of consequence, where you know only three people will ever read them,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are worth writing just for the exercise. Can you imagine you make a major discovery, a real breakthrough, and then you don’t have the skill to turn your results into an excellent paper? That’d be a disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, we arrive at lesson 3:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You need to publish as much as possible so you develop the writing and responding-to-reviewers skills that you will need to write your major hits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesson 3 applies particularly to students and young postdocs. They need all the practice they can get and hence should publish a lot, even if some of their papers turn out thin and inconsequential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publishing clears the mind.&lt;/strong&gt; My arguments so far can be summarized by saying that more publication quantity equals more publication quality. Some might raise the following objection: By writing fewer papers, they will say, they can put more effort into each one and hence raise the overall quality of their output. In other words, quantity can be detrimental to quality. I am not convinced by this argument. As I said earlier, one of my top-cited papers of all time took me all of two weeks to complete. At the same time, I could point you to papers that I put a huge amount of effort into and they never went anywhere. Impact doesn’t necessarily correlate with effort. More importantly, though, I believe that if one tries too hard to control quality both quality and quantity suffer. We need to publish papers so we are mentally ready to move on and write more, hopefully better, papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, ideas for papers can hurt your productivity if you get stuck on them. The most insidious ideas are the marginally good ones, the ones that aren’t so bad that they are easily dismissed out of hand but also aren’t good enough that you want to rush to publication. Those kinds of ideas can drag down your productivity for years, because they divert your attention and energy while not going anywhere. The best thing you can do with those ideas is to just publish them and move on. It’s so much easier to dismiss an idea as bad once the paper is out. I have plenty of papers on my cv where I’m the first to say they are pretty pointless.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But I don’t regret publishing them. If I hadn’t published these papers, maybe I’d still be thinking about the central ideas expressed in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, the final lesson:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best way to get a weak idea out of your head is to publish a paper on it. Don’t dwell on weak ideas, publish them and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There you have it, my reasons to keep publishing even though nobody reads (most) of my papers anyway. Now I’d like to hear from you: What are your reasons to publish or not to publish?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Until you realize that the argument I made was circular, because I arrived at ~80 irrelevant papers by assuming that I’m writing about 1 relevant paper a year, give or take.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;C. O. Wilke, J. L. Wang, C. Ofria, R. E. Lenski, and C. Adami (2001). Evolution of digital organisms at high mutation rate leads to survival of the flattest. Nature 412:331-333.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;To be honest, though, 400 citations and counting still blows me away. When we submitted the paper, I hoped that it would garner maybe 50 citations or so.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Those three being the two reviewers and the editor of the journal.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For example, everything I published in 1998 and 1999.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose the right lab for graduate school</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right lab for graduate school can be a daunting prospect. There are so many issues to consider. So many things that could go wrong. And you have to join the most prestigious lab you can get into, don’t you? Well, let’s consider for a moment what the main point of graduate school is. Graduate school is the time when you transition from being a student to being an independent scientist. It is primarily an educational experience. While in graduate school, you should pick up some subject-matter knowledge in your field. You should become familiar with the most important experimental or computational tools of your trade. You should learn how to choose scientific questions and how to solve them. You should develop general life skills such as how to communicate, how to work with other people, and how to get stuff done on time and to spec. So how do you find the right lab in which to acquire all these skills?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the most important overall consideration should be whether you feel comfortable with the PI, the other members of the lab, and the overall lab culture. In my mind, this is even more important than the specific research area the lab works in. Graduate school will usually take about five years, and it is an important time in your personal development. The people you meet in graduate school will likely remain colleagues and friends for the rest of your life. If you’re miserable the whole time, it’s going to be an awful experience. And even if you manage to power through the misery, you won’t have performed at your best. You could have done better elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, even in the best-case scenario, you can expect that something is going to happen over these five years that will challenge you or bring you down. Maybe a close friend or relative will die. Maybe you’ll experience a prolonged period of illness. Maybe you’ll get pregnant. Maybe you’ll go through a bad relationship breakup. Maybe you’ll just be generally disenchanted with science or with your project in particular. Maybe you’ll feel that you’re not getting enough done and that everybody else is progressing so much more quickly than you are. Whatever it’s going to be in your case, you can be certain that something is going to come your way. And when it happens, being in a lab that is supportive, helpful, and pleasant can make all the difference between a successful PhD and a premature termination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about building a competitive cv? Shouldn’t you go with the most famous lab, so you’ll get great publications and will be set for your future career in academia? I’m not convinced. If you’ve read my &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, you know that I believe all that matters career wise is that your cv is strong enough by the time you graduate that you’ll get the next job on your career path. If you’re on the academic track, that will usually mean 2-3 high-quality first-author publications, plus maybe a few more papers where you’ve made smaller contributions. In this context, “high-quality publications” means solid papers in recognized journals in your field. It does not mean Nature, Science, Cell, or PNAS. (While those won’t hurt, they’re generally not needed to get a good postdoc.) If you’re not on the academic track, the requirements aren’t that different. They aren’t stricter for sure, so for the purpose of choosing the right graduate program and lab it’s probably best to just pretend you’re on the academic track. So, if the main goal is 2-3 high-quality first-author publications, this is totally achievable in many labs all around the world. Even in labs that aren’t that well known, in universities that aren’t that highly ranked, students routinely perform at this level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, don’t obsess too much about the prestige of the university. Prestige is overrated at the graduate level. (It is much more important at the postdoc level.) Even the most prestigious labs in the most prestigious places frequently hire postdocs from all sorts of universities. This happens because the prestigious labs tend to employ many postdocs, often many more than they produce graduate students, and therefore they simply cannot fill all their positions with graduates from comparably prestigious labs. As long as you graduate with a competitive cv (see above), you’ll most likely be fine and get a good postdoc position. My personal opinion is that any university within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2013.html&#34;&gt;top 200&lt;/a&gt; of the world university rankings will probably be just fine for graduate school. I got my PhD from a university ranked somewhere past 300, and I still managed to get a good job, at a university that is consistently ranked in the top 40 worldwide and in the top 10 nationwide in my field. I’m not saying here that getting a PhD from a higher ranked institution won’t help you. I just think that it’s not as important as you may think it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to this issue, I would like to emphasize that choosing a lab for graduate school requires very different considerations than choosing a lab for a postdoc. My advice in this post is specifically for graduate students; I may write an article for postdocs at a later date. Some labs are really good for graduate students but not that great for postdocs. Some labs are the other way round. Some labs are great for everybody, but those are much rarer and may be highly competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I would be wary of very large labs that are staffed primarily with postdocs and senior scientists. In such labs, it’s not uncommon for graduate students to be treated as second-class citizens that need to fend for themselves. If you’re in that kind of a lab, you may rarely see your PI. Your day-to-day supervision—if there is any—is likely going to come from a postdoc. At that point, you may be getting worse supervision than you would have gotten had you gone with an inexperienced, first-year faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All else being equal, I would urge you to choose the lab that publishes more. If you’re in a lab that publishes a lot, chances are you’re going to be publishing a lot as well. By contrast, if you’re in a lab that publishes rarely, don’t expect to see your name in print that often. In fact, it’s not uncommon for a weaker student in a very productive lab to build a better track record than a stronger student might do in a lab that doesn’t like to commit words to print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you go with a junior faculty member or with a more established person? There are arguments for either route. If you go with a junior faculty member, you are more likely to get a lot of personal attention. You have the chance to build a lab from the ground up and to get your name on that lab’s important early papers. Most of the early students of scientists who became famous rose to fame with them. Of course, the early students of scientists who didn’t become famous didn’t, so take that for what it’s worth. The argument for an older, more established person is that that person is more of a known quantity. You can evaluate that person’s productivity, impact on the field, mentoring philosophy, and lab culture. The older adviser is also more likely to have connections that may be beneficial to you, and he/she is less likely to make rookie mistakes. Finally, a younger adviser might end up competing with you if you turn out to be really good. By the same token, an older, very established adviser may suck up much of the available grant money in an entire field. Once you leave the lab, you will have to change field and/or develop a clearly unique and distinct identity to remain competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people worry about joining a younger professor’s lab since he or she might not get tenure. I don’t think this risk is particularly high, unless you’re at a school known for never giving tenure. Of course, be careful if the writing is on the wall and there are rumors that the person whose lab you’re considering may not get tenure. In all other cases, I wouldn’t worry much about the tenure situation. Also, keep in mind that if you go with a famous and established tenured professor it’s not certain either that they will stay for five years at the same place. They might get hired away while you’re in graduate school, and that experience could be almost as stressful as your professor not getting tenure. So don’t decide against a lab out of fear, decide for the lab that overall seems to be the best fit for you. If that turns out to be the lab of an old, established professor, you’ll likely be fine. And if it is the lab of a junior person, you’ll likely be fine as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you need to be aware that there are generally two types of graduate programs: those that have a rotation system and those that don’t. If there is a rotation system, you rotate with 2-4 labs in your first year, and then you decide in which lab to pursue your PhD work. If there is not, then you get accepted into the program under the assumption that you’ll join a specific lab. The advantage of the rotation system is that you can test-drive a lab before joining. The disadvantage is that if none of the rotations work out, or if you don’t get rotation spots in your preferred labs, you may end up in a lab you don’t like or in no lab at all. If there’s no rotation system, then you have to decide on a lab without really knowing much about it. In the latter types of programs, you can set up your own rotation system of sorts by asking to be co-advised by two or three faculty members. After about a year, you can then decide whether you want to stay in the co-advised situation or whether you’d rather just work with one particular faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I don’t think it matters too much whether you join a program with a rotation system or not. Either way, I would encourage you to get to know the labs in the program ahead of time, and to only join a graduate program if multiple participating labs look attractive to you. Regardless of how wisely you choose your initial lab, you may reach a point where you have to switch, and at that point it’s good to have alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How good is good enough?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/10/how-good-is-good-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/10/how-good-is-good-enough/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other day, I wrote a blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;critical decision points in an academic career.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/&#34;&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt; felt that I was perpetuating the belief that being “good enough” is a necessary requirement to becoming a faculty member. My intention in writing the post was actually the exact opposite, to argue that whether somebody is or is not “good enough” is largely irrelevant to their success in academia, and not something they should spend much time thinking about. Clearly I didn’t quite succeed in getting my points across, so I’ll try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RELenski&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@RELenski&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You know, I really disagree with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@clauswilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; phrasing: “Are you good enough to be a faculty member?” even in context here.
&lt;/p&gt;
— Titus Brown (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ctitusbrown&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown/status/377436924710907904&#34;&gt;September 10, 2013&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RELenski&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@RELenski&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ClausWilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Perpetuates belief (unproven) that “being good” is even &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for being faculty, much less sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;
— Titus Brown (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ctitusbrown&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown/status/377437139094355968&#34;&gt;September 10, 2013&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to Malcom Gladwell’s threshold theory,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which argues that beyond a certain minimum required amount of innate talent, professional success is largely independent of talent and depends instead on numerous other factors, such as the amount of training you receive and the opportunities that come your way. In a nutshell, according to Gladwell, you can’t groom the village idiot into becoming a faculty member at Harvard, but any incoming graduate student in any decent university likely has the innate talent necessary to get there.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; From there on out, it’s all just effort, proper coaching, the right connections, and some amount of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There can be no doubt that luck is important for professional success, in particular on the road to getting a tenure-track position.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Many pieces have to fall into place, many of which may not have anything to do with who you are and what you can do. If you’re on the job market in a recession, when there are virtually no faculty searches going on, it’s going to be tough regardless of your track record. If suddenly a new hot area opens up and you happen to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work in that area, it may be difficult to convince departments that you’re the right candidate. My own trajectory reflects this. Without luck, I wouldn’t be a faculty member at UT Austin today. I got my job because Josh Plotkin’s wife needed to be close to a medical school, and UT Austin didn’t have one at the time. So Josh declined my department’s offer, even though it was his first choice. If Josh had been married to a different wife or not at all, or if UT Austin had been ten years ahead of their current schedule to getting a medical school, my life might be very different today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I do subscribe to the idea that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/3304496/Be-lucky-its-an-easy-skill-to-learn.html&#34;&gt;luck is a skill.&lt;/a&gt; I’ve seen this countless times with colleagues, friends, and family. Some people are just consistently lucky. They always seem to make out alright. And others appear to be consistently unlucky. Something always goes wrong for them, no matter what they do. As somebody who (I believe) falls on the luckier side of the spectrum, and also as somebody who has a good sense of how actions connect to possible outcomes,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I can usually spot the behavioral patterns that cause people to be lucky or unlucky. Show me somebody who is &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; unlucky, and I’ll tell you what they’re doing wrong. It would take more than a few lines in this already far-too-long blog post to explain specifics. So I’ll defer that for another time. For now, if you think you’re consistently lucky, keep doing whatever it is you’re doing. If you think you’re consistently unlucky, you probably have a tendency to use the wrong priorities in your decision making. You might make decisions out of fear, or out of a desire for pleasure, or for immediate benefit, rather than based on a rational assessment of the long-term consequences of your decisions. It might help you to discuss your decisions with a thoughtful mentor, &lt;em&gt;and to listen to her advice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get back to the original question. What does it take to become a faculty member? First, you need some amount of innate talent. If you’re still reading, and you’re not constantly thinking “so many complicated words,” you probably have sufficient innate talent. Second, you need some genuine luck. For example, you accidentally meet somebody at a conference who turns out to be really supportive of your work; or you make a genuinely unexpected, major discovery; or your major competitor falls while rock-climbing and is out for a year, just when you go onto the job market. Third, you need some engineered luck. You need to see opportunities when they come your way and take advantage of them. When issues arise that could cause you trouble down the road, you need to deal with them efficiently and effectively. You generally have to behave in such a way that you’re not your own worst enemy. Fourth, you need to be willing to put in the required effort. The impressiveness of a cv is strongly correlated to the amount of work expended to developing said cv, and nothing is ever going to change that. And fifth, you need to have the resilience to slog through the downturns that you will inevitably encounter on your path in academia. There will be times when nothing seems to go right, when no reviewer likes your papers or grant proposals, when you feel you’re just spinning your wheels with nothing to show for. You will have to work through these periods to be successful in academia.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of those five points fall under your control? The first does not. However, you’re still reading, so that point is irrelevant. The second doesn’t either. There’s nothing you can do about genuine luck or genuine misfortune. So don’t spend any time thinking about it. The other three points fall under your control, and they contribute (by my own, totally unscientific estimate) to at least 70%-80% of your success. So get cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The threshold theory is described in Gladwell’s book “Outliers.” It’s a great book. If you haven’t read it yet, do so.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realistically, if you start with serious coaching only in graduate school it may be too late for star-level success. The kids that were groomed to become Harvard professors when they were three years old will have an enormous head start, one that may be difficult to catch up to. You should still try, though.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this note, I find it interesting how many faculty members who are now among the most established scientists in their field were at some point close to giving up on academia. For example, Richard Lenski describes his winding path to &lt;a href=&#34;http://telliamedrevisited.wordpress.com/2013/09/09/the-good-old-days/&#34;&gt;his first faculty appointment here.&lt;/a&gt; I heard about this story first when I was on the job market and thought I’d never find a decent job, and I found it strangely comforting.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.16personalities.com/intj-personality&#34;&gt;INTJ.&lt;/a&gt; My mind is all about possibilities, and how they are connected to what’s happening right now.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course the main issue here is to distinguish between constructively slogging through a temporary setback and delusionally keeping on going even though the situation is truly hopeless. I hope my &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; can help there. As should any capable adviser or mentor.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should you list on your cv a paper that is in review or in preparation?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/10/should-you-list-a-paper-in-review-or-in-preparation-on-your-cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/10/should-you-list-a-paper-in-review-or-in-preparation-on-your-cv/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend that junior scientists (and even senior scientists) list submitted papers on their cv. The main reason is the inevitable delay between when a project is done and when a paper finally comes out. If I see a cv with no publications in the last year, I don’t know if that is because the person got lazy or because there are five papers in the pipeline that just haven’t made their way out of review yet. If I see a couple of papers listed as “submitted” or “in review” it gives me confidence that the person hasn’t gotten lazy yet. Also, from the titles of the papers, I can get a sense of where the person’s work is going at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some might be concerned that a paper that isn’t formally accepted isn’t quite a paper yet, since it doesn’t yet have the official stamp of approval. Therefore it shouldn’t be on the cv. After all, it might never see the light of day. This kind of reasoning does not really reflect reality. As far as I can tell, if a paper has been submitted it might as well have been published, because realistically most papers that get submitted will get published eventually. I have published over 100 papers, and throughout my entire career I can recall maybe 3 or 4 cases where I gave up on a paper after review. I see similar statistics as a reviewer or editor: Most papers that come my way and that I consider to be of insufficient quality to appear in print do so anyway, eventually. So I’m going to argue that maybe 5% of papers get submitted somewhere but never formally appear, while the remaining 95% are on track to becoming published works. I’m a theoretical physicist, and to me 95% is close enough to 100% that I don’t care about the difference. Once a paper has been submitted, I count it as a published paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument becomes even stronger if a senior scientist is a coauthor on the paper. If that senior person generally publishes solid works, and if he or she agreed to submission of the article with their name on it, chances are it is a solid piece of work as it currently stands. Reviewers may still have some issues that they’re going to nitpick over. However, realistically reviewers are wrong as often as they are right, and why should I give more credence to some random, anonymous reviewer than to the senior person whose work I respect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one caveat, though: The number of papers listed on your cv as “in review” should be commensurate to your typical publication output. If you have published two papers a year for the last three years and you list 20 that are in review, I will be skeptical about the quality of those papers and will wonder whether maybe your success rate from submission to publication is not near 100%. But if you usually publish two papers a year and you list three in review, that looks reasonable and I won’t give it a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I view papers “in preparation” differently, however. “In preparation” means nothing. A paper that is submitted must have gotten to the point where at least one, and usually several, scientists felt it could be published in principle. A paper in preparation could be nowhere near that point, and it might never get there. I certainly have had plenty of papers in my life that were “in preparation” and eventually transitioned to “nobody even remembers what the project was supposed to be about.” If I listed all of those papers on my current cv, it’d probably be twice as long and half as useful. If you have a paper in preparation that you really want to list on your cv, then hurry up, get it done, and submit it. And put it on a preprint server, too, so you and others can cite it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From undergraduate to faculty member: Critical decision points in the academic career</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re an undergraduate contemplating an academic career or a graduate student considering the next steps, you may have the long-term goal of becoming a tenured professor at a major research university. At the same time, you may have serious doubts about whether this is the career for you. Are you good enough to be a faculty member? And if you’re not good enough, will you waste years of your life with little to show for it in the end? Even if you’re good enough, is that sufficient, or will you also need an extraordinary amount of luck? By embarking on an academic career, will you be making a high-stakes gamble that may have a catastrophic outcome if you lose? These are serious doubts, and they can make the prospects of pursuing an academic career seem overwhelming and pointless. As a substitute for these overwhelming, larger-than-life questions, I’d like to offer a set of critical decision points and simple rules about how to proceed. I hope that these suggestions will make the path to an academic position more navigable and less stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first clarify, though, that I don’t think every graduate student has to become a tenured professor at a major university. In fact, I believe that the majority of graduate students are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on track to become faculty members. For example, I read about a case study once where of an entering class of 20 graduate students at Yale university, only 2 had a tenure-track career 10 years later (I’m recalling this from memory, so I may have some details wrong, but the gist was approximately that.) Losing that many students to pursuits other than pure academia is Ok, as long as the majority of them finds satisfying and appropriately compensated employment. And I’m pretty sure they do. They certainly do if they picked up serious computational skills during their PhD. On the other hand, while I don’t see it as my mission to turn every student of mine into a professor, I also don’t want to see highly gifted and capable students give up on an academic career just because they perceive it as an impossible feat, one they shouldn’t even attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-undergraduate-to-graduate-student&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From undergraduate to graduate student&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re currently an undergraduate, you shouldn’t even think about whether you’re on track to becoming a professor. It’s impossible to know anyway, and it doesn’t matter for the main decision you have to make: Should you go to graduate school or not? Unless you are under strong financial pressure to earn money right away (e.g. you have enormous student debt, or you have three children that you have to support on your own), this decision should not primarily be a financial one. For most students, graduate school is approximately cost-neutral: The stipend you’re paid while working as teaching assistant or graduate research assistant covers your basic living expenses. You don’t save any money while you’re in graduate school, but you also shouldn’t accumulate any debt. You could think about graduate school in terms of income lost over five years versus your future earnings potential, but frankly, if you think in these terms I don’t think a graduate program in science is right for you. Get a graduate degree in business, economics, or management, and embark on a career of serious money making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A graduate degree in science is for people who really care about figuring things out, or about solving problems. As an undergraduate, you have to be aware that graduate school will be very different from your undergraduate experience, unless you’ve already spent a substantial amount of time in a research lab. Graduate school is not about passing exams, getting good grades, or cramming material. In the end, it’s all about doing science and writing papers. Some people have a 4.0 undergraduate GPA and fail in graduate school, and others have a 2.9 GPA and succeed. If you really care about figuring things out, if you could see yourself spending months at a time getting to the bottom of an issue, then graduate school is for you. Don’t worry about the naysayers that say a PhD is a worthless piece of paper. I am not aware of any evidence that a PhD in science will &lt;em&gt;hurt&lt;/em&gt; your subsequent employability. It may not help you much, depending on how things go, but as I said already, you shouldn’t get into a PhD program for the money anyway. You should get into it because of your passion for research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-graduate-student-to-postdoc&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From graduate student to postdoc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, you’ve now made your way almost all the way through graduate school and the end is in sight. Should you continue and search for a postdoc position? Or should you jump ship and look for alternatives? At this point, I think it is justified to ask about earnings potential. You have obtained the most advanced degree you’ll ever get. From here on out, you’re not in it for the education, you’re in it for the experience. You have to ask yourself: Would I rather make money, or would I rather do nothing but research for a few years? For most academics, the postdoc time is a uniquely rewarding and free time. A time during which you can (mostly) freely pursue whatever research you care about, on your own schedule. You have completed your 10,000 hours of science by that time, so you can hit the ground running and do interesting stuff. For poor compensation, mind you. If your mindset is “I don’t really know what else I’d want to do anyway” then go ahead and do a postdoc. But if you can see a clear alternative path, and if that path looks attractive to you, then that alternative path may be the better choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, though, it is still not time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member. Plenty of graduate students don’t do that well, only to recover spectacularly during their postdoc. And others do well as graduate students but falter as postdocs. Generally, the former group does much better than the latter on the academic job market. I’m part of the former group, and I made out alright. I like to say that if you erased from my resume every single thing I did during graduate school, nothing of consequence would change. I got a job as a faculty member anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do have to make an honest assessment, though. Where do you stand relative to your fellow graduate students? Would you say your performance is comparable to most? Better? Worse? After five years in graduate school, you may not yet have made an earth-shattering discovery, but you should know by now whether you’re cut out for science or not. In particular, do you have one or two papers to your name for which you did the majority of the work, including the conceptual work? (I don’t care how good they are, just that they got done.) If after an honest assessment you find that you’re not really cut out for science, then don’t do a postdoc. Find a different occupation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of hope for finding a postdoc position: For as long as I can remember, the job market has been in favor of postdocs. Any capable graduate student who wants to can find a decent postdoc position. So don’t ever worry about not getting a postdoc position. If you want one, you’ll get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-postdoc-to-faculty-member&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From postdoc to faculty member&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re two to three years into your postdoc. Finally it’s time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member or not. Take honest stock. Where are you, compared to other people in the field that you’d be competing with on the job market. Ask some senior scientists about an honest evaluation. Hopefully your postdoc adviser will be able to tell you where you stand. In my opinion, if you’re three years into a postdoc and you’re nowhere near ready to apply for a faculty position, then it may be time to consider alternative careers. If you’re three years in and you’re ready to apply, then go for it and see how it goes. If you’re three years in and you’re getting close but you’re not quite there yet, then it’d be reasonable to wait another year. But don’t keep saying “I’ll be ready next year.” At some point, if things don’t work out in academia, you have to cut your losses and move on. Where that point is is a somewhat arbitrary and a bit of a personal choice, but I’d place it around five years. After five years of a postdoc-level position, you should find something more permanent. And if that job is not a tenure-track faculty position, then you may have to settle for research scientist, lecturer, administrator, or whatever else you can make work for you. There are plenty of reasonable career paths for a scientist, just don’t become a career postdoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can’t expect things on the job market to work out the first time round. You may not be quite ready, the big paper you wrote may not yet be that well known, or it may just be a bad year for academic hiring. If by your own and by your senior colleagues’ assessment you are ready to get a faculty position, then don’t despair if it doesn’t work out the first time round. Try at least two rounds. Also, if you changed your field after your PhD, or if you didn’t really do much of consequence as a graduate student, you may need a little more time as a postdoc. I was a postdoc for five years, and I think I needed that time to be really ready for a faculty position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As undergraduate, follow your passion. If you have a passion for figuring things out, get a graduate degree and see if you still like it five years down the road. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As graduate student, if your passion hasn’t disappeared, and if you can stomach another three to five years of being poor, go for the postdoc. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As postdoc, do an honest assessment of where you stand. If you are competitive on the job market, go for it. If you’re almost competitive, do what needs to be done to eliminate the “almost.” If you’re nowhere near competitive after about three years, start thinking about alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
