<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Professional development on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/categories/Professional-development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Professional development on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/Professional-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Share your preliminary work with other people, even if you think it’s crap</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/07/08/share-your-preliminary-work-with-other-people-even-if-you-think-its-crap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/07/08/share-your-preliminary-work-with-other-people-even-if-you-think-its-crap/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s quite common for me to have students tell me “the analysis didn’t work out” or “the figure looks bad” or “I don’t have any useful results.” And it’s also quite common for the students to be wrong. Sometimes, students have amazing results but are all disappointed because the results aren’t what they had expected. These students fail to see the data for what they are. More commonly, the students may be right in that the data aren’t that great, but usually I can see something in the data that the student didn’t. In either case, it is important that we look at the data together, because jointly we will see more than either of us individually would have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while some students are happy to show me their “failed” analyses and complain about how nothing works, others are more reserved, sometimes to the point of reluctance. The latter students don’t feel comfortable showing me their preliminary results, or sometimes any results at all, unless they think the work is completed.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; These students are probably under the mistaken impression that I will judge them for “failed” analyses, or that I expect a complete analysis, with proper interpretation of all data points, at all times, or that having remaining open questions means I’ll think the student did a poor job. On the contrary, I want to see all these preliminary, incomplete, and confusing results. The data are the data, and I want to be able to draw my own conclusions about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I submit that unless you know for sure you made a mistake (say, your code has a bug and you know it), you will always be better off discussing your work with other people than silently deciding it’s not good enough. And if your results seem too trivial or wrong to talk about them with your advisor, then at least talk them through with a fellow student or postdoc.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Think about it this way: every time you generate a result or make a figure, and then you delete it before you show it to somebody else, you’re preempting the possibility that somebody else might see something useful in your work. And while a lot of what you’re doing may indeed be worthless, I’d argue that unless you’re a complete disaster, you’ll probably do at least one thing every day that is actually worthwhile. So every day, you should produce some sort of result that you then discuss with somebody else.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the necessity of sharing preliminary work with other people doesn’t stop once you graduate. Just because you have a PhD doesn’t mean that you’re suddenly able to always see the data exactly for what they are. Sometimes even the most experienced scientists are overly attached to a particular hypothesis or miss some critical detail in their data. That’s why many experienced scientists routinely talk to their colleagues about work in progress, why they present preliminary results at conferences or seminar talks, and why they request comments on manuscript drafts and preprints. In my mind, even traditional peer review serves primarily the purpose of having another set of eyes look over the data and check whether the authors are over- or underhyping their results.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing that really changes once you graduate and/or complete your postdoc is that suddenly there is no adviser anymore who makes you show him/her your latest work. Now it’s entirely on you to seek out the advice you need and to receive the feedback that will make your work better. And, if you are advising students yourself, it’s now your job to make them talk to you and show you what they’re doing, warts and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re my student and you think this blog post is about you, let me tell you: you’re not the only one.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;But realize that sometimes students talk each other down. Just because your fellow grad students say what you did was stupid doesn’t mean it actually was; they may just lack perspective.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might argue that you’re working in a field where results accumulate slowly, hence you can’t possibly discuss results from individual days. E.g., you’re collecting beetles in the field, and you need three field seasons before you have enough data to test your hypothesis. My response is that nevertheless there are tons of preliminary data that you should discuss with somebody. E.g., if you’re collecting beetles every day, you know how many you found each day, where you found them, what physical characteristics they had, etc., and how these quantities change over time. All of these are worthwhile preliminary results that you should look at, graph, and discuss with a third party.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second case, where reviewers see more in the data than the authors, is more common than you may think. Many papers get really good only after a solid round of peer review, and frequently the reviews in those cases are not “X is wrong” but rather “You have done X but you should also do Y, and in combination you could conclude Z which would be really cool.”&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to develop a research question, Part II</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/18/how-to-develop-a-research-question-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/18/how-to-develop-a-research-question-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After my last post discussing &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2014/6/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question&#34;&gt;how to develop a research question&lt;/a&gt;, Sergey Kryazhimskiy asked me to write about how to find the rare good research idea among the many mediocre ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ClausWilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; After 2 successful projects the problem shifts to choosing a rare good research idea among many mediocre ones. Next post? 2/2
&lt;/p&gt;
— Sergey Kryazhimskiy (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@skryazhi&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/skryazhi/status/478349857540042753&#34;&gt;June 16, 2014&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that I don’t really know how to do this. If you do, please tell me. I’m sure I could strengthen my research program by picking better problems. Nevertheless, despite my ignorance, I’ve had a reasonably successful career to date. And it was probably not entirely due to sheer luck. So this should give you hope. Even if you don’t know how to pick good problems, you may succeed in science nonetheless. Just work on the problems that seem important to you and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I don’t know how to answer Sergey’s question, at first I thought that I wouldn’t have much to say on this topic. However, not knowing something hasn’t kept me from writing a 1500-word blog post about it. After some pondering, I thought it might be useful to review what other people have said on this topic. If you spend some time with Google, you’ll find expert advice on how to choose a good research problem. For example, in Uri Alon’s paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://wws.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/uploads/nurturing/howtochoosegoodproblem.pdf&#34;&gt;“How To Choose a Good Scientiﬁc Problem”&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; there is a nice graphic (here reproduced as Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;) ranking potential problems according to their difficulty (hard to easy) and according to the gain in knowledge their solution would provide (small to large). Easy problems with a small gain in knowledge are good beginner problems, hard problems with a large gain in knowledge are good long-term goals for an established researcher, and easy problems with a large gain in knowledge are perfect for a postdoc. And nobody should work on hard problems that lead to small gains in knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pareto front of worthwhile research questions. Research questions can be ranked according to difficulty (hard to easy) and gain in knowledge (small to large). The best problems are those that provide the maximum gain of knowledge for the chosen difficulty level. One should never work on hard problems that provide little gain in knowledge. After U. Alon (2009).&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Pareto front of worthwhile research questions. Research questions can be ranked according to difficulty (hard to easy) and gain in knowledge (small to large). The best problems are those that provide the maximum gain of knowledge for the chosen difficulty level. One should never work on hard problems that provide little gain in knowledge. After U. Alon (2009).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all nice and well, until you realize that it is basically impossible to rank problems &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; along either dimension. Uri Alon’s paper explains why. Science does not normally progress in a direct path from A to B. We may intend to work towards B, but on our way there we get stuck in “the cloud,” where every attempt to get closer to B fails, until eventually we give up and go for C, a problem that we hadn’t even considered beforehand (Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;). The two immediate consequences of this process are that (i) we don’t know how hard it will be to get from A to C, and (ii) we don’t know how much of a gain in knowledge C will provide, in both cases because we don’t even know C exists when we start. Thus, even though Uri Alon’s ranking of problems along difficulty and gain in knowledge is beautiful and convincing, it is also quite useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure2&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;How we would like to do science (left) and how it actually works (right). Here, A represents what we currently know and B represents what we would like to know. Our desire is to move from A to B in as direct a line as possible. However, we usually get stuck as we are approaching B, things don’t work out, and we keep taking detours and going in circles. Uri Alon calls this state the cloud. Eventually, we give up on reaching B and instead head for C, a new insight that we found while wandering in the cloud. Usually, C represents the solution to a problem we weren’t even aware of when we started. After U. Alon (2009).&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 2: How we would like to do science (left) and how it actually works (right). Here, A represents what we currently know and B represents what we would like to know. Our desire is to move from A to B in as direct a line as possible. However, we usually get stuck as we are approaching B, things don’t work out, and we keep taking detours and going in circles. Uri Alon calls this state &lt;em&gt;the cloud.&lt;/em&gt; Eventually, we give up on reaching B and instead head for C, a new insight that we found while wandering in the cloud. Usually, C represents the solution to a problem we weren’t even aware of when we started. After U. Alon (2009).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can be done? If we keep reading Uri Alon’s article, we find that he makes some useful suggestions on how to pick important problems. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental aspects of science is that the interest of a problem is subjective and personal. (…) Ranking problems with consideration to the inner voice makes you more likely to choose problems that will satisfy you in the long term. (…) One way to help listening to the inner voice is to ask: ‘‘If I was the only person on earth, which of these problems would I work on?’’ (…) Another good sign of the inner voice are ideas and questions that come back again and again to your mind for months or years. (…) It is remarkable that listening to our own idiosyncratic voice leads to better science. It makes research self-motivated and the routine of research more rewarding. In science, the more you interest yourself, the larger the probability that you will interest your audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you’re not sure which problems to work on, work on the ones that excite you!&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uri Alon is not the only one who has commented on this topic. The famous computer-science pioneer Richard Hamming (of the Hamming distance and Hamming codes) used to give a talk entitled “You and Your Research,” which touches on this issue among other things. You can read a transcript &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The whole thing is worth reading. Here, I’ll just cite a few relevant paragraphs. First this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are famous it is hard to work on small problems. This is what did Shannon in. After information theory, what do you do for an encore? The great scientists often make this error. They fail to continue to plant the little acorns from which the mighty oak trees grow. They try to get the big thing right off. And that isn’t the way things go. So that is another reason why you find that when you get early recognition it seems to sterilize you. In fact I will give you my favorite quotation of many years. The Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, in my opinion, has ruined more good scientists than any institution has created, judged by what they did before they came and judged by what they did after. Not that they weren’t good afterwards, but they were superb before they got there and were only good afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, don’t try too hard to make a big splash. Just keep working on a variety of problems and see which ones turn out to be useful. While you do so, take notice of things that repeatedly don’t work. Those may be hints that can lead to major insights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that if you look carefully you will see that often the great scientists, by turning the problem around a bit, changed a defect to an asset. For example, many scientists when they found they couldn’t do a problem finally began to study why not. They then turned it around the other way and said, “But of course, this is what it is” and got an important result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, keep an eye out for great opportunities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great scientists, when an opportunity opens up, get after it and they pursue it. They drop all other things. They get rid of other things and they get after an idea because they had already thought the thing through. Their minds are prepared; they see the opportunity and they go after it. Now of course lots of times it doesn’t work out, but you don’t have to hit many of them to do some great science. It’s kind of easy. One of the chief tricks is to live a long time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can you do to increase the chance that opportunities come your way? Here is Feynman’s suggestion, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/199701/comm-rota.pdf&#34;&gt;as recounted by Gian-Carlo Rota&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to keep a dozen of your favorite problems constantly present in your mind, although by and large they will lay in a dormant state. Every time you hear or read a new trick or a new result, test it against each of your twelve problems to see whether it helps. Every once in a while there will be a hit, and people will say, “How did he do it? He must be a genius!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is thus to wander around in the cloud and always keep an eye out for exciting opportunities that may open up. While you’re in the cloud, aiming for B, there may be many C’s that come your way that you could pursue, but most of them will not be worthwhile (Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;). However, on occasion, you stumble upon something that is really neat (C&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; in the Figure), and when that happens you should drop everything else and pursue that opportunity. I would recommend applying the following test: Do you personally think you’ve stumbled upon an exciting opportunity? If yes, go for it. If no, keep looking for something else to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Scientific opportunities in the cloud. While we are stuck in the cloud, we encounter all sorts of new insights. Most of them are boring, however, and we shouldn’t pursue them further. But, on occasion, we stumble upon an exciting new insight. When this happens, great scientists drop everything else and seize the opportunity.&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 3: Scientific opportunities in the cloud. While we are stuck in the cloud, we encounter all sorts of new insights. Most of them are boring, however, and we shouldn’t pursue them further. But, on occasion, we stumble upon an exciting new insight. When this happens, great scientists drop everything else and seize the opportunity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this whole process, you might wonder what’s the point of B. If we never get to B, do we need it in the first place? I think we do. B gives us a broad sense of direction while we’re not sure where we’re going in the cloud. Until we have identified an exciting opportunity C, we might as well keep chasing B. Who knows, with luck, we might even manage to get to B at some point. It happens on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;U. Alon (2009) &lt;a href=&#34;http://wws.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/uploads/nurturing/howtochoosegoodproblem.pdf&#34;&gt;How To Choose a Good Scientiﬁc Problem.&lt;/a&gt; Mol. Cell 35:726-728.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should be noted here that the degree to which a problem is of interest to the broader scientific community depends also on how well it is marketed. You can pick problems you know the community finds interesting, or alternatively you can convince the community that they should find interesting what you are working on. Many of the very successful scientists do the latter. In fact, fame and recognition often go to the person who convinced the community that a problem was worthwhile, not to the person who actually solved the problem in the first place.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamming gave this talk many times. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&#34;&gt;transcript available here&lt;/a&gt; is from March 7, 1986. There is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a1zDuOPkMSw&#34;&gt;video recording,&lt;/a&gt; from June 6, 1995. The transcript and the video are largely identical, but I found that the video added a few interesting points that weren’t in the transcript.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;G.-C. Rota (1997) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/199701/comm-rota.pdf&#34;&gt;Ten Lessons I Wish I Had Been Taught.&lt;/a&gt; Notices of the AMS 44:22-25.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to develop a research question</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most daunting prospects for a fresh graduate student is having to develop a solid research question.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In my experience, many graduate students feel like they don’t even know where to start. The literature can seem overwhelming, everything has already be done by somebody, and in any case it’s impossible to really know all the literature there is anyway. Making matters worse, almost every cohort or lab inevitably has one or two students who just seem to be fountains of good ideas, who constantly come up with new research ideas they want to pursue. As a result, students who are less inventive or less imaginative can feel like they’re not cut out for a career in research, they’re never going to have the necessary ideas to sustain a research program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that having good ideas is a skill that can be learned. There are simple strategies that almost always work. In the following, I describe one strategy in particular that I’ve found useful over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;define-a-vision-for-your-research&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Define a vision for your research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you start doing any concrete work towards developing your specific research question, you need to know what broad topic you want to work on. I call this the research vision. It turns out that developing a research vision is not that hard, for two reasons: First, the vision doesn’t have to be that specific; it doesn’t have to come with specific ideas for projects you want to do or questions you want to pursue. It’s just a guiding idea that tells you where to start. For example, a vision could be “I want to do computational work in cancer genomics” or “I want to study experimentally how bacteria adapt to novel environments” or “I want to work in infectious disease epidemiology.” Second, choosing a particular vision over another one is generally a low-stakes decision. There is interesting and valuable research to be done in the context of nearly any reasonable research vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing you should double-check though, in particular as graduate student or postdoc, is whether the vision you want to pursue fits broadly into the topics your lab is working on. If you’re in a molecular biology lab that studies cancer genetics but your research vision is to investigate the effects of climate change on future precipitation patterns then you have a problem. In this situation, either find a different research vision or consider switching labs.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;read-the-literature&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have decided on your research vision, you need to start reading the relevant literature. There are two ways to proceed: First, if your research vision matches well with the work that is already going on in the lab you’re in, then start by reading the lab’s papers. Also, ask your PI for suggestions on which papers to read. Use all these papers as your starting point for a careful literature search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if your research vision deviates somewhat from the current direction of the lab,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or if there are other reasons why you can’t ask anybody for relevant papers, then skip right ahead to the literature search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start your literature search, enter some key words or phrases into Google Scholar and see what comes up. Google Scholar tends to place the most highly cited papers at the top of its search results, so you’ll almost never go wrong by looking into the top hits. Using these papers as your starting point, expand your search by reading the papers that they cite (searching backwards in time), and also look up the more recent papers that cite them (searching forward in time).&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; By alternating between backwards and forwards search you will develop a solid grasp of the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to Google Scholar, the “related citations” function on PubMed is also an excellent way to deepen your knowledge of the field. Look up a paper on PubMed, and then read through the papers that PubMed flags as related to the paper you looked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;stop-reading-the-literature-and-start-doing-something&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stop reading the literature and start doing something&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be a well-read scientist. Most students don’t read enough. There’s always something else to read. However, at some point, you have to stop reading and start doing. To give a concrete (but somewhat arbitrary) cutoff: If you’ve been reading for two months or more, or if you’re familiar with over 100 papers in your broad area, and you still feel like you don’t know enough of the literature to come up with your own project, then reading even more is likely not going to improve your situation much. At this point, it’s more important that you start doing actual research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you start if you’re not sure what your project is? My recommendation is to always start by reproducing somebody else’s work. Among all the papers in your broad area that you have read, pick one or two that you liked the most, and simply try to repeat what they did.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Very quickly, you will discover a few things: 1. It’s not that easy to reproduce existing work, and you can learn a lot in the process. 2. There are flaws, limitations, or pitfalls that weren’t really described in the paper. Maybe the paper’s methods work only under very specific conditions and fail the moment you try something slightly different. Or the methods are somewhat unreliable and fail at random times/under random conditions. 3. There are all sorts of things you’d like to know. Such as why the methods always fail when it’s raining outside. Or why there are certain strange trends you see in the raw data. 4. There are all sorts of things you’d like to have. Like a better way to prep your samples. Or some additional measurements no existing method can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voilà, you have your research question. In fact, you probably have more than you bargained for.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You may have so many questions that you still don’t know where to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;keep-it-simple&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keep it simple&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s important to keep things simple. Of the many open questions you have, pursue the one that requires the simplest possible extension to existing work but will still provide meaningful progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’ve ever seen a student fail for trying to do something too simple. However, I’ve seen plenty of student fail for trying things that were too complicated. Most students overestimate the complexity that is required to do good science. It’s better to do something simple, write it up, and publish than to do something complicated, get stuck, and get discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may think the whole process I propose is haphazard. I suggested you start with a random topic, do some reading, try to reproduce somebody’s work, and then pursue some extension to the work, an extension that will hopefully reveal itself to you as you work on the topic. The reason why this seems haphazard is because it is. Science doesn’t follow a simple A to B path. Albert Einstein famously said “If we knew what it was we were doing, it would not be called research.” Uri Alon calls it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/uri_alon_why_truly_innovative_science_demands_a_leap_into_the_unknown&#34;&gt;being stuck in the cloud.&lt;/a&gt; Donald Rumsfeld talked about the unknown unknowns. Even though Rumsfeld wasn’t talking about scientific research, he correctly described the world in which most scientists operate day to day. We usually don’t know what we’re doing, we don’t know where we’re going, and we don’t know what we don’t know. However, we do stuff anyway, and from time to time we stumble upon a useful and novel bit of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;And sometimes, postdocs or even young faculty members struggle with the same issue. It mostly depends on when you were asked for the first time to come up with your own project. If your graduate project was basically handed to you by your PI, and similarly during your postdoc you were working on somebody else’s project, then you may never have independently developed a project before becoming an assistant professor.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would almost always recommend against switching lab while in grad school, but that is a topic for a different post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It may seem strange that a graduate student would have her own research vision that differs from the lab’s vision. However, this scenario is often quite productive, both for the student and for the lab. The best PhD theses can take an entire lab into a new direction. PIs are generally aware of this and want their students to bring new ideas into the lab.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Searching forward in time used to be a complicated undertaking but it is trivial with tools such as Google Scholar. Simply click on “cited by” and see which other papers cite the paper you’re interested in.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, you have to choose a paper that uses methods and/or materials that you have access to. If your favorite paper in the field uses a mass spec and you don’t have access to one then that’s a bad paper to try to reproduce.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s one of the reasons why senior scientists usually have tons of research ideas. The longer you’ve been around in science, the more you’re aware of what we don’t know.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uri Alon on creativity and staying sane in science: &#34;Yes and ...&#34;</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/14/uri-alon-on-creativity-and-staying-sane-in-science-yes-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/14/uri-alon-on-creativity-and-staying-sane-in-science-yes-and/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just saw this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/uri_alon_why_truly_innovative_science_demands_a_leap_into_the_unknown&#34;&gt;nice TED Talk by Uri Alon&lt;/a&gt; about how new scientific insights are generated. Even though the talk is a year old I think it’s worth posting, so here you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uri makes a number of points that I’ve been aware of for a long time but have never seen expressed quite so clearly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discovery is not linear. We usually don’t obtain the result we were aiming for. However, as we try, we make worthwhile discoveries that constitute the real scientific progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not helpful to shoot down ideas before you’ve even tried them. Statements like “this is never going to work” “this is too complicated” “X, Y, and Z are going to go wrong” “nobody will believe me anyway” are all not useful. Accept the crazy ideas, try them out, and see what happens. Say “yes and …”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being worried about your research shuts down your creativity. Try to be more relaxed, even if things don’t go the way you think they should. Don’t try to obtain a particular goal, focus more on exploring the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When things don’t go well, talk to other people, look for support. Science can be hard on your mental well being, and to keep going sometimes you just need people to cheer you on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI, and 6 reasons not to</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the eternal questions of graduate schools is whether you should work with a junior or a senior PI. I have commented on this question before &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school&#34;&gt;and argued that either decision can be the right one.&lt;/a&gt; Here, I present a more comprehensive list of arguments for and against. As you’ll see, there are plenty of arguments going both ways. You may assign more weight to some than others and thus arrive at a decision that is best for you. Ultimately, I think it doesn’t matter too much; there are other factors that are more important, such as whether you enjoy and fit in with the lab’s culture and approach to research, collaboration, publication, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is my list. If you can think of something I forgot, please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the early students in the lab of a rising star, you can rise to prominence with your PI. You may end up as the first author in one or more of your PI’s key publications, and this in turn may secure your own faculty position and seniority in the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may have more time to supervise you. The lab is likely relatively small and you’re not competing with 10 other lab members for your PI’s attention. Also, your PI may not yet be that involved with university service and other non-research obligations, and thus have more time to interact with the lab (i.e., you).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A young lab may be doing some really novel, cutting-edge work. An older lab is more likely to work on the stuff they’ve always worked on, stuff that was real innovative 10 years ago but is an old hat now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your PI is not that established, there’s less risk that once you graduate your adviser is such a towering influence in the field that you can’t establish yourself as distinct from him/her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a large, established lab, you might find yourself working on a small part of a larger project. Even if you do excellent work, your name might in the end not get associated with the big paper that comes out of that work. (I’m not saying you won’t be a coauthor. I’m saying you might be one of 20 coauthors and nobody will think you were the person who made it happen.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The younger your adviser, the less likely it is that he or she come down with a debilitating disease or die a sudden death. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3298961/figure/fig2/&#34;&gt;the risk of death of a 60-year old man is 10 times higher than that of a 35-year old man.&lt;/a&gt; Just avoid younger PIs with a passion for BASE jumping, cave diving, or motorcycle racing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-senior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a senior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI is untested. It is less clear how sustainable the PI’s research program is, how likely the PI will be able to attract funding, and how good his/her research ideas are. If the junior PI is on a bad trajectory, it is likely that your PhD won’t be that great either. (Keep in mind, though, that your PI’s success depends to some extent on you!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the field. The two of you may find yourselves fighting uphill battles with reviewers, journal editors, and other labs in the field. The exact same work might be lauded as the world’s greatest invention since sliced bread when coming from an established, senior lab or derided as inconsequential, boring, or wrong when coming from a junior lab. Having a junior adviser can also make it harder to find an academic job after you graduate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the university. This may put you at a disadvantage when it comes to TA positions, university fellowships, and other dealings with university administration. In particular, if something unexpected happens, e.g. the class you were supposed to TA for gets cancelled, a senior PI is more likely going to have resources to deal with the situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lab of a junior PI may not have the resources you will need to carry out outstanding research. In particular, if you join a lab in its first or second year, you may find yourself spending a year or longer just setting up lab infrastructure. By contrast, a large, established lab will likely have everything you need to do ground-breaking work the moment you walk into the door.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since your PI is new, he or she still has to prove himself/herself. As a result, your PI might end up competing with you. For example, a junior PI might insist on being the one presenting your work at a conference where a senior PI might let you present your work yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you join the lab of an untenured professor, you risk that your PI won’t get tenure while you’re in the lab. That experience is likely going to be as disruptive to you as it will be to your PI. The worst-case scenario is an upcoming tenure decision 2-4 years out from when you start your PhD. If you’re only in your first year when your PI doesn’t get tenure, you should be able to just join another lab, without having wasted much time and effort. And if you’re in your fifth year or later, you should be able to finish up your dissertation work even if your PI has to close down his/her lab and move on. But if you’re right in the middle of your thesis work, you may have to throw away 2-3 years of work and start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does it take to be a computational biologist?</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/10/what-does-it-take-to-be-a-computational-biologist/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/10/what-does-it-take-to-be-a-computational-biologist/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I would like to talk about what it takes to be a computational biologist, specifically in comparison to being an experimental biologist. If you’re wondering whether instead of becoming a computational biologist you should become a race-car driver, fighter pilot, or ballet dancer, this post probably won’t help you. But if you’re wondering whether a computational biology lab is a better choice for you than an experimental biology lab, this post should provide you with some useful guidelines. To cut right to the chase, here is the take-home message: To become a computational biologist, you need to &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to become a computational biologist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I interview students who are potentially interested in joining my lab, the interviews inevitably take one of two routes, depending on the students’ background. The students with extensive computational experience usually make a point emphasizing all the techniques, systems, and languages they have learned, to showcase their technical expertise. By contrast, the students with little computational experience are usually rather timid. They say that they might be interested in computational biology but don’t really know much about it, and also that they don’t know if they would be any good at it.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I don’t really worry much about pre-existing expertise.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Sure, I won’t be disappointed if a student knows a lot already, but it plays a rather minimal role in my decision of whether or not to take a particular student.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I think that computation can be learned relatively easily, &lt;em&gt;if you really want to learn it,&lt;/em&gt; so what matters much more than your current knowledge is your intention.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; For this reason, when students express any concern about their ability to be computational biologists, I usually ask them a simple question: Would you rather spend your day in front of a bench pipetting, or would you rather spend your day in front of a computer screen staring at symbols and numbers? Anybody who would rather stare at a computer screen is going to be fine in my lab, and anybody who would rather pipette is not going to have a good time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, too much pre-existing computational knowledge can be a disadvantage, when the students think they know things better than they actually do. At least the inexperienced students are a blank slate. They are willing to listen and they accept the conventions of the lab. The more experienced students may have idiosyncratic views on how things should be done, views that may make sense from their perspective but not from the perspective of the person running the lab (i.e., me). For example, a student who insists on using java for a project when the rest of the lab uses python is going to cause problems,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; even if he has lots of experience with java and none with python. With some experienced students, I spend as much time re-training them as I would have spent with less experienced students training them from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you don’t have a lot of computational experience but you would like to do computational work, ask yourself whether you have the patience to hack away for hours in front of a computer screen, until you have solved a problem. If the answer is yes, you’ll be fine. And if you do already have a lot of computational experience, keep an open mind, realize that there is probably still a lot you can learn, and accept that some things are just conventions. Even if you don’t like a particular convention (such as “we use python”) you should accept it if you want to be successful in your lab.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Actually, more recently there is also a third type, students who think they have computational experience but they really don’t. MS Word, Excel, or Facebook do not count as computational experience. If you have never written an actual program and never used a command line, you don’t have any meaningful experience.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This statement applies to undergraduate researchers or prospective graduate students. I wouldn’t hire a postdoc without any computational expertise. If somebody has done a purely experimental PhD they are unlikely going to be a good match for my lab at the postdoc stage, since we don’t do any experiments whatsoever.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tend to evaluate students primarily on whether they appear to be motivated, whether they appear to be smart, whether I can connect with them, and whether I think they would fit into the lab.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;This point is also made &lt;a href=&#34;http://pgbovine.net/tech-privilege.htm&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; As long as people give you a chance to try yourself at programming and you make an effort, you should be fine.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As just one example, it will be more difficult for other students to take advantage of that student’s work and vice versa. Further, once the student leaves, the project may be abandoned or somebody else may have to re-engineer it using the lab’s preferred language.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge that there may be situations where the convention a lab has chosen is genuinely poor, and where the student truly knows better than the faculty member how to do things properly. However, I think these situations are rare, in particular for labs run by experienced computational biologists. And moreover, if you as a student really have so much computing experience that you can see all the poor decisions your PI is making, why did you join the lab in the first place? You should have seen these issues ahead of time. For example, if I were a prospective graduate student now, and I was told a lab did everything in perl and fortran, I’d run. By contrast, if they used languages I approve of, if they deposited their code on github, and if the code they deposited looked more or less decent, then I should be fine in that lab.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Excess ambition—the eternal flaw of all PhD thesis proposals</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/12/07/excess-ambitionthe-eternal-flaw-of-all-phd-thesis-proposals/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/12/07/excess-ambitionthe-eternal-flaw-of-all-phd-thesis-proposals/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I cannot remember ever having seen a graduate student present a PhD thesis proposal and be criticized for lack of ambition. It never happens. Even the weakest students—especially the weakest students—present proposals that are overly ambitious and that won’t ever get done, and certainly not in the 3–4 years remaining until graduation. In fact, in my experience it is exceedingly rare that a student presents a reasonable proposal, one that is actually doable during the remainder of the time in graduate school. Usually, those only happen when students “forget” to have their qualifying exams and end up presenting their “proposal” six months before the intended graduation date. In those cases, the students know that they won’t accomplish much new between proposal day and defense day, and basically present a proposal that consists entirely of completed work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Biology, most professors expect graduate students to complete about three projects, corresponding to the magical three specific aims in a typical grant proposal.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In my mind, a graduate student who is defending her proposal, 2–3 years into her program, should have one project completed, one well under way, and one in the early planning stages. Students doing complicated experimental work might be less advanced at that time, but at a minimum they should have one project well under way by the time they defend their thesis proposal. This gives a pretty good rule of thumb for the amount of work the proposal should encompass: Aim 1 should be the work that is in the bag, and Aims 2 and 3 together should not require more than twice the amount of work already accomplished. Instead, what I commonly see is that the completed work is only a small component of Aim 1, which alone is going to take another two years to completion. Aim 2 will need four years on top of that, and Aim 3 another ten. Basically, many graduate students propose to carry out a lifetime of research during their graduate work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t quite know why PhD proposals tend to be overly ambitious. Maybe it’s youthful optimism or naiveté. I suspect, though, that there is a component of fear, the eternal graduate student fear of not being sufficiently productive, of not doing enough. Ironically, this fear often causes students to overlook the successes that are within reach and instead try to reach for the stars. In general, doing a successful thesis is a fine balancing act between being overly ambitious and playing it too safe, a topic for another post. However, there’s a difference between an actual PhD thesis and a thesis proposal: The thesis should contain some exciting, risky work, but for the proposal most professors want to see a plan that is doable, not one that might be doable if the stars align correctly. As a smart graduate student, you have two alternative plans, one safe and one daring, you work on both of them at the same time, and you present the safe one during the committee meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second, related issue I frequently notice is that students display poor judgment in how much work they can realistically accomplish in the remaining time. Estimates are consistently too optimistic. If you are in year three, and you have completed 50% of your first project, it is unlikely that you’ll complete this and two entirely different projects in the remaining 2–3 years of your PhD. Further, unless you’re a paper-writing machine, it’s unlikely that you can write a paper in less than three months. (And if you are a paper-writing machine, you should have plenty of papers by the time you defend your proposal anyway.) So, if you still have three manuscripts to complete, plus a thesis, the writing time alone is going to be about a year. If you’re already halfway into year three, you’ll have about another 18 months of actual research work you can do, because the other 12 you’ll spend writing. (Of course I’d recommend that you &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/8/26/when-should-you-stop-doing-science-and-start-writing-a-paper&#34;&gt;don’t wait all the way till the end before you start writing&lt;/a&gt;, but the math comes out the same.) My personal rule of thumb is things take about three times as long as students estimate things will take. So if a student says a particular project needs another three months in the lab plus a month to be written up, I expect that project to be done around the same time next year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, when you prepare your thesis proposal, realistically assess how much work you can complete during the remainder of your graduate years. Don’t assume that your productivity will double or triple over the next two years, because it won’t. Budget at least three months for every paper you have to write, and triple the time you think it takes to complete the remaining lab work. If you have papers in review, consider that responding to reviewer comments and revising a paper frequently takes another two to three months, during which nothing else gets done. If you end up with a plan that will require another five years of work or more, then you’ll have to change your aims. See whether your current Aim 1 can be broken down into reasonable sub-aims which can be considered the separate chapters of your thesis. It’s quite common for me to conclude a PhD proposal defense by telling the student it’d be best to scrap Aims 2 and 3 altogether and instead expand Aim 1 into the entire thesis. If you come to that realization before the committee meeting, I don’t have to tell you so during, and everybody is happier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;While proposals with either two or four aims can also be viable, two can appear as unimaginative (he really couldn’t think of anything else?) and four is getting dangerously close to being overly ambitious, so three it is.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Giving effective presentations</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/20/giving-effective-presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/20/giving-effective-presentations/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today, I gave a talk in our weekly departmental seminar about giving effective presentations. Here are the slides I used. Not all of them may make sense without the accompanying oral presentation. (There’s one slide in particular where I purposefully tell a different story than the slide does.) However, most of the material should make sense as is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If anything is unclear, please ask questions in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.slideshare.net/slideshow/embed_code/key/cYcOAnmJQPQwbJ&#34; width=&#34;595&#34; height=&#34;485&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34; marginwidth=&#34;0&#34; marginheight=&#34;0&#34; scrolling=&#34;no&#34; style=&#34;border:1px solid #CCC; border-width:1px; margin-bottom:5px; max-width: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/wilkelab/giving-effective-presentations-oct-2013&#34;&gt;Giving effective presentations&lt;/a&gt; – Claus Wilke, Oct. 2013&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update July 3, 2018:&lt;/strong&gt; An updated and expanded version of this presentation &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.slideshare.net/ClausWilke/giving-effective-presentations-oct-2016&#34;&gt;is available here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the value of a mentor?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/19/what-is-the-value-of-a-mentor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/19/what-is-the-value-of-a-mentor/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Amidst the flurry of posts on the recent sexual-harassment-in-science-blogging scandal,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I found &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.slate.com/articles/double_x/doublex/2013/10/science_blogging_scandal_bora_zivkovic_and_sexual_harassment.html&#34;&gt;this post on slate.com&lt;/a&gt; which made some interesting statements about the value (or lack thereof) of mentors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the mentor-mentee relationship is one of the most fraught of adulthood. We glibly advise people starting out in business to find a mentor, to identify a successful, established, generous person in your field and somehow get her to help you become her.&lt;br /&gt;
This is &lt;em&gt;terrible&lt;/em&gt; advice. It perpetuates old-boy networks, wastes time that early career people could spend actually doing their work, and tells them they are only as good as their contacts and charm. Young people, don’t look for a mentor. Listen to and learn from people who have more experience, but don’t hitch your wagon to their star. Just do your job well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay then. I guess I can shut this site down and go home. I’ll just tell my students that from now on they’ll have to figure it out for themselves.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I may give them a word of advice now and then, but other than that they’re on their own. I’m sure the most meritorious ones of them will find their way. After all, I did.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No I won’t. I think there are at least three distinct ways in which a mentor can be valuable. Of those three, the last is probably the most important one. It also provides a relatively clear litmus test on whether a person is truly mentoring or instead potentially abusing his/her power for personal objectives. I agree with &lt;a href=&#34;http://tenureshewrote.wordpress.com/2013/09/08/it-takes-a-village-to-mentor-an-academic/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; that the different mentorship functions could (and maybe even should) be filled by different people. And I’d argue that good mentors will encourage you to build a network of people that can all provide additional mentorship to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-mentor-as-coach&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. The mentor as coach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first important role a mentor can play is that of a coach, just like in sports. Most people need a coach to perform at their highest level. A coach recognizes your strengths and weaknesses, she calls you out when you’re lazy, and she knows how far she can push you. You are still the one who has to put in all the work, but she makes sure that you do. She also makes sure you do the right kind of work, you don’t waste your time with stuff that isn’t needed and you don’t skimp on things that really need to be done. Even Michael Phelps, the greatest Olympian of all time, has a coach that prepares him for competitions. I don’t think anybody would ever say “Michael Phelps is just as good as his coach. If his coach hadn’t helped him, Phelps wouldn’t have won a single medal.” And yet, the second sentence is probably true. Phelps wouldn’t have succeeded without a good coach. At the highest level of human performance, nobody does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-mentor-as-counselor&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. The mentor as counselor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, a mentor can be a counselor, a trusted source of advice when you need help in a professional situation or, depending on your relationship with your mentor, in a situation that tends more towards the personal side. For example, maybe you’re unsure about your professional future. Or you don’t know how to best interact with a difficult colleague. Or you’re wondering whether you should take your dream job or rather follow your partner to a different part of the country. In all those situations, a mentor who knows you well may be able to provide important insight. A person who knows the field but not you may also be helpful, but not necessarily to the same extent. The latter person may not be aware of specific issues you might encounter because of your personal strengths and weaknesses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;the-mentor-as-sponsor&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. The mentor as sponsor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, and most importantly, a mentor &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.forbes.com/sites/danschawbel/2013/09/10/sylvia-ann-hewlett-find-a-sponsor-instead-of-a-mentor/&#34;&gt;can and should be a sponsor,&lt;/a&gt; a person who speaks up on your behalf and who puts you in contact with the right people and in front of the right opportunities. For as long as hiring is done by humans and not by computers, who you know and what they say about you will be an important determinant of your professional success. You may not like this, you may not think it fair, none of this matters. Reality is what it is. The right contacts help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said the third point would provide a litmus test to the mentor’s intentions. A mentor who truly wants to help her mentees will sponsor them incessantly. She will put them in contact with other important figures in the field, she will send them to conferences or professional meetings, she will give them opportunities to shine. Through all these actions, she reduces her mentee’s dependency on her, since all these other contacts can serve as further mentors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the litmus test is this: Does your mentor/adviser/manager/person in power connect you with other important people? Does she encourage you to showcase your work? Does she hand you opportunities and put you in charge of things? Does she nominate you for awards or other honors? Or, instead, does she keep you out of the spotlight? Does she discourage you from talking to other people? Does she create anxiety and paranoia? (“Be careful who you talk to about your research. They might steal your ideas.”) Does she keep you slaving away by promising big payoffs some day in the future? (“Once you get that Science paper, which you absolutely deserve, you’ll get a faculty job in no time. But now get back to the lab so you can finish that last experiment we need.”) Does she throw up unnecessary stumbling blocks? (“Yes, you have enough work for a regular paper, and I understand you would like to graduate soon, but a Science paper would be so much better for you. Just do another bit of work.”) Does she send mixed messages, such as helping you get papers but then not allowing you to present the work outside the lab?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you can answer the first set of questions with “yes” then you’re working with somebody who wants you to succeed on your own terms and who also knows that nobody succeeds in a vacuum and without any help. If you can answer the second set of questions with “yes” then you have to doubt your mentor’s motives. The second sets of behaviors create dependency, they put you in a position where you need your mentor’s continued favor to keep doing what you’re doing. If you find yourself in that situation, you should start developing an exit strategy. Some of the advice in &lt;a href=&#34;http://tenureshewrote.wordpress.com/2013/08/12/toxic-academic-mentors/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; may be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;but-i-only-succeeded-because-i-charmed-my-mentor&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;But I only succeeded because I charmed my mentor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When people have been mentored well, they sometimes start worrying that they didn’t succeed out of their own ability, that they were just handed success because their mentor liked them (&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impostor_syndrome&#34;&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/a&gt;). In this context, it’s important to realize that a mentor who is a sponsor constantly relies on the mentee to perform on his own: At a professional meeting, or in a one-on-one conversation with an important colleague, the mentee has to follow through. Just like Phelps and Phelps alone is swimming for gold, the mentee and the mentee alone is giving the talk, making conversation, doing the work. I don’t believe for a minute that one can take a mediocre student or employee and, through skillful mentoring, make them be successful beyond their own abilities. That’s just not how things work. If Michael Phelps’ coach took me under his wings because I charmed him with my beautiful smile and my bright green eyes I’d probably become a better swimmer but I’d certainly never win olympic gold. If you find yourself thinking “X helped me, therefore I didn’t do this on my own, therefore I don’t deserve this success” you’re likely experiencing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_distortion&#34;&gt;cognitive distortion,&lt;/a&gt; specifically all-or-nothing thinking/false dilemma. X helped you, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you did your part, and therefore you succeeded. You absolutely did deserve it. Chances are, if X hadn’t recognized your ability to succeed, she wouldn’t have helped you in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you missed it, &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.plos.org/onscienceblogs/2013/10/18/gossip-scandal-shutdown-shutdown-obamacare/&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; gives a good summary.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The majority of my students are female and several are non-white, whereas I’m very much non-female and white. Most likely I’m not a good role model for them anyway.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;In graduate school I didn’t receive much in the form of mentoring from my adviser. I learned mostly from reviewers and journal editors. Reviewers commented on the papers I submitted and told me where my research fell short. Editors taught me important things about how science works, such as that one writes a response to reviewers upon resubmission of an article or that axis labels need to be larger than 2mm on the final printed page.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtual Books</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/13/virtual-books/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/13/virtual-books/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Blogs tend to be ephemeral. They are usually presented as a constant stream of novel contents, where the most recent posts are easily seen but the older posts can be difficult to discover. Even when blogs have excellent archive and search functions, I often wonder whether I have seen all the relevant posts on a topic. And the larger and more active a blog, the more of an issue it becomes. For example, one of my favorite blogs, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.marksdailyapple.com/&#34;&gt;Mark’s Daily Apple,&lt;/a&gt; updates daily and contains thousands of interesting posts. Its archive lists posts by a variety of different criteria, and its search function generally returns relevant hits. Nevertheless, I often have difficulty finding my way around that blog. I’m never really sure that I’ve read the most important articles on a given topic, in the right order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like my blog to have more permanence, and over time to develop into a useful resource that covers in depth a variety of important topics. As a first step towards this goal, I’m introducing a new section to the blog, &lt;a href=&#34;/virtualbooks&#34;&gt;Virtual Books.&lt;/a&gt; In this section, I am collecting blog posts into chapters of related topics, and the chapters into books. Think of the whole experiment as books that you can read as they are being written. As of today, there are two such virtual books in that section, &lt;em&gt;Scientific Writing&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Professional Development as a Scientist.&lt;/em&gt; For these two, I feel that I now have sufficient material online that organizing it more systematically makes sense. Over time, as I keep blogging on different topics, I’ll probably add a few more virtual books on different topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ll see how it goes. Let me know what you think. And also, let me know if you’d like me to post on a specific topic.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to choose the right lab for graduate school</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Choosing the right lab for graduate school can be a daunting prospect. There are so many issues to consider. So many things that could go wrong. And you have to join the most prestigious lab you can get into, don’t you? Well, let’s consider for a moment what the main point of graduate school is. Graduate school is the time when you transition from being a student to being an independent scientist. It is primarily an educational experience. While in graduate school, you should pick up some subject-matter knowledge in your field. You should become familiar with the most important experimental or computational tools of your trade. You should learn how to choose scientific questions and how to solve them. You should develop general life skills such as how to communicate, how to work with other people, and how to get stuff done on time and to spec. So how do you find the right lab in which to acquire all these skills?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that the most important overall consideration should be whether you feel comfortable with the PI, the other members of the lab, and the overall lab culture. In my mind, this is even more important than the specific research area the lab works in. Graduate school will usually take about five years, and it is an important time in your personal development. The people you meet in graduate school will likely remain colleagues and friends for the rest of your life. If you’re miserable the whole time, it’s going to be an awful experience. And even if you manage to power through the misery, you won’t have performed at your best. You could have done better elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further, even in the best-case scenario, you can expect that something is going to happen over these five years that will challenge you or bring you down. Maybe a close friend or relative will die. Maybe you’ll experience a prolonged period of illness. Maybe you’ll get pregnant. Maybe you’ll go through a bad relationship breakup. Maybe you’ll just be generally disenchanted with science or with your project in particular. Maybe you’ll feel that you’re not getting enough done and that everybody else is progressing so much more quickly than you are. Whatever it’s going to be in your case, you can be certain that something is going to come your way. And when it happens, being in a lab that is supportive, helpful, and pleasant can make all the difference between a successful PhD and a premature termination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what about building a competitive cv? Shouldn’t you go with the most famous lab, so you’ll get great publications and will be set for your future career in academia? I’m not convinced. If you’ve read my &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt;, you know that I believe all that matters career wise is that your cv is strong enough by the time you graduate that you’ll get the next job on your career path. If you’re on the academic track, that will usually mean 2-3 high-quality first-author publications, plus maybe a few more papers where you’ve made smaller contributions. In this context, “high-quality publications” means solid papers in recognized journals in your field. It does not mean Nature, Science, Cell, or PNAS. (While those won’t hurt, they’re generally not needed to get a good postdoc.) If you’re not on the academic track, the requirements aren’t that different. They aren’t stricter for sure, so for the purpose of choosing the right graduate program and lab it’s probably best to just pretend you’re on the academic track. So, if the main goal is 2-3 high-quality first-author publications, this is totally achievable in many labs all around the world. Even in labs that aren’t that well known, in universities that aren’t that highly ranked, students routinely perform at this level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequently, don’t obsess too much about the prestige of the university. Prestige is overrated at the graduate level. (It is much more important at the postdoc level.) Even the most prestigious labs in the most prestigious places frequently hire postdocs from all sorts of universities. This happens because the prestigious labs tend to employ many postdocs, often many more than they produce graduate students, and therefore they simply cannot fill all their positions with graduates from comparably prestigious labs. As long as you graduate with a competitive cv (see above), you’ll most likely be fine and get a good postdoc position. My personal opinion is that any university within the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.shanghairanking.com/ARWU2013.html&#34;&gt;top 200&lt;/a&gt; of the world university rankings will probably be just fine for graduate school. I got my PhD from a university ranked somewhere past 300, and I still managed to get a good job, at a university that is consistently ranked in the top 40 worldwide and in the top 10 nationwide in my field. I’m not saying here that getting a PhD from a higher ranked institution won’t help you. I just think that it’s not as important as you may think it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Related to this issue, I would like to emphasize that choosing a lab for graduate school requires very different considerations than choosing a lab for a postdoc. My advice in this post is specifically for graduate students; I may write an article for postdocs at a later date. Some labs are really good for graduate students but not that great for postdocs. Some labs are the other way round. Some labs are great for everybody, but those are much rarer and may be highly competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I would be wary of very large labs that are staffed primarily with postdocs and senior scientists. In such labs, it’s not uncommon for graduate students to be treated as second-class citizens that need to fend for themselves. If you’re in that kind of a lab, you may rarely see your PI. Your day-to-day supervision—if there is any—is likely going to come from a postdoc. At that point, you may be getting worse supervision than you would have gotten had you gone with an inexperienced, first-year faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All else being equal, I would urge you to choose the lab that publishes more. If you’re in a lab that publishes a lot, chances are you’re going to be publishing a lot as well. By contrast, if you’re in a lab that publishes rarely, don’t expect to see your name in print that often. In fact, it’s not uncommon for a weaker student in a very productive lab to build a better track record than a stronger student might do in a lab that doesn’t like to commit words to print.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you go with a junior faculty member or with a more established person? There are arguments for either route. If you go with a junior faculty member, you are more likely to get a lot of personal attention. You have the chance to build a lab from the ground up and to get your name on that lab’s important early papers. Most of the early students of scientists who became famous rose to fame with them. Of course, the early students of scientists who didn’t become famous didn’t, so take that for what it’s worth. The argument for an older, more established person is that that person is more of a known quantity. You can evaluate that person’s productivity, impact on the field, mentoring philosophy, and lab culture. The older adviser is also more likely to have connections that may be beneficial to you, and he/she is less likely to make rookie mistakes. Finally, a younger adviser might end up competing with you if you turn out to be really good. By the same token, an older, very established adviser may suck up much of the available grant money in an entire field. Once you leave the lab, you will have to change field and/or develop a clearly unique and distinct identity to remain competitive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people worry about joining a younger professor’s lab since he or she might not get tenure. I don’t think this risk is particularly high, unless you’re at a school known for never giving tenure. Of course, be careful if the writing is on the wall and there are rumors that the person whose lab you’re considering may not get tenure. In all other cases, I wouldn’t worry much about the tenure situation. Also, keep in mind that if you go with a famous and established tenured professor it’s not certain either that they will stay for five years at the same place. They might get hired away while you’re in graduate school, and that experience could be almost as stressful as your professor not getting tenure. So don’t decide against a lab out of fear, decide for the lab that overall seems to be the best fit for you. If that turns out to be the lab of an old, established professor, you’ll likely be fine. And if it is the lab of a junior person, you’ll likely be fine as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, you need to be aware that there are generally two types of graduate programs: those that have a rotation system and those that don’t. If there is a rotation system, you rotate with 2-4 labs in your first year, and then you decide in which lab to pursue your PhD work. If there is not, then you get accepted into the program under the assumption that you’ll join a specific lab. The advantage of the rotation system is that you can test-drive a lab before joining. The disadvantage is that if none of the rotations work out, or if you don’t get rotation spots in your preferred labs, you may end up in a lab you don’t like or in no lab at all. If there’s no rotation system, then you have to decide on a lab without really knowing much about it. In the latter types of programs, you can set up your own rotation system of sorts by asking to be co-advised by two or three faculty members. After about a year, you can then decide whether you want to stay in the co-advised situation or whether you’d rather just work with one particular faculty member.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I don’t think it matters too much whether you join a program with a rotation system or not. Either way, I would encourage you to get to know the labs in the program ahead of time, and to only join a graduate program if multiple participating labs look attractive to you. Regardless of how wisely you choose your initial lab, you may reach a point where you have to switch, and at that point it’s good to have alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should you list on your cv a paper that is in review or in preparation?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/10/should-you-list-a-paper-in-review-or-in-preparation-on-your-cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/10/should-you-list-a-paper-in-review-or-in-preparation-on-your-cv/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I strongly recommend that junior scientists (and even senior scientists) list submitted papers on their cv. The main reason is the inevitable delay between when a project is done and when a paper finally comes out. If I see a cv with no publications in the last year, I don’t know if that is because the person got lazy or because there are five papers in the pipeline that just haven’t made their way out of review yet. If I see a couple of papers listed as “submitted” or “in review” it gives me confidence that the person hasn’t gotten lazy yet. Also, from the titles of the papers, I can get a sense of where the person’s work is going at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some might be concerned that a paper that isn’t formally accepted isn’t quite a paper yet, since it doesn’t yet have the official stamp of approval. Therefore it shouldn’t be on the cv. After all, it might never see the light of day. This kind of reasoning does not really reflect reality. As far as I can tell, if a paper has been submitted it might as well have been published, because realistically most papers that get submitted will get published eventually. I have published over 100 papers, and throughout my entire career I can recall maybe 3 or 4 cases where I gave up on a paper after review. I see similar statistics as a reviewer or editor: Most papers that come my way and that I consider to be of insufficient quality to appear in print do so anyway, eventually. So I’m going to argue that maybe 5% of papers get submitted somewhere but never formally appear, while the remaining 95% are on track to becoming published works. I’m a theoretical physicist, and to me 95% is close enough to 100% that I don’t care about the difference. Once a paper has been submitted, I count it as a published paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument becomes even stronger if a senior scientist is a coauthor on the paper. If that senior person generally publishes solid works, and if he or she agreed to submission of the article with their name on it, chances are it is a solid piece of work as it currently stands. Reviewers may still have some issues that they’re going to nitpick over. However, realistically reviewers are wrong as often as they are right, and why should I give more credence to some random, anonymous reviewer than to the senior person whose work I respect?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one caveat, though: The number of papers listed on your cv as “in review” should be commensurate to your typical publication output. If you have published two papers a year for the last three years and you list 20 that are in review, I will be skeptical about the quality of those papers and will wonder whether maybe your success rate from submission to publication is not near 100%. But if you usually publish two papers a year and you list three in review, that looks reasonable and I won’t give it a second thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I view papers “in preparation” differently, however. “In preparation” means nothing. A paper that is submitted must have gotten to the point where at least one, and usually several, scientists felt it could be published in principle. A paper in preparation could be nowhere near that point, and it might never get there. I certainly have had plenty of papers in my life that were “in preparation” and eventually transitioned to “nobody even remembers what the project was supposed to be about.” If I listed all of those papers on my current cv, it’d probably be twice as long and half as useful. If you have a paper in preparation that you really want to list on your cv, then hurry up, get it done, and submit it. And put it on a preprint server, too, so you and others can cite it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From undergraduate to faculty member: Critical decision points in the academic career</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re an undergraduate contemplating an academic career or a graduate student considering the next steps, you may have the long-term goal of becoming a tenured professor at a major research university. At the same time, you may have serious doubts about whether this is the career for you. Are you good enough to be a faculty member? And if you’re not good enough, will you waste years of your life with little to show for it in the end? Even if you’re good enough, is that sufficient, or will you also need an extraordinary amount of luck? By embarking on an academic career, will you be making a high-stakes gamble that may have a catastrophic outcome if you lose? These are serious doubts, and they can make the prospects of pursuing an academic career seem overwhelming and pointless. As a substitute for these overwhelming, larger-than-life questions, I’d like to offer a set of critical decision points and simple rules about how to proceed. I hope that these suggestions will make the path to an academic position more navigable and less stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first clarify, though, that I don’t think every graduate student has to become a tenured professor at a major university. In fact, I believe that the majority of graduate students are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on track to become faculty members. For example, I read about a case study once where of an entering class of 20 graduate students at Yale university, only 2 had a tenure-track career 10 years later (I’m recalling this from memory, so I may have some details wrong, but the gist was approximately that.) Losing that many students to pursuits other than pure academia is Ok, as long as the majority of them finds satisfying and appropriately compensated employment. And I’m pretty sure they do. They certainly do if they picked up serious computational skills during their PhD. On the other hand, while I don’t see it as my mission to turn every student of mine into a professor, I also don’t want to see highly gifted and capable students give up on an academic career just because they perceive it as an impossible feat, one they shouldn’t even attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-undergraduate-to-graduate-student&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From undergraduate to graduate student&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re currently an undergraduate, you shouldn’t even think about whether you’re on track to becoming a professor. It’s impossible to know anyway, and it doesn’t matter for the main decision you have to make: Should you go to graduate school or not? Unless you are under strong financial pressure to earn money right away (e.g. you have enormous student debt, or you have three children that you have to support on your own), this decision should not primarily be a financial one. For most students, graduate school is approximately cost-neutral: The stipend you’re paid while working as teaching assistant or graduate research assistant covers your basic living expenses. You don’t save any money while you’re in graduate school, but you also shouldn’t accumulate any debt. You could think about graduate school in terms of income lost over five years versus your future earnings potential, but frankly, if you think in these terms I don’t think a graduate program in science is right for you. Get a graduate degree in business, economics, or management, and embark on a career of serious money making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A graduate degree in science is for people who really care about figuring things out, or about solving problems. As an undergraduate, you have to be aware that graduate school will be very different from your undergraduate experience, unless you’ve already spent a substantial amount of time in a research lab. Graduate school is not about passing exams, getting good grades, or cramming material. In the end, it’s all about doing science and writing papers. Some people have a 4.0 undergraduate GPA and fail in graduate school, and others have a 2.9 GPA and succeed. If you really care about figuring things out, if you could see yourself spending months at a time getting to the bottom of an issue, then graduate school is for you. Don’t worry about the naysayers that say a PhD is a worthless piece of paper. I am not aware of any evidence that a PhD in science will &lt;em&gt;hurt&lt;/em&gt; your subsequent employability. It may not help you much, depending on how things go, but as I said already, you shouldn’t get into a PhD program for the money anyway. You should get into it because of your passion for research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-graduate-student-to-postdoc&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From graduate student to postdoc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, you’ve now made your way almost all the way through graduate school and the end is in sight. Should you continue and search for a postdoc position? Or should you jump ship and look for alternatives? At this point, I think it is justified to ask about earnings potential. You have obtained the most advanced degree you’ll ever get. From here on out, you’re not in it for the education, you’re in it for the experience. You have to ask yourself: Would I rather make money, or would I rather do nothing but research for a few years? For most academics, the postdoc time is a uniquely rewarding and free time. A time during which you can (mostly) freely pursue whatever research you care about, on your own schedule. You have completed your 10,000 hours of science by that time, so you can hit the ground running and do interesting stuff. For poor compensation, mind you. If your mindset is “I don’t really know what else I’d want to do anyway” then go ahead and do a postdoc. But if you can see a clear alternative path, and if that path looks attractive to you, then that alternative path may be the better choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, though, it is still not time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member. Plenty of graduate students don’t do that well, only to recover spectacularly during their postdoc. And others do well as graduate students but falter as postdocs. Generally, the former group does much better than the latter on the academic job market. I’m part of the former group, and I made out alright. I like to say that if you erased from my resume every single thing I did during graduate school, nothing of consequence would change. I got a job as a faculty member anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do have to make an honest assessment, though. Where do you stand relative to your fellow graduate students? Would you say your performance is comparable to most? Better? Worse? After five years in graduate school, you may not yet have made an earth-shattering discovery, but you should know by now whether you’re cut out for science or not. In particular, do you have one or two papers to your name for which you did the majority of the work, including the conceptual work? (I don’t care how good they are, just that they got done.) If after an honest assessment you find that you’re not really cut out for science, then don’t do a postdoc. Find a different occupation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of hope for finding a postdoc position: For as long as I can remember, the job market has been in favor of postdocs. Any capable graduate student who wants to can find a decent postdoc position. So don’t ever worry about not getting a postdoc position. If you want one, you’ll get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-postdoc-to-faculty-member&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From postdoc to faculty member&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re two to three years into your postdoc. Finally it’s time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member or not. Take honest stock. Where are you, compared to other people in the field that you’d be competing with on the job market. Ask some senior scientists about an honest evaluation. Hopefully your postdoc adviser will be able to tell you where you stand. In my opinion, if you’re three years into a postdoc and you’re nowhere near ready to apply for a faculty position, then it may be time to consider alternative careers. If you’re three years in and you’re ready to apply, then go for it and see how it goes. If you’re three years in and you’re getting close but you’re not quite there yet, then it’d be reasonable to wait another year. But don’t keep saying “I’ll be ready next year.” At some point, if things don’t work out in academia, you have to cut your losses and move on. Where that point is is a somewhat arbitrary and a bit of a personal choice, but I’d place it around five years. After five years of a postdoc-level position, you should find something more permanent. And if that job is not a tenure-track faculty position, then you may have to settle for research scientist, lecturer, administrator, or whatever else you can make work for you. There are plenty of reasonable career paths for a scientist, just don’t become a career postdoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can’t expect things on the job market to work out the first time round. You may not be quite ready, the big paper you wrote may not yet be that well known, or it may just be a bad year for academic hiring. If by your own and by your senior colleagues’ assessment you are ready to get a faculty position, then don’t despair if it doesn’t work out the first time round. Try at least two rounds. Also, if you changed your field after your PhD, or if you didn’t really do much of consequence as a graduate student, you may need a little more time as a postdoc. I was a postdoc for five years, and I think I needed that time to be really ready for a faculty position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As undergraduate, follow your passion. If you have a passion for figuring things out, get a graduate degree and see if you still like it five years down the road. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As graduate student, if your passion hasn’t disappeared, and if you can stomach another three to five years of being poor, go for the postdoc. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As postdoc, do an honest assessment of where you stand. If you are competitive on the job market, go for it. If you’re almost competitive, do what needs to be done to eliminate the “almost.” If you’re nowhere near competitive after about three years, start thinking about alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to approach professors by email</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/23/how-to-approach-professors-by-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/23/how-to-approach-professors-by-email/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today’s advice is written specifically for undergraduates, even though graduate students and postdocs may benefit as well. (I certainly didn’t figure these things out until I was a faculty member myself.) What is the best way to approach professors by email, in particular if you want or need something from them? I’ll give you the most important advice up front: &lt;strong&gt;Be absolutely clear about your intentions.&lt;/strong&gt; Tell me exactly what you want or need from me, and why. This will save both of us a lot of time, energy, and frustration. (Frustration would be mostly on your part, though, when I silently ignore your messages.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a professor, I am constantly being inundated with requests, propositions, recommendations, and demands. And most of them fall into the category of spam, or at least not very high on my priority list. Almost daily, I receive requests from people who would like to join my “esteemed laboratory.” They usually come from overseas, sport a long list of qualifications in the latest experimental techniques, and seem to have no knowledge of the fact that my lab is entirely computational (it says so &lt;a href=&#34;http://wilkelab.org/#about&#34;&gt;right on our homepage&lt;/a&gt;). I’m also constantly asked if I want to participate in this or that activity, survey, or committee. (Do I want to be on the university committee that decides on the color of the men’s changing room in the new gym? No.) Over time, I’ve gotten quite good at deleting or at least ignoring these emails. Usually, I don’t need to read past the first or second sentence before I send the message to the circular filing cabinet. If you want to reach me, you have to somehow make it through that noise. Your message has to be clearly different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, reaching me through this noise may seem a daunting task, but it’s actually not that bad. The truth is, I want to interact with you, I truly do. For example, I have over 10 people in my lab, from undergrads to senior scientists, and almost all of them got there by sending me an email at some point. They all got through to me. In order for me to be able to help you, though, to consider your request, I need you to help me. I need you to be crystal clear in what you need or want. Do you need to see me before Friday because you want to drop my class before the deadline? Say so. I’m not going to chew off your head. (An aside: Students seem to be extremely shy about requesting a drop. I really don’t care. If you want out of my class, I won’t be in your way.) Would you like to meet me because you’d like to work in my laboratory? Say so. If you’re an undergrad, say whether you are looking for a paid job or are willing to volunteer/work for course credit. If you’re a graduate student, tell me why you are interested in my lab and what topics you’d like to work on. In general, the more clearly you can spell out what it is you want from me, the quicker I can decide whether I can be of help or not. And if I receive a clear, well-formulated request that I have to deny, I’ll generally respond quickly with a “no,” and possibly with suggestions where else you could go. By contrast, I’ll generally just ignore or delete any messages whose intent is not clear to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to request a meeting with me, please suggest possible times that would work for you. Don’t just write “I would like to meet with you.” Write “I would like to meet with you. I’m available this week Wed. before noon or Thurs. after 2pm.” This saves us one round trip, because I can immediately suggest a time that might work for both of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if I ignore your message, don’t take it as a “no,” try again. I may simply have overlooked it. Or I may have had the best of intentions to respond to you, but then I got distracted by something, then I had to teach a class, and by the time I was back in my office your email was long forgotten. So if I don’t respond to your message, send me another one the next day, or maybe two days later. In general, I think you should try at least 2-3 times before you conclude that your message is being actively ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; I wanted to add some thoughts about how to address professors in email. If you’re an undergrad, I think you should write “Dear Dr.” + last name. In my case, that would be “Dear Dr. Wilke.” If you’re a graduate student or postdoc in my department, first-name basis is fine, so “Dear Claus” or just “Claus.” If you’re a graduate student or postdoc at a different institution, I think the formal “Dear Dr. …” is the better option, in particular if we’ve never had any interactions before. (If we hung out at a conference over a beer and talked until 2am about everybody and their dog, “Claus” is probably fine.) If you choose the formal address, pay attention to the response. If the response is signed just with a first name, you can assume you’re on first-name basis from there on out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My gripes with prezi, and some suggestions for making good prezi presentations</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/21/my-gripes-with-prezis-and-some-suggestions-for-making-good-prezi-presentations/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/21/my-gripes-with-prezis-and-some-suggestions-for-making-good-prezi-presentations/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Prezi is all the rage lately. It seems everybody and their dog is switching over to prezi for presentations. My twitter stream has more prezis than it has powerpoints, keynotes, openoffices, or whatever else people use to make presentations. (Latex beamer? Please don’t tell me you use latex beamer.) Just last week, I gave a presentation on giving engaging presentations, and one of the first questions I received afterwards was what I thought about prezi. In my opinion, everything I said in my talk applied to prezi just the same as it did to powerpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that people think prezi will magically make their presentations wonderful. Well, I’ve got news for you: it won’t. If you don’t have a story, prezi won’t help you. If you tell your story backwards, prezi won’t help you. If you have no stage presence, prezi won’t help you. If your slide design is atrocious, prezi won’t help you. &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/8/18/engaging-presentations-and-text-heavy-slides&#34;&gt;If you fill your slides with text you don’t read out aloud&lt;/a&gt;, prezi won’t help you. Moreover, prezi gives you the unique new power of &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke/status/370037036633182208&#34;&gt;making your audience seasick.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s the deal with prezi, what problems does it cause, and how could we use the prezi paradigm to make great presentations? The unique feature that distinguishes prezi from most other presentation software is that instead of individual slides that you flip through you have one large canvas on which you can pan, rotate, and zoom. This allows for some really cool effects that are not possible with any other presentation software, but it also adds a whole new level of complexity. Essentially, to make the most of prezi, you need to have some knowledge about videography. Very few people fit that bill and are sought-after public speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the two main issues with the prezis I’ve seen are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unexpected and excessive camera movement. The whole presentation can feel like a roller-coaster ride. You never know what’s next, but for sure it’s going to be some serious flying over the canvas. Experienced videographers know that &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.cisco.com/channels/five_tips_for_filming_your_next_or_first_video/&#34;&gt;excessive panning and zooming is disturbing,&lt;/a&gt; but apparently this info has not yet filtered through to the typical prezi user.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Distracting and mysterious previews of the material to come. Prezi encourages a slide design where the contents of the next slide is visible in the present slide, albeit scaled down to a really small size. I think that’s a bad idea, because it distracts the audience. Every time I see a prezi, I start wondering which element of the current slide we’ll zoom to next. Can I find the hidden text in the current slide? Needless to say, while I’m having these thoughts, I’ve stopped listening to the speaker, and I’ll probably miss most of the salient points in the presentation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve thought a bit about how one could work around those issues, and I’ve come up with the following design concepts. This list is not exclusive; there are almost certainly other really cool ways to make prezi work. I just don’t have enough imagination to dream them up myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infinite pan:&lt;/strong&gt; Just choose one direction (up, down, left, right, whatever you prefer) and keep panning in that direction. Simple, predictable, boring. But it will not detract from your presentation. And that’s a good thing! Astute readers will of course have noticed that the infinite pan effect can also be achieved with transition effects in powerpoint or keynote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infinite zoom out:&lt;/strong&gt; Start at the highest zoom level and add new material by zooming out further and further. The previous material will appear as a trail of little specks after a while. This might be a pretty cool effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infinite zoom in:&lt;/strong&gt; Like the infinite zoom out but in reverse. Start at the lowest zoom level (where you can see the entire canvas at once) and keep zooming in. This effect has the disadvantage that it can cause the audience to speculate about what’s going to come next, so I wouldn’t use it. But otherwise it’s sufficiently predictable that’s it’s probably a reasonable choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, just choose a consistent movement pattern for your camera and stick to it. Also, make use of prezi’s ability to make things appear in the current viewport. If you have a slide with a title and three bullet points, I think you should zoom/pan/rotate to the appropriate viewport containing only the title. Then, the bullet points should appear one by one as you go over them, but without further movement of the camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I wish prezi added the possibility to swap canvases during the presentation. If it had that feature, it would have the best of both worlds. One could do regular powerpoint presentations (each new slide is a new canvas), pure prezi-style presentations (each new slide is just a different viewport on the same canvas), and hybrids (e.g., a different canvas is used for different major parts of the presentation). I suspect that some clever people could make really cool presentations with a system that allows for the hybrid design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have a prezi that you think makes intelligent use of prezi’s paradigm, and that doesn’t have the issues I outlined above (disorienting movements and/or mysterious previews of things to come), please share that prezi with me. I’d like to be able to say that I’ve seen a great prezi.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should you as a scientist be active on LinkedIn?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/20/should-you-as-a-scientist-be-active-on-linkedin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/20/should-you-as-a-scientist-be-active-on-linkedin/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Mention &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/&#34;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, and you generally get two types of responses. Either you will hear that LinkedIn is the most important invention in the search for jobs since the invention of the printed resume, or you will hear that LinkedIn is completely irrelevant and that you shouldn’t waste your time with it. In my mind, there is no doubt that LinkedIn plays an important role in connecting people with new employment opportunities in the business world. For example, I know some people here in Austin who run a successful recruiting company, and they operate almost entirely on LinkedIn. If you don’t have a LinkedIn profile, you’re basically invisible to them. (Did I mention that they generally look for candidates with advanced knowledge in data analysis, visualization, and statistics, basically the exact kind of person my lab trains?) However, things are different in academia. I don’t know of a single faculty member who got her job through LinkedIn, and I doubt I’ll hear about such a case any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So should you, as a scientist, spend valuable time polishing your LinkedIn profile and connecting with people on the site? In my opinion, the answer is absolutely “yes”, and I’ll explain below why I think so. I will separately address two different groups of people, scientists in training (undergraduate, graduate student, postdoc) and faculty members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;scientists-in-training&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Scientists in training&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a scientist in training, the most important thing you have to realize is that it is by no means certain that you will end up in academia. In fact, most graduate students and even many postdocs will never become faculty members. And that is not a problem, in and of itself. Not everybody needs to become a professor. As long as our graduates find appropriate, satisfying, and well compensated employment, the world is in order. But what this means to you, as scientist in training, is that until you sign that offer letter for a tenure track position, you need to be open to alternative options. Building a solid LinkedIn profile and network may just provide you with the ticket to alternative career options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, do not underestimate the value of the connections you build early in your career. If you go to a top university and/or generally hang out with smart kids, I can guarantee you that the majority of your current friends, however inconspicuous they may appear, will go on and make something of themselves. Check back where they are ten to fifteen years from now, and you’ll be impressed. (If you don’t generally hang out with smart kids: what’s wrong with you?) The dude from across the hall that you always met in the gym may just have gotten tenure at Harvard. The girl who was two years ahead of you in graduate school may just have gone through the IPO of the company she founded after graduating. And the hottie you had a fleeting crush on when you attended your first conference as an undergraduate may now be on the committee that is considering hiring you for your next job. So take networking seriously, even as a lowly undergraduate. You never know who you will want to contact again ten years down the road, or who will become important to your career at some point in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;faculty-members&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Faculty members&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For faculty members, using LinkedIn is probably less about the next job opportunity. Notwithstanding people who don’t get tenure, and notwithstanding people who leave academia to work at Google or at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.deshawresearch.com/&#34;&gt;D. E. Shaw&lt;/a&gt;, or to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.linkedin.com/pub/matt-winkler/7/156/830&#34;&gt;found their own company,&lt;/a&gt; the general rule is “once a faculty member, always a faculty member.” For faculty members, I believe the value of LinkedIn is in the network which they can provide their students access to. As a faculty member, if you have done your job right, you should have a solid network of influential and successful people, not all in academia. You should be connected to former students or colleagues who have left academia to work in industry. You should also be connected to people in industry you have met at social events. So when one of your students approaches you about alternative career paths, you should be able to put that student in contact with the right people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, I recently had a student in my lab who was interested in consulting. Through LinkedIn, I was able to connect that student to two people who have successful careers in consulting. One of the two was a graduate student at Caltech while I was a postdoc there. The other was the husband of a former coworker of my wife. Without LinkedIn, I would not have known how to get in touch with either of them. (An observation that may come as a bit of a surprise to academics: not everybody can be found through a simple Google search of their name. In fact, most people &lt;strong&gt;can not&lt;/strong&gt; be found through a Google search.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;concluding-thoughts&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Concluding thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is LinkedIn the be all of professional networking? Probably not. Do you absolutely need to have an active, up-to-date LinkedIn profile to be successful as a scientist? Almost certainly not. Nevertheless, there are tangible benefits to keeping your LinkedIn profile active, so I think it’s worth it. And let’s be real, updating your LinkedIn profile doesn’t take a lot of time. With the time it took me to write this blog post, I can keep my LinkedIn profile updated for the next several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, because we academics need contacts outside academia, and because people move back and forth (maybe more forth than back) between academia and industry, I think that social networking sites geared specifically to scientists, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.researchgate.net/&#34;&gt;ResearchGate&lt;/a&gt;, are not particularly attractive. These sites generate an artificial distinction between scientists and other people when reality is more fluid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find my LinkedIn profile here: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/clauswilke&#34;&gt;Claus Wilke on LinkedIn.&lt;/a&gt; Connect with me if we’ve ever had a meaningful professional (or social) interaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engaging presentations and text-heavy slides</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/18/engaging-presentations-and-text-heavy-slides/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/18/engaging-presentations-and-text-heavy-slides/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;At this year’s BEACON conference, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/artcovert&#34;&gt;Art Covert&lt;/a&gt; and I gave a presentation on how to give engaging presentations. The slides for my part of the presentation are available &lt;a href=&#34;http://figshare.com/articles/Giving_Effective_Presentations/775322&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; If you browse through the slides, you’ll see that some of them are rather text-heavy. I did this on purpose, to demonstrate that text-heavy slides are not the bane of engaging talks, &lt;em&gt;if presented appropriately&lt;/em&gt;. By all accounts, despite the amount of text on my slides, &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/briandconnelly/status/368067764478439425/photo/1&#34;&gt;my presentation was engaging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first recommendations that we usually give our students is to put less text on their slides, and instead use images, drawings, and diagrams. I wholeheartedly agree with this recommendation in principle, and for most of my presentations I spend a lot of time developing graphics instead of text. However, I think that there are other recommendations that we should emphasize first; the text-heavyness of slides really is a minor issue. After all, one can absolutely give an excellent presentation using text-heavy slides, and one can also give a terrible presentation using slides with very little text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, I propose to replace the advice of using less text with the following advice, which I call &lt;em&gt;Claus’ 1st law of giving presentations&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All text on slides needs to be read aloud, word for word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Similarly, all visual elements need to be pointed out and explained.) The problem with text-heavy slides arises when the presenter paraphrases the text or, even worse, talks about something completely different while displaying the text-heavy slide. The audience members cannot process two different streams of information, one visual and one auditory, at the same time. Hence, they have to make the decision of either listening or reading. Whatever decision they make, they will likely feel that they missed something, and they will be more likely to disengage from the presentation altogether. I believe in particular that when audience members start reading instead of listening to the presenter, the presenter has lost them at that point and will likely not get them back for the remainder of the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By contrast, if the presenter reads the text word for word, the visual and the auditory cues reinforce each other. The audience will be more engaged and less likely to drift mentally. For the same reason, I like text to appear line by line, as I read it, rather than all in one block. Again, this increases the synchronicity between the visual and auditory cues and gives the audience members less opportunity to drift. If you ever get the chance to see a talk by Steven Pinker, observe how he reinforces auditory and visual cues. Nearly his entire talk is spelled out word for word on his slides. His slides basically serve as sub-titles to his voice. (You can probably find an example of this on YouTube. If you do, please post the link in the comments below.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that an additional benefit of my 1st law is that you can never make slides &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; text-heavy, because there is a limit to how much text you can read during the time alotted for your presentation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
