<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fitness on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/categories/Fitness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fitness on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/categories/Fitness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Weight doesn’t matter</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/30/weight-doesnt-matter/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/30/weight-doesnt-matter/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The majority of people on a diet will tell you that they’re dieting because they want to lose weight.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you ask them &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they want to lose weight, you’ll hear things like “I don’t want to have a heart attack at 50” or “I have some extra flab” or “I want to get rid of my spare tire” or “I want a six pack.” So people want to be healthy, or they want to look good naked, or both. Importantly, though, none of these goals have much to do with weight &lt;em&gt;per se.&lt;/em&gt; What people are actually concerned with is excess fat. And we generally know this, of course. We know that when we say somebody is overweight we really mean the person is overfat. Yet, in day-to-day practice, we don’t use the word “overfat,” we keep saying “overweight.” And as a result, we keep confusing weight and fat, and more importantly, we use the wrong metrics to keep track of our dieting success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask anybody on a diet how they’re keeping track of their progress, and the answer you’ll hear most frequently is going to be “I weigh myself regularly.” There we have a major problem. People want to lose fat, but they keep track of their progress using a metric that inherently cannot distinguish between desirable (i.e., lean) and undesirable (i.e., fat) mass. As a consequence, they’re setting themselves up for failure. They may indeed lose weight but this weight loss may not be accompanied by the desired improvements in physique and health.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flawed metric of weight leads to such terrible TV shows as “The biggest loser,” which promote awful dieting advice. If you make it your goal to lose as much weight as possible in as little time as possible, you’ll inevitably burn off a lot of muscle mass. And that’s terribly sad, in my mind. The one thing every obese person has going for them is that they have a substantial amount of muscle under their layer of fat, from all the extra weight they’re carrying around all the time. Strip away the fat and keep the muscle, and you’ll have a strong, healthy person. But burn the muscle alongside the fat, and you’ll end up with a skinny-fat person. This person would now have to embark on a process of regaining (lean) mass, which will be psychologically terrifying and will usually not happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I should probably demonstrate that there is indeed a substantive difference between losing fat and losing weight. Enter one of my &lt;a href=&#34;http://crossfitnewengland.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/11/fat-vs-muscle.jpg&#34;&gt;favorite pictures&lt;/a&gt; on the internet. (&lt;strong&gt;Warning:&lt;/strong&gt; mildly NSFW, woman in underwear.) It shows how the same person can look visibly slimmer and more toned after gaining a substantial amount of weight, if that weight comes in the form of lean mass not fat. The reason for this dramatic difference is that muscle is substantially more dense than fat. You need &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt; of muscle to fill a decent volume of space, and that muscle is going to weigh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If weight is a bad metric for fat-loss progress, how can you know whether you’re on track with your diet? Let’s first go over all the other commonly used methods that also don’t work:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assessing body-fat bia bio-electrical impedance analysis (BIA). Many scales these days have BIA built in as well. When you step on the scales, they show you not only how much you weigh but also what your body-fat percentage is. Only that this number can be quite inaccurate. BIA results depend on numerous factors, not the least of which is your hydration status which may change daily. You can find a more detailed discussion of this issue &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bioelectrical_impedance_analysis&#34;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; The one-sentence summary is that you shouldn’t track your fat-loss progress with a BIA device, and in particular not with regular scales that have BIA built in.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Looking at your abs in the mirror. This doesn’t work because it’s easy to trick yourself into thinking you’re doing great when actually you’re not. Even more likely is the opposite, though: You may think nothing much is happening when actually you have changed a lot. Fundamentally, this method is not sufficiently quantitative. You can never really be sure whether things have actually changed and by how much.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pinching your belly fat. This method is also surprisingly unreliable, in particular when you’re getting lean. As you’re leaning out, your skin gets looser and you can pinch from a larger area, seemingly being able to pinch more at a time. This effect is particularly pronounced when you’re pinching from top and bottom. Try pinching your belly fat right underneath your navel, either from top and bottom or from left and right. Do you see the difference? Also, sometimes we can have a substantial layer of fat but can’t pinch it. For example, try to pinch the fat on top of your thigh. Can you do that? Chances are, if you can you’re pretty lean. For most people, the fat on the thighs doesn’t really separate from the muscles, and as they lean out it separates more easily.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One method that works reasonably well is &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.edb.utexas.edu/fit/bodycompfit.php&#34;&gt;dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA),&lt;/a&gt; basically a low-dose X ray. It’s the same method that is used to measure bone density. While it’s a great way to keep track of your body composition over time, it’s also cumbersome, expensive, requires professional equipment, and exposes your body to unnecessary X rays. Not something you want to do once a week.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other method that works is super cheap, easy, and reliable: get a &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/AccuFitness-MT05-MyoTape-Body-Measure/dp/B000G7YW7Y/&#34;&gt;$5 tape measure&lt;/a&gt; and measure your waist circumference (just at the height of the belly button). That measurement should go down over time if you’re progressing successfully. How do you know you’re not losing lean mass at the same time? Your strength should stay the same or go up. If you’re increasingly &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/10/1/why-i-lift-weights-and-so-should-you&#34;&gt;lifting heavier weights&lt;/a&gt; while your waistline is slimming, you can be pretty certain that everything is on track. And if you happen to keep track of your weight at the same time, you may notice that your weight is going up even as your waist circumference is going down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in the future, don’t plan to lose weight, plan to lose fat. And lose that fat while keeping as much of your weight as you can, maybe even increase your weight by a few pounds!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;As incredulous as it may sound, there are indeed some people who are on a diet to &lt;em&gt;gain&lt;/em&gt; weight. There are entire online communities dedicated to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.reddit.com/r/gainit/wiki/index&#34;&gt;gaining weight.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s important to realize that people can weigh little and nevertheless have poor metabolic health. See e.g. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.huffingtonpost.com/dr-mark-hyman/skinny-fat_b_1799797.html&#34;&gt;this article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It probably also isn’t sensitive enough to measure changes week by week. But doing a DEXA scan once a year might not be a bad idea.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I lift weights (and so should you)</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/10/01/why-i-lift-weights-and-so-should-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/10/01/why-i-lift-weights-and-so-should-you/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;For the first forty years of my life, I thought lifting weights was for meatheads. If you lifted weights, my thinking went, you cared more about your looks than your health or fitness level. Actually, not looks even, just sheer size. I was convinced that my fitness regimen of endurance training (running, cycling, walking), flexibility (yoga), and basic whole-body movements (more yoga) was far superior to stupidly lifting weights in a gym. I mean, look at those guys&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in the gym: they take a barbell, lift it five times, and then they take a five minute break. Do they even break a sweat? I don’t call that exercise, I call that sitting around on your lazy behind. Only when I started to read up on exercise physiology did I realize that lifting heavy is an extremely beneficial activity. Further, it is likely the most important type of exercise we can engage in, in particular as we grow older. And those five-minute breaks are absolutely necessary if you’re doing it right, in particular if you care more for strength than size.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before I continue, though, a word of clarification: While the title of this post says “lift weights,” what really matters is that one engages in resistance training, i.e., putting heavy loads onto the muscles, tendons, and bones. Conventional resistance training involves barbell work, e.g. the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8JOqwynLV1w&#34;&gt;barbell squat&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YQi8xUZ0V90&#34;&gt;deadlift&lt;/a&gt;. However, other forms of exercise can be resistance training as well. For example, there are many excellent bodyweight resistance exercises. If you’re regularly cranking out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kw0kXtvOpfU&#34;&gt;planche pushups&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vlASvQCD4lY&#34;&gt;one-arm chins&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5orjYQupmWo&#34;&gt;one-arm handstands&lt;/a&gt;, you probably don’t have to pick up a barbell anytime soon. To find out whether a particular exercise can be considered resistance training &lt;em&gt;for you&lt;/em&gt;, find out how many repetitions you could do at most. If you can’t do more than about eight to ten repetitions, you’re in the resistance range. For example, if the max number of pushups you can do in one go is four, pushups are a viable resistance exercise for you. But if you can easily crank out twenty, pushups are an endurance exercise for you and you have to move on to something harder for resistance work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;float: right; width: 50%; margin-left: 1em;&#34; src=&#34;2013-10-01_143502.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why should you do resistance training? First, only heavy resistance training can actually activate and train all muscle fibers, including the strongest fast-twitch fibers. If you go jogging for 30 minutes, even at a pretty fast pace, you may feel tired afterwards, your legs may even be sore, but a substantial fraction of your leg muscle hasn’t actually done anything. By comparison, a single set of five barbell squats, at a weight that you can lift only about five times in a row, will have hit nearly every single muscle fiber in your leg muscles. Thus, you get way more exercise bang for your buck. (Incidentally, that’s why you need a few minutes break between sets of heavy resistance training. The exercises truly are that exhausting.) Second, there is better transfer from strength to endurance than the other way round. Once you have strength, it’s relatively easy to build endurance on top. But just because you have endurance doesn’t mean you can easily add strength. In simple terms, if you can do a one-arm pushup, you could easily acquire the ability to do 50 regular pushups in a row. On the flip side, being able to do 50 regular pushups doesn’t do much for your ability to do one-arm pushups. (If you want to see this principle in action, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NiCqpMGItP8&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; of a woman first squatting a barbell weighing over twice(!) her own bodyweight and then squatting a barbell weighing her own bodyweight 33 times. I’m sure she could easily do a couple hundred unloaded squats.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would also argue that strength has much more every-day applicability than endurance. When was the last time you had to run at a sustained effort for 30 minutes, outside an organized race? At least for me, that’s not something I encounter frequently (or ever). But carrying five-gallon water containers from the car, putting my luggage into the airplane overhead bin, moving furniture around while cleaning the house, those are things I do all the time. And every bit of strength I have makes those tasks easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&#34;float: left; width: 50%; margin-right: 1em;&#34; src=&#34;2013-10-01_121817.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the unique benefits of resistance training, one that cannot be realized any other way, is increased bone density. Bones strengthen when they are subjected to load, and they wither away in its absence. (Incidentally, that’s why astronauts experience &lt;a href=&#34;http://science1.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2001/ast01oct_1/&#34;&gt;substantial loss of bone mass during extended stays in zero g.&lt;/a&gt;) If you are young and engage in serious resistance training, you will build a strong skeletal structure that will serve you well for a life-time of activities. And if you are old and engage in serious resistance training, you will &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/9927006&#34;&gt;maintain and possibly even regain bone mass.&lt;/a&gt; By contrast, if you don’t do any exercise at all, or the only exercise you ever do is riding a stationary bike, you will most certainly experience substantial bone loss as you age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people who are not familiar with weight lifting are concerned of the possible injury risks. They picture themselves crushed under a 200lb barbell and can’t imagine how anybody in their right mind would subject themselves to such a risk. However, weightlifting is fairly safe when done properly, i.e., with good form and using weights that are appropriate to the strength level of the athlete. Compared to other physical activities one could engage in (soccer, football, cycling on public roads), weightlifting does not cause more serious or more frequent injuries. Even among people who lift a lot and lift very heavy, any injuries that occur &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1322916/&#34;&gt;are usually minor (&amp;lt;1 day of training missed).&lt;/a&gt; In the elderly, strength training caused &lt;a href=&#34;http://europepmc.org/abstract/MED/1758297&#34;&gt;about as many injuries as walking and many fewer than jogging.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only downside to heavy lifting is that you’ll look like Arnold Schwarzenegger. Nah, you won’t. Nobody looks like Arnold by accident. Not even Arnold. That look requires years of dedicated effort, very high-volume training, superior genetics, and the right pharmacological support. If you’re just a regular guy or gal going to the gym a few times a week, you’ll look fit, but you won’t look like the Michelin man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;For the purpose of this topic, we can safely assume that a person lifting weights in a gym is a man. There’s probably twenty guys lifting weights to one woman doing so. If you’re a woman who is seriously into lifting, I tip my hat to you, and you know what I’m talking about.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do we know anything about nutrition?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/13/do-we-know-anything-about-nutrition/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/13/do-we-know-anything-about-nutrition/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I was pointed to this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informationisbeautiful.net/visualizations/snake-oil-superfoods/&#34;&gt;infographic on superfoods,&lt;/a&gt; which aims at summarizing the scientific information we have about the health benefits of specific foods. It ranks health claims about specific foods by the strength of scientific evidence for the claim, and provides direct links to the relevant studies. The first thing you’ll notice if you look at it is that most claims fall well below promising. However, there are a few that are listed as good or strong. Since I’m somewhat of a nutrition geek, I of course went immediately and looked at the claims that are supposed to be the strongest. I was dismayed to find that of the four claims listed as very strong, at least two are rather dubious. Those two are barley and oats. (I stopped reading after that. The other two may well be dubious as well.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;superfoods.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Interactive superfoods infographic from informationisbeautiful.net.&#34; width=&#34;60%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.informationisbeautiful.net/visualizations/snake-oil-superfoods/&#34;&gt;Interactive superfoods infographic&lt;/a&gt; from informationisbeautiful.net.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two issues with those two claims: First, there is no credible health claim. Second, regardless of the validity of the claim itself, the claim is not well supported by evidence. Let’s consider these two pieces in turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credibility of the health claim:&lt;/strong&gt; Both oats and barley are listed for cholesterol. The problem is, cholesterol is not a disease. At best, cholesterol is a marker for a disease (cardiovascular disease, CVD). But it’s a really weak marker. It basically doesn’t work. The main reason we are obsessed with cholesterol is that in the 1950s, it was one of the first physiologic markers of CVD that could be easily measured. As a consequence, cholesterol testing became standard, and we all started to worry about cholesterol levels. But the science hasn’t held up. By now, it is pretty well established that CVD is caused primarily by inflammation, and inflammation is caused by an excess &lt;em&gt;number&lt;/em&gt; of oxidized Low-Density Lipoprotein particles (LDL particles). A standard cholesterol test measures the &lt;em&gt;amount&lt;/em&gt; of cholesterol carried by LDL particles. It is entirely possible to have a small number of particles carry a large amount of cholesterol (high cholesterol, low disease risk) or to have a large number of particles carry a small amount of cholesterol (low cholesterol, high disease risk). Thus, unless a food lowers the number of LDL particles, its effects on cholesterol levels are irrelevant. If this is news to you, read the nine-part series on cholesterol by Peter Attia, in particular &lt;a href=&#34;http://eatingacademy.com/nutrition/the-straight-dope-on-cholesterol-part-vi&#34;&gt;part vi&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://eatingacademy.com/cholesterol-2/the-straight-dope-on-cholesterol-part-ix&#34;&gt;part ix.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strength of evidence supporting the claim:&lt;/strong&gt; The link between oats/barley and cholesterol is supported by nutritional epidemiology, a field that has largely failed to produce any useful insight. Nutritional epidemiology can reveal &lt;em&gt;associations&lt;/em&gt; between components of a diet and diseases/disease markers, but it cannot establish any causal relation. Further, because the number of potential confounding variables is huge, and the effect size generally small, nearly all results in nutritional epidemiology are driven by unobserved or uncontrolled confounders. Yes, you could use nutritional epidemiology to establish that eating potassium cyanide is bad, or even that eating arsenic in large quantities is bad, but you’ll generally not be able to ascribe specific health benefits to regular foods that people have eaten for generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest confounder in nutritional epidemiology is the healthy person bias, which means that people who take good care of themselves will generally be healthier, and they will also do what is commonly believed to be healthy. At that point, nutritional epidemiology becomes a self-fulfilling prophecy. If we’re being told that oats and barley are good for us, then the most healthy-conscious people are going to eat more oats and barley, and hence we’ll see an association between consumption of oats and barley on the one hand and better health profiles on the other hand. The number of people who are like me, who are very health conscious but think that a diet of eggs, steak, and butter is healthy, is rather small. Therefore, I don’t expect any association study in the near future to support my view. But even if it did, it would be just as meaningless, for the same reasons. If you want to learn more about the problems with nutritional epidemiology, I recommend the work by Gary Taubes, in particular his book “Good Calories Bad Calories.” For a quick online read, check out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/09/16/magazine/16epidemiology-t.html&#34;&gt;this article.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; I don’t think we know much about nutrition at all at this time. I’m generally sceptical of any health claim, unless it is linked to a solid, experimentally verified mechanistic explanation. (There can be little doubt, for example, that an &lt;em&gt;excess&lt;/em&gt; of refined carbohydrates is a main driver in Type-II diabetes.) But even if a mechanistic explanation is available, we all have different genetic backgrounds and react to food differently as a consequence of that. For example, some people can eat grains and sugar all their life and be fine, while others need only look at a slice of bread and develop insulin resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For myself, I’ve come up with the following list of simple guidelines that I think are well supported and reasonable:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you eat something and it makes you feel bad, stop eating it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you’re frequently tired, have low energy, or have frequent digestive issues (heartburn, bloating, constipation, loose stools), you may be eating things your body can’t handle well. Try an elimination diet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you suffer from allergies, you may be eating things your body can’t handle well. Try an elimination diet.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you frequently have energy supply problems, i.e., you easily get tired in the afternoon, or you frequently feel like your brain will shut off unless you eat something immediately, you lack metabolic flexibility. Play around with the macronutrient composition of your diet (more fat, more protein, fewer carbs) and see if it makes a difference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you feel great, have good energy, generally feel awake and productive, it’s very unlikely that your diet has major issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year without breakfast</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/04/a-year-without-breakfast/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/04/a-year-without-breakfast/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;About a year ago, I gave up breakfast. The truth is, I’ve never liked breakfast. When I wake up, I’m not hungry. Why should I eat? However, breakfast is important, right? Everybody knows, breakfast is the most important meal of the day. Not eating breakfast is associated with all sorts of ills.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; It will &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21448130&#34;&gt;make you fat.&lt;/a&gt; It will give you &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23031568&#34;&gt;heart disease.&lt;/a&gt; Why would anybody in their right mind not have breakfast?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, two things happened about a year ago that made me change my mind. First, I learned about the recent trend of intermittent fasting, which basically amounts to not eating for extended periods of time on a somewhat regular schedule. One of the most popular schedules for intermittent fasting is 16 / 8, which means that every day you fast for 16 hours and then you have an 8 hour window in which you’re allowed to eat. If you do the math, if you skip breakfast, have lunch at noon, and finish dinner before 8pm, you’re on a 16 / 8 intermittent fasting schedule. So 16 / 8 intermittent fasting is really just a fancy term for “skipping breakfast.” Second, and more importantly, I read this life-changing article: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leangains.com/2012/06/why-does-breakfast-make-me-hungry.html&#34;&gt;“Why does breakfast make me hungry?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This article, written by one of the leading intermittent fasting proponents, explains in detail the hormonal reasons that cause some people to get really hungry shortly after breakfast. In fact, I had always noticed that I got really hungry about an hour or so after having had breakfast. And it didn’t seem to matter much what I ate, or how much I ate, for breakfast. I would be reliably hungry around 10am–11am. (I’m not an early riser.) So clearly, what was written in this article held true for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, between having a solid scientific explanation for why breakfast seemed to make me more not less hungry and a cool name for my new habit of not eating breakfast, I decided to take the plunge with 16 / 8 intermittent fasting. I haven’t had more than maybe 5–10 breakfasts, total, over the last year. Well, technically, my &lt;em&gt;break fast&lt;/em&gt; is the first meal I eat after fasting, regardless of the time. So to be more precise, I haven’t eaten before noon more than maybe 5–10 times, total, over the last year. When I started out, I would have coffee with some cream in the morning, so I had a small caloric intake shortly after waking up. But lately I’ve given that up as well. I now take my coffee black.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has been the outcome of this experiment? If you google “intermittent fasting,” you can read about all sorts of demonstrated or plausible health benefits, such as increased insulin sensitivity, improved body composition, or neuroprotection. But I don’t want to talk about that here. Instead, I want to talk about how it has affected me, personally, in my day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, my dependency on regular feeding has gone way down. Do you ever have the sense of “I’m starving; my brain is going to stop functioning unless I get food right now?” I used to have these sensations all the time. But if you think about it, it can’t be true. Unless you’re anorexic, if you live in the civilized world you’re not about to starve. You’re not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a day. Realistically, you’re not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a week. You’re certainly not about to starve if you haven’t had food for a few hours. So why would your body tell you so? Because after years of around-the-clock feeding, after rarely if ever experiencing more than a few hours in the non-fed state, your body has forgotten how to make effective use of its energy reserves. The required genes are not turned on. You can’t burn the layer of fat on your belly, even though it’s there. So your body screams for food. I know mine used to. Now, after a year of intermittent fasting, I don’t usually have this issue anymore. I’m certainly not hungry during my regular fasting window. And even if I have to fast longer, for example because I really have to get something done and can’t eat at my regular lunch hour, it doesn’t really matter to me. I just keep going, and I eat when I can. I also don’t usually snack anymore. Why should I need a snack if I’ve just eaten a few hours earlier? My body isn’t even done digesting yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other huge benefit is all the extra time I now have that I’m not spending on thinking about getting food, procuring food, preparing food, eating food. After getting out of bed, I usually have at least six waking hours before I first seriously think about eating. That’s a lot of productive time. Once you start cutting meals, you start realizing how much time and effort they require. Now mind you, I like to eat, and I like to prepare food. But once or twice a day is plenty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also don’t really experience afternoon slumps anymore. I feel overall much more awake. I have to add the caveat, though, that concomitantly with intermittent fasting I’ve also reduced my carb intake, a lot. Metabolically, the fasted state and the state on a low-carb, high-fat diet are very similar, so it’s hard to distinguish which intervention has caused what.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But intermittent fasting is not all unicorns and rainbows. There are a few clear downsides that need to be mentioned. First, it took me probably 6 months to get really comfortable with extended fasts (16+ hours). Initially, there were days when I felt quite hungry, when I was literally looking at the clock waiting for my feeding window to open up. Second, on an intermittent fasting protocol, when you eat, you need to EAT. I usually have two meals a day; hence, each meal needs to be around 1100 Cals or so. (I don’t really keep track, but I estimate that I eat around 2200 Cals a day. Definitely not less, maybe more.) I rarely worry about excess calories when I eat, but I frequently worry about not getting sufficiently many calories. As a regular faster, when you go out to eat with your friends and family, you may find that they think you’ve gone nuts. While they barely finish their chicken breast, you order a couple of appetizers, extra butter for your steak, and some extra sides. And still you leave the restaurant hungry. Third, if you have business or social meal events during your fasting window, you have to decide whether you want to be weird and watch your company eating or rather break your fast. I’ve gotten quite good with just having a black coffee during breakfast events, but depending on your job and social demands, it could be difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, has skipping breakfast made me fat and given me heart disease? Well, I have to admit that I’ve gained about eight pounds over the last year. And I’ve also lost about an inch around my waist. That’s what they mean when they say “improved body composition.” As to heart disease, so far I’m alive and kicking. Of course I can’t promise you that I won’t drop dead from a heart attack tomorrow. I’ll take my chances, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s the kind of nonsense that frequently passes for science in the field of nutrition. Not eating breakfast is &lt;em&gt;associated&lt;/em&gt; with all sorts of ills, mostly because both skipping breakfast and the associated ills are indicators of a stressful lifestyle and of poor eating habits. There’s absolutely no evidence that skipping breakfast in the context of a well-formulated diet and otherwise healthy lifestyle is harmful. Controlled studies generally find the opposite. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23672851&#34;&gt;skipping breakfast is a simple method to control overall caloric intake.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The author of this article is quite a character. But the science is solid.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The great weight-loss mystery</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/25/the-great-weight-loss-mystery/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/25/the-great-weight-loss-mystery/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The scientific consensus is that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0031938413002448&#34;&gt;long-term weight loss and weight control is impossible.&lt;/a&gt; Yet some people &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nwcr.ws/stories.htm&#34;&gt;seem to manage.&lt;/a&gt; So what gives? The truth is, nobody knows. The science of nutrition and weight loss is still recovering from 40 years of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Good-Calories-Bad-Controversial-Science/dp/1400033462/&#34;&gt;collective delusion&lt;/a&gt;, and frankly most scientific studies in this field are not that insightful. (I do have high hopes, though, that the &lt;a href=&#34;http://nusi.org/&#34;&gt;Nutrition Science Initiative&lt;/a&gt; is going to be a game changer. Some of the smartest people in the field, with access to very substantial private funding, should make a difference.) In the absence of solid science, I feel that I can freely speculate about why some people succeed and others don’t. So what follows below are my own opinions, poorly sourced and not scientifically proven.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are about six distinct approaches to weight loss (not necessarily mutually exclusive), and people have succeeded and failed on all of them: calorie counting, exercise, low-fat diets, low-carb diets, ancestral diets (paleo, primal), and intermittent fasting. The only thing that everybody seems to be able to agree on is that a low-protein diet (less than 0.7 grams of protein per pound of lean body mass per day) is not a good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that I’m following general convention here and talk about weight loss, even though we should really be talking about fat loss. There’s no reason to believe that muscle loss is good for anybody under any circumstances. Also note that I’m not considering surgery or drug-assisted methods for weight loss. (Yes, you can get ripped on &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trenbolone&#34;&gt;tren&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clenbuterol&#34;&gt;clen&lt;/a&gt;. And no, I wouldn’t do it.) I’m also not discussing serious medical issues that would prevent weight loss, such as &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/000387.htm&#34;&gt;insulinoma&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19730134&#34;&gt;leptin deficiency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So let’s consider the advantages and disadvantages of the six weight-loss approaches:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calorie counting.&lt;/strong&gt; Calorie counting absolutely works. If you meticulously keep track of everything you eat, and you make sure you eat at a consistent deficit of at least a few hundred calories a day, you will lose weight. However, there are a number of downsides: First, you have to be meticulous about keeping track, to the extent of weighing all your food. This requires an OCD-level of attention to your food intake. Second, as you restrict your food intake, you may feel low on energy, moody, or develop headaches. Third, long-term caloric restriction can mess up your leptin levels and your thyroid, and then you’ll need regular diet breaks to fix these issues, another level of complication.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exercise.&lt;/strong&gt; Conventional wisdom says that you need to exercise to lose weight. Yet the consensus these days, both among scientists and among fitness experts, is that exercise is a poor tool for weight loss. You generally can’t out-exercise a poor diet. I’ve seen estimates that maybe 5% of the population will be able to lose weight primarily through exercise and the remaining 95% will not. This statistic is easily verified in any gym, where you’ll find plenty of people that are fit, strong, and also overweight. My heart breaks everytime I see an obese person struggling on the treadmill or the elliptical. These people have seriously gotten the wrong advice. They’d be much better off fixing their diet and hanging out on the sofa in front of the TV than wasting their willpower on pointless exercise while keeping poor dietary habits.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-fat diets.&lt;/strong&gt; Low-fat diets are the diets we’ve been told for years we should follow to lose weight. They are supported by people like Ornish, who has demonstrated remarkable health improvements in people on his diet. (In this context, it’s important to realize that Ornish has only ever compared his diet to the standard American diet full of refined carbohydrates and soft-drinks. There’s no evidence whatsoever that Ornish’s diet performs better than other well-formulated, healthy diets.) There can be no doubt that low-fat diets can work. Some people do really well on those diets. Yet many others do not. And if you’re an adult male, and care about your testosterone levels, you might stay clear of these diets because &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/15741266&#34;&gt;they lower testosterone levels.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low-carb diets.&lt;/strong&gt; Low-carb diets, aka the Atkins diet, have been extremely polarizing ever since Atkins wrote his first book. For the longest time, we’ve heard that the Atkins diet will clog your arteries and cause heart disease. At the same time, a few daring individuals tried it out and found they lost a lot of weight. Careful review of the scientific evidence shows that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/The-Art-Science-Carbohydrate-Living/dp/0983490708/&#34;&gt;well-formulated low-carb diets are perfectly healthy,&lt;/a&gt; and I suspect that most obese people will do very well on low-carb diets. Major downsides of low-carb diets are (i) poor societal acceptance; you’re constantly swimming against the stream; (ii) a 3-4 week induction phase during which you may feel miserable; (iii) reduced thyroid function and low leptin, which may require targeted carbohydrate refeeds to address. Also, while low-carb diets sometimes seem to work like miracles for very obese people, they are not a weight-loss panacea. In particular, to reach extreme levels of leanness it may be necessary to up the carbohydrate intake.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ancestral diets (paleo, primal).&lt;/strong&gt; Ancestral diets are primarily about food quality. While many people are hung up on the name “paleo,” these diets fundamentally boil down to the recommendation to avoid highly processed foods and foods that make you sick. I don’t see how anybody can take issue with these recommendations. I personally am a big fan of paleo diets, in particular Mark Sisson’s &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.marksdailyapple.com/definitive-guide-to-the-primal-eating-plan/&#34;&gt;primal approach to food&lt;/a&gt;. At the same time, it must be said that just going paleo does not guarantee weight loss. In particular, if you knock yourself out on paleo desserts (e.g. banana-coconut smoothie, blueberry paleo ice cream, paleo muffins) you may find that the scales don’t move quite as much as you might have hoped.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intermittent fasting.&lt;/strong&gt; Intermittent fasting is the latest weight-loss craze. What it boils down to is skipping meals on a regular basis. For example, you could never eat breakfast, or you could eat only one meal a day, or you could eat only every other day. At this time, it’s not very well understood how to best fast intermittently, and whether the exact fasting schedule makes a difference. However, there can be no doubt that some people derive &lt;a href=&#34;http://bradpilon.com/weight-loss/my-birthday-dexa-results/&#34;&gt;impressive results from intermittent fasting.&lt;/a&gt; The science on intermittent fasting is still in its infancy, and we don’t really know whether the results are mostly due to inadvertend caloric restriction (it’s hard to overeat if you eat only 1-2 times a day) or due to actual hormonal changes, e.g. improved insulin sensitivity. But one thing seems pretty clear: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.leangains.com/2010/10/top-ten-fasting-myths-debunked.html&#34;&gt;skipping breakfast is not bad for you&lt;/a&gt;, despite what you will read in &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cosmopolitan.com/celebrity/news/skipping-meals&#34;&gt;Cosmopolitan&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://eatthis.menshealth.com/node/77644&#34;&gt;Men’s Health.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing I’m absolutely convinced of is that there’s not one best approach to weight loss. We all have different genetics, different personalities, and different societal pressures, that all affect which approaches may or may not work for us. Some people may do really well on calorie counting while others could never maintain the required discipline. Some people are really happy on low-carb, high-fat diets while others get grossed out by the amount of fat you have to consume on such diets. However, all approaches have in common that they require some amount of discipline; I’m not aware of any diet on which you can eat unlimited amounts of cookies. So it’s important to find an approach that works for you, and that you can stick with in the long run, with relative ease and consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m also convinced that short-term dieting is pretty pointless, unless you’re a bodybuilder or figure model getting ready for stage. You need to find an approach to eating (i.e., a diet) that you can maintain long-term, without thinking much about it. You should never think of diet as something you do for a few weeks to lose weight and then you stop. Diet is how you eat, every day, for the rest of your life. And if your diet doesn’t give you satisfaction, see if you can change it to something better. If I had to be on the Ornish diet, I’d feel like I’m eating sadness every day. By contrast, on my mostly low-carb, mostly paleo diet, I’m eating plenty of meat, eggs, fish, butter, cream, spinach (I love spinach), nuts, and dark chocolate, and I rarely if ever eat anything I’m not absolutely excited about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I believe that diet success largely depends on how well we can access the fuel stored as fat on our bodies. Approaches such as low-carb dieting, paleo, and intermittent fasting all create hormonal environments that increase metabolic flexibility and make it easier to use body fat for energy. The same hormonal changes may happen for those people who are successful on calorie-counting diets or extensive exercise, but not for those who fail on those approaches. Think about it as follows: Why is anybody ever hungry? One pound of fat contains roughly 3600 Calories, more than sufficient fuel for an entire day for most people. And very few people don’t carry at least a few pounds of extra fat on them. So why would they be hungry multiple times a day, clearly before those energy reserves have been used up? When we’re hungry, there is hormonal signaling that tells us we need to refuel, even though objectively we don’t. The more we can manipulate our body to suppress this hormonal signaling, the leaner we will be without experiencing discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m not saying here that exercise is pointless. Exercise has a lot of benefits, it’s just not very useful for weight loss. Also, an obese person already gets plenty of exercise just by carrying around all the extra weight they do. Immagine strapping a backpack weighing 50 or 100 lb onto your back and walking around with it all day. That would be plenty of exercise, wouldn’t it? I think that for any person who is seriously overweight, the right strategy has to be to first lose weight purely by diet, and then start exercising once a normal weight range has been reached.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
