<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Postdocs on Claus O. Wilke</title>
    <link>/tags/Postdocs/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Postdocs on Claus O. Wilke</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="/tags/Postdocs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Safety projects</title>
      <link>/blog/2015/07/01/safety-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2015/07/01/safety-projects/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been in science long enough, eventually you’ll have reached a point where you needed a safety project, either for yourself or for a student. A safety project is a project whose success is all but guaranteed, that doesn’t require much in terms of critical thinking or properly aligned stars. All that is required to complete a safety project is proper execution of the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most common example I see is the graduate student in year four or five who doesn’t have a single completed project but needs to graduate in a year. Alternatively, maybe tenure is looming and your cv looks thin, you need some papers on a given topic before you can submit a grant on that topic, or you’re a postdoc looking for a job and you don’t have that many papers yet. In all these cases, it’s a good idea to pursue a safety project. More generally, it’s a good idea to have a portfolio of different projects where some are high-risk, high-reward and some are low-risk safety projects that you know will give you some sort of publication at the end. So let’s take a look at a couple of generic types of safety projects that can be pursued in almost any research field you may be working in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;repeat-previous-study-with-larger-sample-size-or-expanded-conditions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Repeat previous study with larger sample size or expanded conditions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always possible to just redo an earlier study but to increase the scope somewhat. Choose a larger sample size, add experimental conditions, or use more recent raw data (if you’re doing bioinformatics). As long as your lab has the technical capability to carry out the study in the first place, there is really nothing that can go wrong here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;benchmark-or-compare-competing-methods&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Benchmark or compare competing methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For virtually any problem one might want to investigate, there are competing approaches to carry out the analysis. And it is rarely the case that we completely understand which approach is better, and under which conditions. So compare a couple of competing approaches in your area. Test them under a couple of different, carefully controlled conditions, and see how they perform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;write-a-methods-or-software-paper&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Write a methods or software paper&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have been working on some research topic for a while, chances are you have found some new ways of doing certain experiments, or you have written some software to do certain analyses. Thus, even if the actual experiments you have done don’t tell an interesting story, you may be able to just flesh out the methods or software you have developed and publish those.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;review-the-literature-on-a-topic&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Review the literature on a topic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literature reviews are often overlooked as serious scholarly contributions, in particular by graduate students and postdocs. And while scientists who only ever write reviews will likely develop the reputation of never having an original thought, there’s nothing wrong with writing the occasional review to bolster your resume, in particular early in your career. If you’re a graduate student or postdoc and your original research hasn’t been that successful lately, you can at least write a review on the area you’re working on. Publishing a review demonstrates both your understanding of the field and your ability to complete a project. I’d rather hire a scientist who has published one original research article and one review than one who has published only one original research article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you think of other types of projects that are generally safe and rely only on careful execution? If so, please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>In defense of anonymous peer review</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/10/12/in-defense-of-anonymous-peer-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/10/12/in-defense-of-anonymous-peer-review/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a recent blog post, Mick Watson argued that &lt;a href=&#34;http://biomickwatson.wordpress.com/2014/10/08/why-anonymous-peer-review-is-bad-for-science/&#34;&gt;anonymous peer review is bad for science.&lt;/a&gt; The post makes a number of insightful and valid points. However, the one point I cannot agree with is that junior scientists don’t need anonymity so they can freely speak their mind without fear of retaliation. Mick Watson argues that retaliation should be a non-issue, and that in the cases where it is not we just have to make it so. Frankly, I think this is simplistic black-and-white thinking. There are so many ways in which a senior person can make a junior person’s life more difficult; I would always recommend my graduate students and postdocs that they review anonymously unless they can write a very positive review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A senior person can retaliate against a junior person in a million subtle ways, and all of them are entirely ethical &lt;em&gt;unless they are done in bad faith.&lt;/em&gt; In fact, they are the exact same behaviors we engage in all the time to separate stronger science/scientists from weaker science/scientists. Let me just list a few examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don’t have to prominently cite Junior Person’s work in all of my papers if my papers don’t build directly on top of Junior Person’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I give invited lectures, I don’t have to mention Junior Person’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don’t have to invite Junior Person to give a Departmental Seminar at my institution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am free to rank Junior Person’s grant as “very good” rather than “excellent.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I’m on a grant panel and my colleagues are tearing apart Junior Person’s grant, I don’t have to speak up. I’m allowed to have no strong opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I don’t have to invite Junior Person to give a keynote lecture at the conference I’m organizing. In particular, if Junior Person is a man, I can always say “we needed more women speakers.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If Junior Person comes up for tenure, I don’t have to write a letter. I can claim I’m busy. Or, if I accept the assignment, I can weaken my statements of support, e.g., by saying “I think Junior Person would get tenure at my institution” instead of saying “Without doubt Junior Person would get tenure at my institution.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I’m handling one of Junior Person’s papers as Associate Editor, I can invite reviewers who I suspect are going to be critical of Junior Person’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If I’m handling one of Junior Person’s papers as Section Editor, I can place little seeds of doubt in the mind of my Associate Editor, e.g. by forwarding the paper with a note that says “I’m not entirely sure this fits into the scope of &lt;em&gt;Journal of Amazing Results.&lt;/em&gt; Feel free to reject without review if you have doubts yourself.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I’m reviewing a paper by somebody else, I don’t have to tell the authors that they should cite Junior Person’s work.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I’m reviewing Junior Person’s paper, I can place little seeds of doubt in the handling editor’s mind, e.g. by placing the following in the confidential comments to the editor: “There’s nothing technically wrong with this work, but I don’t quite see it meeting the standards of &lt;em&gt;Journal of Amazing Results.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I speak informally with colleagues, I don’t have to mention how amazing Junior Person’s work is. In fact, I don’t have to mention Junior Person at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course, I can do the opposite of all these behaviors if I really want to promote a junior scientist. In fact, I strongly suspect that these kinds of behaviors (subtle promotion or demotion of individuals) are at the heart of observed differences in recognition of male vs. female scientists, but that’s a topic for another day. For now, it suffices to emphasize that all of these behaviors are entirely reasonable, ethical, and even desired &lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; they are driven by an objective assessment of the quality of one person’s science over another’s, and not by personal biases, preferences, or desire for revenge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mick Watson argues that the scientific community should expel retaliating scientists. This suggestion sounds good in theory, but in practice it won’t work for any but the most egregious cases. And importantly, expelling retaliating scientists must not turn into a witch hunt. If I have to be concerned that any time I rank a grant proposal as “very good” or even just “good” somebody is going to accuse me of retaliation then I might as well stop reviewing grants or papers altogether.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mind you, I’m strongly in favor of &lt;em&gt;open&lt;/em&gt; peer review, where the entire review history is routinely published alongside the paper. It adds a lot of transparency to the process. And I think (though I have no data) that people will generally write more polite and factual reviews if they know that their reviews will become public eventually. In the end, though, science—like anything else in life—is always going to be somewhat unfair, open to manipulation, and subject to personal biases and opinion. As a minor protection against these mechanisms, in particular for junior people and women, scientists should be allowed to give anonymous feedback if they so choose.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Surviving the pre-tenure years at an R1 university</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/07/12/surviving-the-pre-tenure-years-at-an-r1-university/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/07/12/surviving-the-pre-tenure-years-at-an-r1-university/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;A few days ago, Pröf-like Substance &lt;a href=&#34;http://scientopia.org/blogs/proflikesubstance/2014/07/02/blog-carnival-surviving-the-pre-tenure-years/&#34;&gt;asked for posts with suggestions on how to survive the pre-tenure years.&lt;/a&gt; I went over my blogging history and realized that I hadn’t really written anything on this topic yet. Most of my advice to date is targeted at more junior scientists. So here is my attempt at giving some suggestions on how to make the most out of your years on the tenure track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The below applies to a tenure-track position at an R1 university, where your promotion will largely depend on your research productivity. I’m assuming that you’re teaching one course a semester or less, you have limited requirements in terms of departmental service, and you have access to a pool of capable graduate students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;relax-youre-not-going-to-die&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relax, you’re not going to die&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you are, but likely not any time soon. Being a fresh Assistant Professor on the tenure track is a pretty sweet deal. You have 5-7 years of guaranteed job security, during which nobody is going to tell you what to do. Your teaching load is pretty light. You get to spend most of your time doing stuff you really enjoy. Also, unless you’ve signed up with a place known for not tenuring their junior faculty members, such as Harvard, odds are in your favor. As long as you perform reasonably, you will probably get tenure. And, even if you are denied tenure, you’ll likely land on your feet and find a good job elsewhere. I can think of only a handful of people I know who were denied tenure, and all of them have done Ok. In fact, the vast majority of them are now in permanent academic positions at different (or even the same&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) universities, or at national labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stressing over tenure will only make you perform worse. To be successful, you need to be original, you need to be productive, and you need to inspire the students and postdocs in your lab to perform at their best. Worrying about tenure will interfere with all of this. So you might as well forget that there is such a thing as tenure, do your day-to-day job as best you can, and enjoy the ride.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;carefully-evaluate-any-advice-you-receive&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Carefully evaluate any advice you receive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll receive tons of advice on how to get tenure, including this piece you’re reading right now. Chances are, some of the advice you hear will not jibe with you. Some of it may even conflict with other advice you’re hearing. If you try to follow all this advice to the letter, you may feel dragged back and forth, and you may be doing all sorts of things that aren’t really you. Being an academic is all about being original and independent, doing things differently than other people have done, swimming against the stream. For any piece of advice somebody gives you, I’ll be able to point to a person who ignored it and got tenure anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this shouldn’t be a license to behave like a complete idiot. You will need to show some productivity, you will likely need some external funding, and you need to behave reasonably towards your colleagues and your students. But beyond that, there’s many ways to skin a cat, and you’ll have to find your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;write-at-least-two-papers-a-year&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Write at least two papers a year&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A minimum of two papers a year will provide insurance against any potential claims of poor productivity somewhere up the chain in the promotion process. These claims are usually brought up when applicants have on their cv one or more years without any papers, in particular in succession. One paper a year might be sufficient, but two is safer. It protects against the vagaries of the review process, which may overly delay some of your papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since you’re working at a place that emphasizes research, writing two papers a year should be eminently doable, even if you’re doing difficult experimental work that progresses slowly. Let’s do the math. Over a five-year period, that’s about 10 papers. Three of them can be review papers, which you can write without needing any new data. Two of them should be major contributions. Let’s say one is a piece of work you started as a postdoc. That’s a paper for which you should have most or all of the data already, and you should be able to write that quickly. The other should be the first major, independent piece from your own lab, which you may submit late in year three or early in year four so it comes out in time for your tenure review. Surely your research isn’t so complicated that you can’t generate enough data for a solid paper in three years. (If it is, maybe you should reevaluate your research program.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves five more papers to write. Those can be small, “least publishable unit” (LPU) papers. You should be able to write one of those each year. Write something about a method you developed. Re-analyze a previously published data set. Publish some of the partial results that will eventually lead to your big paper, three years down the line. Honestly, if you can’t write at least one LPU paper a year, you have to take a hard look at your standards and ask yourself whether they’re too high.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;publish-the-same-idea-multiple-times&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Publish the same idea multiple times&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not asking you to self-plagiarize, I’m just encouraging you to keep beating the horse even though you may think you have slain it already. If you’ve shown something once, show it again in a different way. Or in a different system. Or write a follow-up paper showing something that may be totally obvious to you given your earlier results. Then write a review paper about all of the above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, this approach will help you with productivity. Second, and more importantly, it will associate your name with the particular effect you’re investigating. As part of the promotion process, letter writers will be asked whether you’re a leader in your field. One of the best ways to become known and recognized as a leader is to say the same thing, over and over, until it’s been heard in even the last corner of every ivory tower.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;say-yes-to-as-many-conference-and-seminar-invitations-as-possible&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Say “yes” to as many conference and seminar invitations as possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I said in the previous point, being known helps tremendously with getting tenure. And traveling around the country giving talks at departmental seminars and conferences helps tremendously with being known. Thus, if you’re invited to speak somewhere, try to say “yes.” For some, this advice is a no-brainer. But if you don’t enjoy traveling, or if you have health concerns, or if you have teaching or family obligations that make it difficult to travel, you may be inclined to say “no.” Of course there are perfectly valid reasons to decline a travel invitation, and in the end you have to weigh the various priorities and make your own decision. My advice, if you have a tendency to say “no,” is to make an honest assessment of how much travel you can realistically accommodate into your life, and then plan accordingly. For example, you might decide that you can travel &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; times a year, or that you need at least &lt;em&gt;Y&lt;/em&gt; weeks between trips, or that you can never travel in the spring. If you have a clear system like that, then it’ll be easy for you to take advantage of the opportunities that come your way. And you’ll also feel more comfortable saying “no” if you have a straightforward reason to decline, e.g.: “I’m sorry, this would be my second trip in August, and I never make more than one trip a month.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;apply-for-funding-early-often-and-widely&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Apply for funding early, often, and widely&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll probably need funding to receive tenure. Even if your university doesn’t make funding a requirement, you’ll probably need funding to keep your lab going/productive, and you’ll definitely need a productive lab to get tenure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to publishing a paper, getting a grant is much harder. Most papers I write get published; most grants I write get rejected. However, the good thing about grants is that you don’t need to obtain that many. If you’re receiving one medium-sized grant every other year or so you’re doing pretty good. To maximize your chances of receiving funding, apply often and widely. You should probably write 3-5 grants a year. Most importantly, don’t just try one funding agency or one program. Even if you’re told you need the R01 to get tenure, I doubt your colleagues will be upset with you if you’re getting a nice grant from the Navy instead. Also, don’t write all of these grants entirely by yourself. Build some collaborations, and try to be part of some larger research teams. Again, even if you’re told you need the single-investigator grant, your promotion committee will certainly rank collaborative funding higher than no funding at all. And, any funding you manage to secure helps you to hire people and pay for experiments which may be preliminary results in your next single-investigator grant application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;make-sure-you-recruit-graduate-students-as-soon-as-possible&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make sure you recruit graduate students as soon as possible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate students are the lifeblood of a new lab. Attempt to recruit one or two good ones as early as possible. The moment you receive your offer letter, find out how graduate recruitment works, and make sure you’re in the system and prospective students know about you. If possible, attend events for prospective graduate students even if you haven’t actually started your position yet. Ask your (prospective) department to add you to their web site as soon as possible. If your department has a rotation system, make sure you’re on the rotation schedule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate student recruitment happens only once a year, and if you miss the first year, you’ll risk sitting in an empty lab for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;be-careful-with-your-postdoc-hires&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Be careful with your postdoc hires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hiring a postdoc can be tricky for a young faculty member, unless you’re at Harvard or similar, where postdocs are willing to join any lab just for the overall reputation of the university. Most really good postdocs prefer to go to large, established labs with a proven track record. I’ve heard lots of stories from young faculty members about the postdoc woes they have gone through. This doesn’t mean you shouldn’t hire a postdoc at all. It just means you should focus on getting someone really good and vet them well. One option that may work is hiring a student from a past adviser, possibly somebody you worked with when you were a postdoc yourself. In case of doubt, recruit graduate students rather than postdocs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;teaching-may-hurt-you-but-it-is-unlikely-to-help-you&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teaching may hurt you but it is unlikely to help you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your teaching is atrocious, you may be denied tenure even if your research is stellar. However, if your teaching is stellar and your research weak, chances are nobody will care about your teaching performance. So plan accordingly. Put enough effort into your teaching so that nobody can say you are a bad teacher, but don’t sacrifice your research program for the goal of becoming the best teacher in the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;do-things-that-make-you-happy&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Do things that make you happy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter how much you enjoy being an academic, there will be elements to your job that you don’t enjoy. It’s a job after all. Therefore, it is important that you find a balance between doing the things that you do enjoy and those that you don’t. When you’re under pressure to perform, such as with tenure looming, it is easy to get dragged down into doing mostly the things that you don’t enjoy but that must get done. You need to be aware of this dynamic and consciously work against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, assume you have successfully set up lab, and you now have a couple of grad students and a technician. They are all reasonably capable and they produce results. What your lab now needs is papers and grants. And you’re the only one in the lab who can write them. So, clearly, you should be spending all your time writing and none of your time doing experiments, right? This is only true if you really enjoy writing papers and grants. Let’s say you don’t. Let’s say what you really enjoy is standing at the bench doing experiments. In this case you need to find a balance such that you sometimes get to do the things that made you become an academic in the first place. Maybe you write in the morning and work at the bench in the afternoon. Or you work at the bench one day a week. Even though theoretically your productivity would be higher if you spent all your time doing the things only you can do, in practice your productivity will only stay high if you’re happy. If standing in front of a bench makes you happy, then absolutely do so, without any regrets.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Not getting tenure the first time round but eventually getting it anyway seems to be somewhat common at UT. I can think of at least four cases since I’ve been here.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;See also: &lt;a href=&#34;http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/2013/07/21/the-awesomest-7-year-postdoc-or-how-i-learned-to-stop-worrying-and-love-the-tenure-track-faculty-life/&#34;&gt;The Awesomest 7-Year Postdoc.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the topic of whether it is worth it to write low-impact papers, see also &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/11/3/no-one-reads-your-paper-either&#34;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; I wrote a while back.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The same concept applies to balancing your job with the rest of your life. You need to do things that make you happy. Go exercise, watch a play, learn how to juggle, write a blog, write a novel. Anything that gives you joy deserves some of your time.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Share your preliminary work with other people, even if you think it’s crap</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/07/08/share-your-preliminary-work-with-other-people-even-if-you-think-its-crap/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/07/08/share-your-preliminary-work-with-other-people-even-if-you-think-its-crap/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;It’s quite common for me to have students tell me “the analysis didn’t work out” or “the figure looks bad” or “I don’t have any useful results.” And it’s also quite common for the students to be wrong. Sometimes, students have amazing results but are all disappointed because the results aren’t what they had expected. These students fail to see the data for what they are. More commonly, the students may be right in that the data aren’t that great, but usually I can see something in the data that the student didn’t. In either case, it is important that we look at the data together, because jointly we will see more than either of us individually would have seen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, while some students are happy to show me their “failed” analyses and complain about how nothing works, others are more reserved, sometimes to the point of reluctance. The latter students don’t feel comfortable showing me their preliminary results, or sometimes any results at all, unless they think the work is completed.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; These students are probably under the mistaken impression that I will judge them for “failed” analyses, or that I expect a complete analysis, with proper interpretation of all data points, at all times, or that having remaining open questions means I’ll think the student did a poor job. On the contrary, I want to see all these preliminary, incomplete, and confusing results. The data are the data, and I want to be able to draw my own conclusions about them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, I submit that unless you know for sure you made a mistake (say, your code has a bug and you know it), you will always be better off discussing your work with other people than silently deciding it’s not good enough. And if your results seem too trivial or wrong to talk about them with your advisor, then at least talk them through with a fellow student or postdoc.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Think about it this way: every time you generate a result or make a figure, and then you delete it before you show it to somebody else, you’re preempting the possibility that somebody else might see something useful in your work. And while a lot of what you’re doing may indeed be worthless, I’d argue that unless you’re a complete disaster, you’ll probably do at least one thing every day that is actually worthwhile. So every day, you should produce some sort of result that you then discuss with somebody else.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, the necessity of sharing preliminary work with other people doesn’t stop once you graduate. Just because you have a PhD doesn’t mean that you’re suddenly able to always see the data exactly for what they are. Sometimes even the most experienced scientists are overly attached to a particular hypothesis or miss some critical detail in their data. That’s why many experienced scientists routinely talk to their colleagues about work in progress, why they present preliminary results at conferences or seminar talks, and why they request comments on manuscript drafts and preprints. In my mind, even traditional peer review serves primarily the purpose of having another set of eyes look over the data and check whether the authors are over- or underhyping their results.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing that really changes once you graduate and/or complete your postdoc is that suddenly there is no adviser anymore who makes you show him/her your latest work. Now it’s entirely on you to seek out the advice you need and to receive the feedback that will make your work better. And, if you are advising students yourself, it’s now your job to make them talk to you and show you what they’re doing, warts and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re my student and you think this blog post is about you, let me tell you: you’re not the only one.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;But realize that sometimes students talk each other down. Just because your fellow grad students say what you did was stupid doesn’t mean it actually was; they may just lack perspective.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;You might argue that you’re working in a field where results accumulate slowly, hence you can’t possibly discuss results from individual days. E.g., you’re collecting beetles in the field, and you need three field seasons before you have enough data to test your hypothesis. My response is that nevertheless there are tons of preliminary data that you should discuss with somebody. E.g., if you’re collecting beetles every day, you know how many you found each day, where you found them, what physical characteristics they had, etc., and how these quantities change over time. All of these are worthwhile preliminary results that you should look at, graph, and discuss with a third party.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second case, where reviewers see more in the data than the authors, is more common than you may think. Many papers get really good only after a solid round of peer review, and frequently the reviews in those cases are not “X is wrong” but rather “You have done X but you should also do Y, and in combination you could conclude Z which would be really cool.”&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to develop a research question, Part II</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/18/how-to-develop-a-research-question-part-ii/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/18/how-to-develop-a-research-question-part-ii/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;After my last post discussing &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2014/6/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question&#34;&gt;how to develop a research question&lt;/a&gt;, Sergey Kryazhimskiy asked me to write about how to find the rare good research idea among the many mediocre ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ClausWilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; After 2 successful projects the problem shifts to choosing a rare good research idea among many mediocre ones. Next post? 2/2
&lt;/p&gt;
— Sergey Kryazhimskiy (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@skryazhi&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/skryazhi/status/478349857540042753&#34;&gt;June 16, 2014&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that I don’t really know how to do this. If you do, please tell me. I’m sure I could strengthen my research program by picking better problems. Nevertheless, despite my ignorance, I’ve had a reasonably successful career to date. And it was probably not entirely due to sheer luck. So this should give you hope. Even if you don’t know how to pick good problems, you may succeed in science nonetheless. Just work on the problems that seem important to you and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because I don’t know how to answer Sergey’s question, at first I thought that I wouldn’t have much to say on this topic. However, not knowing something hasn’t kept me from writing a 1500-word blog post about it. After some pondering, I thought it might be useful to review what other people have said on this topic. If you spend some time with Google, you’ll find expert advice on how to choose a good research problem. For example, in Uri Alon’s paper &lt;a href=&#34;http://wws.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/uploads/nurturing/howtochoosegoodproblem.pdf&#34;&gt;“How To Choose a Good Scientiﬁc Problem”&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; there is a nice graphic (here reproduced as Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;) ranking potential problems according to their difficulty (hard to easy) and according to the gain in knowledge their solution would provide (small to large). Easy problems with a small gain in knowledge are good beginner problems, hard problems with a large gain in knowledge are good long-term goals for an established researcher, and easy problems with a large gain in knowledge are perfect for a postdoc. And nobody should work on hard problems that lead to small gains in knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure1&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pareto front of worthwhile research questions. Research questions can be ranked according to difficulty (hard to easy) and gain in knowledge (small to large). The best problems are those that provide the maximum gain of knowledge for the chosen difficulty level. One should never work on hard problems that provide little gain in knowledge. After U. Alon (2009).&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 1: Pareto front of worthwhile research questions. Research questions can be ranked according to difficulty (hard to easy) and gain in knowledge (small to large). The best problems are those that provide the maximum gain of knowledge for the chosen difficulty level. One should never work on hard problems that provide little gain in knowledge. After U. Alon (2009).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is all nice and well, until you realize that it is basically impossible to rank problems &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; along either dimension. Uri Alon’s paper explains why. Science does not normally progress in a direct path from A to B. We may intend to work towards B, but on our way there we get stuck in “the cloud,” where every attempt to get closer to B fails, until eventually we give up and go for C, a problem that we hadn’t even considered beforehand (Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;). The two immediate consequences of this process are that (i) we don’t know how hard it will be to get from A to C, and (ii) we don’t know how much of a gain in knowledge C will provide, in both cases because we don’t even know C exists when we start. Thus, even though Uri Alon’s ranking of problems along difficulty and gain in knowledge is beautiful and convincing, it is also quite useless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure2&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig2.png&#34; alt=&#34;How we would like to do science (left) and how it actually works (right). Here, A represents what we currently know and B represents what we would like to know. Our desire is to move from A to B in as direct a line as possible. However, we usually get stuck as we are approaching B, things don’t work out, and we keep taking detours and going in circles. Uri Alon calls this state the cloud. Eventually, we give up on reaching B and instead head for C, a new insight that we found while wandering in the cloud. Usually, C represents the solution to a problem we weren’t even aware of when we started. After U. Alon (2009).&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 2: How we would like to do science (left) and how it actually works (right). Here, A represents what we currently know and B represents what we would like to know. Our desire is to move from A to B in as direct a line as possible. However, we usually get stuck as we are approaching B, things don’t work out, and we keep taking detours and going in circles. Uri Alon calls this state &lt;em&gt;the cloud.&lt;/em&gt; Eventually, we give up on reaching B and instead head for C, a new insight that we found while wandering in the cloud. Usually, C represents the solution to a problem we weren’t even aware of when we started. After U. Alon (2009).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what can be done? If we keep reading Uri Alon’s article, we find that he makes some useful suggestions on how to pick important problems. He writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental aspects of science is that the interest of a problem is subjective and personal. (…) Ranking problems with consideration to the inner voice makes you more likely to choose problems that will satisfy you in the long term. (…) One way to help listening to the inner voice is to ask: ‘‘If I was the only person on earth, which of these problems would I work on?’’ (…) Another good sign of the inner voice are ideas and questions that come back again and again to your mind for months or years. (…) It is remarkable that listening to our own idiosyncratic voice leads to better science. It makes research self-motivated and the routine of research more rewarding. In science, the more you interest yourself, the larger the probability that you will interest your audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, if you’re not sure which problems to work on, work on the ones that excite you!&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uri Alon is not the only one who has commented on this topic. The famous computer-science pioneer Richard Hamming (of the Hamming distance and Hamming codes) used to give a talk entitled “You and Your Research,” which touches on this issue among other things. You can read a transcript &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The whole thing is worth reading. Here, I’ll just cite a few relevant paragraphs. First this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are famous it is hard to work on small problems. This is what did Shannon in. After information theory, what do you do for an encore? The great scientists often make this error. They fail to continue to plant the little acorns from which the mighty oak trees grow. They try to get the big thing right off. And that isn’t the way things go. So that is another reason why you find that when you get early recognition it seems to sterilize you. In fact I will give you my favorite quotation of many years. The Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, in my opinion, has ruined more good scientists than any institution has created, judged by what they did before they came and judged by what they did after. Not that they weren’t good afterwards, but they were superb before they got there and were only good afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, don’t try too hard to make a big splash. Just keep working on a variety of problems and see which ones turn out to be useful. While you do so, take notice of things that repeatedly don’t work. Those may be hints that can lead to major insights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that if you look carefully you will see that often the great scientists, by turning the problem around a bit, changed a defect to an asset. For example, many scientists when they found they couldn’t do a problem finally began to study why not. They then turned it around the other way and said, “But of course, this is what it is” and got an important result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, keep an eye out for great opportunities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great scientists, when an opportunity opens up, get after it and they pursue it. They drop all other things. They get rid of other things and they get after an idea because they had already thought the thing through. Their minds are prepared; they see the opportunity and they go after it. Now of course lots of times it doesn’t work out, but you don’t have to hit many of them to do some great science. It’s kind of easy. One of the chief tricks is to live a long time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What can you do to increase the chance that opportunities come your way? Here is Feynman’s suggestion, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/199701/comm-rota.pdf&#34;&gt;as recounted by Gian-Carlo Rota&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have to keep a dozen of your favorite problems constantly present in your mind, although by and large they will lay in a dormant state. Every time you hear or read a new trick or a new result, test it against each of your twelve problems to see whether it helps. Every once in a while there will be a hit, and people will say, “How did he do it? He must be a genius!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is thus to wander around in the cloud and always keep an eye out for exciting opportunities that may open up. While you’re in the cloud, aiming for B, there may be many C’s that come your way that you could pursue, but most of them will not be worthwhile (Figure &lt;a href=&#34;#fig:figure3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;). However, on occasion, you stumble upon something that is really neat (C&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt; in the Figure), and when that happens you should drop everything else and pursue that opportunity. I would recommend applying the following test: Do you personally think you’ve stumbled upon an exciting opportunity? If yes, go for it. If no, keep looking for something else to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;&lt;span id=&#34;fig:figure3&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;Fig3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Scientific opportunities in the cloud. While we are stuck in the cloud, we encounter all sorts of new insights. Most of them are boring, however, and we shouldn’t pursue them further. But, on occasion, we stumble upon an exciting new insight. When this happens, great scientists drop everything else and seize the opportunity.&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;
Figure 3: Scientific opportunities in the cloud. While we are stuck in the cloud, we encounter all sorts of new insights. Most of them are boring, however, and we shouldn’t pursue them further. But, on occasion, we stumble upon an exciting new insight. When this happens, great scientists drop everything else and seize the opportunity.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this whole process, you might wonder what’s the point of B. If we never get to B, do we need it in the first place? I think we do. B gives us a broad sense of direction while we’re not sure where we’re going in the cloud. Until we have identified an exciting opportunity C, we might as well keep chasing B. Who knows, with luck, we might even manage to get to B at some point. It happens on occasion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;U. Alon (2009) &lt;a href=&#34;http://wws.weizmann.ac.il/mcb/UriAlon/sites/mcb.UriAlon/files/uploads/nurturing/howtochoosegoodproblem.pdf&#34;&gt;How To Choose a Good Scientiﬁc Problem.&lt;/a&gt; Mol. Cell 35:726-728.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It should be noted here that the degree to which a problem is of interest to the broader scientific community depends also on how well it is marketed. You can pick problems you know the community finds interesting, or alternatively you can convince the community that they should find interesting what you are working on. Many of the very successful scientists do the latter. In fact, fame and recognition often go to the person who convinced the community that a problem was worthwhile, not to the person who actually solved the problem in the first place.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hamming gave this talk many times. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&#34;&gt;transcript available here&lt;/a&gt; is from March 7, 1986. There is also a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a1zDuOPkMSw&#34;&gt;video recording,&lt;/a&gt; from June 6, 1995. The transcript and the video are largely identical, but I found that the video added a few interesting points that weren’t in the transcript.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;G.-C. Rota (1997) &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ams.org/notices/199701/comm-rota.pdf&#34;&gt;Ten Lessons I Wish I Had Been Taught.&lt;/a&gt; Notices of the AMS 44:22-25.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to develop a research question</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/15/how-to-develop-a-research-question/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the most daunting prospects for a fresh graduate student is having to develop a solid research question.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; In my experience, many graduate students feel like they don’t even know where to start. The literature can seem overwhelming, everything has already be done by somebody, and in any case it’s impossible to really know all the literature there is anyway. Making matters worse, almost every cohort or lab inevitably has one or two students who just seem to be fountains of good ideas, who constantly come up with new research ideas they want to pursue. As a result, students who are less inventive or less imaginative can feel like they’re not cut out for a career in research, they’re never going to have the necessary ideas to sustain a research program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that having good ideas is a skill that can be learned. There are simple strategies that almost always work. In the following, I describe one strategy in particular that I’ve found useful over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;define-a-vision-for-your-research&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Define a vision for your research&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you start doing any concrete work towards developing your specific research question, you need to know what broad topic you want to work on. I call this the research vision. It turns out that developing a research vision is not that hard, for two reasons: First, the vision doesn’t have to be that specific; it doesn’t have to come with specific ideas for projects you want to do or questions you want to pursue. It’s just a guiding idea that tells you where to start. For example, a vision could be “I want to do computational work in cancer genomics” or “I want to study experimentally how bacteria adapt to novel environments” or “I want to work in infectious disease epidemiology.” Second, choosing a particular vision over another one is generally a low-stakes decision. There is interesting and valuable research to be done in the context of nearly any reasonable research vision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing you should double-check though, in particular as graduate student or postdoc, is whether the vision you want to pursue fits broadly into the topics your lab is working on. If you’re in a molecular biology lab that studies cancer genetics but your research vision is to investigate the effects of climate change on future precipitation patterns then you have a problem. In this situation, either find a different research vision or consider switching labs.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;read-the-literature&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Read the literature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have decided on your research vision, you need to start reading the relevant literature. There are two ways to proceed: First, if your research vision matches well with the work that is already going on in the lab you’re in, then start by reading the lab’s papers. Also, ask your PI for suggestions on which papers to read. Use all these papers as your starting point for a careful literature search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, if your research vision deviates somewhat from the current direction of the lab,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or if there are other reasons why you can’t ask anybody for relevant papers, then skip right ahead to the literature search.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start your literature search, enter some key words or phrases into Google Scholar and see what comes up. Google Scholar tends to place the most highly cited papers at the top of its search results, so you’ll almost never go wrong by looking into the top hits. Using these papers as your starting point, expand your search by reading the papers that they cite (searching backwards in time), and also look up the more recent papers that cite them (searching forward in time).&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; By alternating between backwards and forwards search you will develop a solid grasp of the field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to Google Scholar, the “related citations” function on PubMed is also an excellent way to deepen your knowledge of the field. Look up a paper on PubMed, and then read through the papers that PubMed flags as related to the paper you looked up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;stop-reading-the-literature-and-start-doing-something&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stop reading the literature and start doing something&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s great to be a well-read scientist. Most students don’t read enough. There’s always something else to read. However, at some point, you have to stop reading and start doing. To give a concrete (but somewhat arbitrary) cutoff: If you’ve been reading for two months or more, or if you’re familiar with over 100 papers in your broad area, and you still feel like you don’t know enough of the literature to come up with your own project, then reading even more is likely not going to improve your situation much. At this point, it’s more important that you start doing actual research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you start if you’re not sure what your project is? My recommendation is to always start by reproducing somebody else’s work. Among all the papers in your broad area that you have read, pick one or two that you liked the most, and simply try to repeat what they did.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Very quickly, you will discover a few things: 1. It’s not that easy to reproduce existing work, and you can learn a lot in the process. 2. There are flaws, limitations, or pitfalls that weren’t really described in the paper. Maybe the paper’s methods work only under very specific conditions and fail the moment you try something slightly different. Or the methods are somewhat unreliable and fail at random times/under random conditions. 3. There are all sorts of things you’d like to know. Such as why the methods always fail when it’s raining outside. Or why there are certain strange trends you see in the raw data. 4. There are all sorts of things you’d like to have. Like a better way to prep your samples. Or some additional measurements no existing method can produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voilà, you have your research question. In fact, you probably have more than you bargained for.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You may have so many questions that you still don’t know where to start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;keep-it-simple&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Keep it simple&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it’s important to keep things simple. Of the many open questions you have, pursue the one that requires the simplest possible extension to existing work but will still provide meaningful progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I’ve ever seen a student fail for trying to do something too simple. However, I’ve seen plenty of student fail for trying things that were too complicated. Most students overestimate the complexity that is required to do good science. It’s better to do something simple, write it up, and publish than to do something complicated, get stuck, and get discouraged.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;conclusions&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may think the whole process I propose is haphazard. I suggested you start with a random topic, do some reading, try to reproduce somebody’s work, and then pursue some extension to the work, an extension that will hopefully reveal itself to you as you work on the topic. The reason why this seems haphazard is because it is. Science doesn’t follow a simple A to B path. Albert Einstein famously said “If we knew what it was we were doing, it would not be called research.” Uri Alon calls it &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/uri_alon_why_truly_innovative_science_demands_a_leap_into_the_unknown&#34;&gt;being stuck in the cloud.&lt;/a&gt; Donald Rumsfeld talked about the unknown unknowns. Even though Rumsfeld wasn’t talking about scientific research, he correctly described the world in which most scientists operate day to day. We usually don’t know what we’re doing, we don’t know where we’re going, and we don’t know what we don’t know. However, we do stuff anyway, and from time to time we stumble upon a useful and novel bit of knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;And sometimes, postdocs or even young faculty members struggle with the same issue. It mostly depends on when you were asked for the first time to come up with your own project. If your graduate project was basically handed to you by your PI, and similarly during your postdoc you were working on somebody else’s project, then you may never have independently developed a project before becoming an assistant professor.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I would almost always recommend against switching lab while in grad school, but that is a topic for a different post.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;It may seem strange that a graduate student would have her own research vision that differs from the lab’s vision. However, this scenario is often quite productive, both for the student and for the lab. The best PhD theses can take an entire lab into a new direction. PIs are generally aware of this and want their students to bring new ideas into the lab.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Searching forward in time used to be a complicated undertaking but it is trivial with tools such as Google Scholar. Simply click on “cited by” and see which other papers cite the paper you’re interested in.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, you have to choose a paper that uses methods and/or materials that you have access to. If your favorite paper in the field uses a mass spec and you don’t have access to one then that’s a bad paper to try to reproduce.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn6&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;That’s one of the reasons why senior scientists usually have tons of research ideas. The longer you’ve been around in science, the more you’re aware of what we don’t know.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uri Alon on creativity and staying sane in science: &#34;Yes and ...&#34;</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/06/14/uri-alon-on-creativity-and-staying-sane-in-science-yes-and/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/06/14/uri-alon-on-creativity-and-staying-sane-in-science-yes-and/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;I just saw this &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/uri_alon_why_truly_innovative_science_demands_a_leap_into_the_unknown&#34;&gt;nice TED Talk by Uri Alon&lt;/a&gt; about how new scientific insights are generated. Even though the talk is a year old I think it’s worth posting, so here you go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uri makes a number of points that I’ve been aware of for a long time but have never seen expressed quite so clearly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discovery is not linear. We usually don’t obtain the result we were aiming for. However, as we try, we make worthwhile discoveries that constitute the real scientific progress.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It is not helpful to shoot down ideas before you’ve even tried them. Statements like “this is never going to work” “this is too complicated” “X, Y, and Z are going to go wrong” “nobody will believe me anyway” are all not useful. Accept the crazy ideas, try them out, and see what happens. Say “yes and …”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Being worried about your research shuts down your creativity. Try to be more relaxed, even if things don’t go the way you think they should. Don’t try to obtain a particular goal, focus more on exploring the unknown.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When things don’t go well, talk to other people, look for support. Science can be hard on your mental well being, and to keep going sometimes you just need people to cheer you on.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI, and 6 reasons not to</title>
      <link>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2014/01/25/6-reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi-and-6-reasons-not-to/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;One of the eternal questions of graduate schools is whether you should work with a junior or a senior PI. I have commented on this question before &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/29/how-to-choose-the-right-lab-for-graduate-school&#34;&gt;and argued that either decision can be the right one.&lt;/a&gt; Here, I present a more comprehensive list of arguments for and against. As you’ll see, there are plenty of arguments going both ways. You may assign more weight to some than others and thus arrive at a decision that is best for you. Ultimately, I think it doesn’t matter too much; there are other factors that are more important, such as whether you enjoy and fit in with the lab’s culture and approach to research, collaboration, publication, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here is my list. If you can think of something I forgot, please let me know in the comments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-junior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a junior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you’re one of the early students in the lab of a rising star, you can rise to prominence with your PI. You may end up as the first author in one or more of your PI’s key publications, and this in turn may secure your own faculty position and seniority in the field.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may have more time to supervise you. The lab is likely relatively small and you’re not competing with 10 other lab members for your PI’s attention. Also, your PI may not yet be that involved with university service and other non-research obligations, and thus have more time to interact with the lab (i.e., you).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A young lab may be doing some really novel, cutting-edge work. An older lab is more likely to work on the stuff they’ve always worked on, stuff that was real innovative 10 years ago but is an old hat now.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your PI is not that established, there’s less risk that once you graduate your adviser is such a towering influence in the field that you can’t establish yourself as distinct from him/her.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a large, established lab, you might find yourself working on a small part of a larger project. Even if you do excellent work, your name might in the end not get associated with the big paper that comes out of that work. (I’m not saying you won’t be a coauthor. I’m saying you might be one of 20 coauthors and nobody will think you were the person who made it happen.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The younger your adviser, the less likely it is that he or she come down with a debilitating disease or die a sudden death. For example, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3298961/figure/fig2/&#34;&gt;the risk of death of a 60-year old man is 10 times higher than that of a 35-year old man.&lt;/a&gt; Just avoid younger PIs with a passion for BASE jumping, cave diving, or motorcycle racing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reasons-to-do-your-graduate-work-in-the-lab-of-a-senior-pi&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6 reasons to do your graduate work in the lab of a senior PI&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI is untested. It is less clear how sustainable the PI’s research program is, how likely the PI will be able to attract funding, and how good his/her research ideas are. If the junior PI is on a bad trajectory, it is likely that your PhD won’t be that great either. (Keep in mind, though, that your PI’s success depends to some extent on you!)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the field. The two of you may find yourselves fighting uphill battles with reviewers, journal editors, and other labs in the field. The exact same work might be lauded as the world’s greatest invention since sliced bread when coming from an established, senior lab or derided as inconsequential, boring, or wrong when coming from a junior lab. Having a junior adviser can also make it harder to find an academic job after you graduate.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A junior PI may not be that powerful or well-connected in the university. This may put you at a disadvantage when it comes to TA positions, university fellowships, and other dealings with university administration. In particular, if something unexpected happens, e.g. the class you were supposed to TA for gets cancelled, a senior PI is more likely going to have resources to deal with the situation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The lab of a junior PI may not have the resources you will need to carry out outstanding research. In particular, if you join a lab in its first or second year, you may find yourself spending a year or longer just setting up lab infrastructure. By contrast, a large, established lab will likely have everything you need to do ground-breaking work the moment you walk into the door.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since your PI is new, he or she still has to prove himself/herself. As a result, your PI might end up competing with you. For example, a junior PI might insist on being the one presenting your work at a conference where a senior PI might let you present your work yourself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you join the lab of an untenured professor, you risk that your PI won’t get tenure while you’re in the lab. That experience is likely going to be as disruptive to you as it will be to your PI. The worst-case scenario is an upcoming tenure decision 2-4 years out from when you start your PhD. If you’re only in your first year when your PI doesn’t get tenure, you should be able to just join another lab, without having wasted much time and effort. And if you’re in your fifth year or later, you should be able to finish up your dissertation work even if your PI has to close down his/her lab and move on. But if you’re right in the middle of your thesis work, you may have to throw away 2-3 years of work and start from scratch.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How good is good enough?</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/10/how-good-is-good-enough/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/10/how-good-is-good-enough/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The other day, I wrote a blog post about &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;critical decision points in an academic career.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://ivory.idyll.org/blog/&#34;&gt;Titus Brown&lt;/a&gt; felt that I was perpetuating the belief that being “good enough” is a necessary requirement to becoming a faculty member. My intention in writing the post was actually the exact opposite, to argue that whether somebody is or is not “good enough” is largely irrelevant to their success in academia, and not something they should spend much time thinking about. Clearly I didn’t quite succeed in getting my points across, so I’ll try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RELenski&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@RELenski&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; You know, I really disagree with &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@clauswilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; phrasing: “Are you good enough to be a faculty member?” even in context here.
&lt;/p&gt;
— Titus Brown (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ctitusbrown&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown/status/377436924710907904&#34;&gt;September 10, 2013&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class=&#34;twitter-tweet&#34; data-conversation=&#34;none&#34; lang=&#34;en&#34;&gt;
&lt;p lang=&#34;en&#34; dir=&#34;ltr&#34;&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/RELenski&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@RELenski&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ClausWilke&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ClausWilke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Perpetuates belief (unproven) that “being good” is even &lt;em&gt;necessary&lt;/em&gt; for being faculty, much less sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;
— Titus Brown (&lt;span class=&#34;citation&#34;&gt;@ctitusbrown&lt;/span&gt;) &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/ctitusbrown/status/377437139094355968&#34;&gt;September 10, 2013&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src=&#34;//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&#34; charset=&#34;utf-8&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I subscribe to Malcom Gladwell’s threshold theory,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; which argues that beyond a certain minimum required amount of innate talent, professional success is largely independent of talent and depends instead on numerous other factors, such as the amount of training you receive and the opportunities that come your way. In a nutshell, according to Gladwell, you can’t groom the village idiot into becoming a faculty member at Harvard, but any incoming graduate student in any decent university likely has the innate talent necessary to get there.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; From there on out, it’s all just effort, proper coaching, the right connections, and some amount of luck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There can be no doubt that luck is important for professional success, in particular on the road to getting a tenure-track position.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Many pieces have to fall into place, many of which may not have anything to do with who you are and what you can do. If you’re on the job market in a recession, when there are virtually no faculty searches going on, it’s going to be tough regardless of your track record. If suddenly a new hot area opens up and you happen to &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work in that area, it may be difficult to convince departments that you’re the right candidate. My own trajectory reflects this. Without luck, I wouldn’t be a faculty member at UT Austin today. I got my job because Josh Plotkin’s wife needed to be close to a medical school, and UT Austin didn’t have one at the time. So Josh declined my department’s offer, even though it was his first choice. If Josh had been married to a different wife or not at all, or if UT Austin had been ten years ahead of their current schedule to getting a medical school, my life might be very different today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I do subscribe to the idea that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/3304496/Be-lucky-its-an-easy-skill-to-learn.html&#34;&gt;luck is a skill.&lt;/a&gt; I’ve seen this countless times with colleagues, friends, and family. Some people are just consistently lucky. They always seem to make out alright. And others appear to be consistently unlucky. Something always goes wrong for them, no matter what they do. As somebody who (I believe) falls on the luckier side of the spectrum, and also as somebody who has a good sense of how actions connect to possible outcomes,&lt;a href=&#34;#fn4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; I can usually spot the behavioral patterns that cause people to be lucky or unlucky. Show me somebody who is &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; unlucky, and I’ll tell you what they’re doing wrong. It would take more than a few lines in this already far-too-long blog post to explain specifics. So I’ll defer that for another time. For now, if you think you’re consistently lucky, keep doing whatever it is you’re doing. If you think you’re consistently unlucky, you probably have a tendency to use the wrong priorities in your decision making. You might make decisions out of fear, or out of a desire for pleasure, or for immediate benefit, rather than based on a rational assessment of the long-term consequences of your decisions. It might help you to discuss your decisions with a thoughtful mentor, &lt;em&gt;and to listen to her advice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s get back to the original question. What does it take to become a faculty member? First, you need some amount of innate talent. If you’re still reading, and you’re not constantly thinking “so many complicated words,” you probably have sufficient innate talent. Second, you need some genuine luck. For example, you accidentally meet somebody at a conference who turns out to be really supportive of your work; or you make a genuinely unexpected, major discovery; or your major competitor falls while rock-climbing and is out for a year, just when you go onto the job market. Third, you need some engineered luck. You need to see opportunities when they come your way and take advantage of them. When issues arise that could cause you trouble down the road, you need to deal with them efficiently and effectively. You generally have to behave in such a way that you’re not your own worst enemy. Fourth, you need to be willing to put in the required effort. The impressiveness of a cv is strongly correlated to the amount of work expended to developing said cv, and nothing is ever going to change that. And fifth, you need to have the resilience to slog through the downturns that you will inevitably encounter on your path in academia. There will be times when nothing seems to go right, when no reviewer likes your papers or grant proposals, when you feel you’re just spinning your wheels with nothing to show for. You will have to work through these periods to be successful in academia.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which of those five points fall under your control? The first does not. However, you’re still reading, so that point is irrelevant. The second doesn’t either. There’s nothing you can do about genuine luck or genuine misfortune. So don’t spend any time thinking about it. The other three points fall under your control, and they contribute (by my own, totally unscientific estimate) to at least 70%-80% of your success. So get cracking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;The threshold theory is described in Gladwell’s book “Outliers.” It’s a great book. If you haven’t read it yet, do so.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn2&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Realistically, if you start with serious coaching only in graduate school it may be too late for star-level success. The kids that were groomed to become Harvard professors when they were three years old will have an enormous head start, one that may be difficult to catch up to. You should still try, though.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn3&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this note, I find it interesting how many faculty members who are now among the most established scientists in their field were at some point close to giving up on academia. For example, Richard Lenski describes his winding path to &lt;a href=&#34;http://telliamedrevisited.wordpress.com/2013/09/09/the-good-old-days/&#34;&gt;his first faculty appointment here.&lt;/a&gt; I heard about this story first when I was on the job market and thought I’d never find a decent job, and I found it strangely comforting.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn4&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m an &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.16personalities.com/intj-personality&#34;&gt;INTJ.&lt;/a&gt; My mind is all about possibilities, and how they are connected to what’s happening right now.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn5&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course the main issue here is to distinguish between constructively slogging through a temporary setback and delusionally keeping on going even though the situation is truly hopeless. I hope my &lt;a href=&#34;/blog/2013/9/6/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career&#34;&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; can help there. As should any capable adviser or mentor.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From undergraduate to faculty member: Critical decision points in the academic career</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/09/06/from-undergraduate-to-faculty-member-critical-decision-points-in-the-academic-career/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you’re an undergraduate contemplating an academic career or a graduate student considering the next steps, you may have the long-term goal of becoming a tenured professor at a major research university. At the same time, you may have serious doubts about whether this is the career for you. Are you good enough to be a faculty member? And if you’re not good enough, will you waste years of your life with little to show for it in the end? Even if you’re good enough, is that sufficient, or will you also need an extraordinary amount of luck? By embarking on an academic career, will you be making a high-stakes gamble that may have a catastrophic outcome if you lose? These are serious doubts, and they can make the prospects of pursuing an academic career seem overwhelming and pointless. As a substitute for these overwhelming, larger-than-life questions, I’d like to offer a set of critical decision points and simple rules about how to proceed. I hope that these suggestions will make the path to an academic position more navigable and less stressful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me first clarify, though, that I don’t think every graduate student has to become a tenured professor at a major university. In fact, I believe that the majority of graduate students are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; on track to become faculty members. For example, I read about a case study once where of an entering class of 20 graduate students at Yale university, only 2 had a tenure-track career 10 years later (I’m recalling this from memory, so I may have some details wrong, but the gist was approximately that.) Losing that many students to pursuits other than pure academia is Ok, as long as the majority of them finds satisfying and appropriately compensated employment. And I’m pretty sure they do. They certainly do if they picked up serious computational skills during their PhD. On the other hand, while I don’t see it as my mission to turn every student of mine into a professor, I also don’t want to see highly gifted and capable students give up on an academic career just because they perceive it as an impossible feat, one they shouldn’t even attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-undergraduate-to-graduate-student&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From undergraduate to graduate student&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re currently an undergraduate, you shouldn’t even think about whether you’re on track to becoming a professor. It’s impossible to know anyway, and it doesn’t matter for the main decision you have to make: Should you go to graduate school or not? Unless you are under strong financial pressure to earn money right away (e.g. you have enormous student debt, or you have three children that you have to support on your own), this decision should not primarily be a financial one. For most students, graduate school is approximately cost-neutral: The stipend you’re paid while working as teaching assistant or graduate research assistant covers your basic living expenses. You don’t save any money while you’re in graduate school, but you also shouldn’t accumulate any debt. You could think about graduate school in terms of income lost over five years versus your future earnings potential, but frankly, if you think in these terms I don’t think a graduate program in science is right for you. Get a graduate degree in business, economics, or management, and embark on a career of serious money making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A graduate degree in science is for people who really care about figuring things out, or about solving problems. As an undergraduate, you have to be aware that graduate school will be very different from your undergraduate experience, unless you’ve already spent a substantial amount of time in a research lab. Graduate school is not about passing exams, getting good grades, or cramming material. In the end, it’s all about doing science and writing papers. Some people have a 4.0 undergraduate GPA and fail in graduate school, and others have a 2.9 GPA and succeed. If you really care about figuring things out, if you could see yourself spending months at a time getting to the bottom of an issue, then graduate school is for you. Don’t worry about the naysayers that say a PhD is a worthless piece of paper. I am not aware of any evidence that a PhD in science will &lt;em&gt;hurt&lt;/em&gt; your subsequent employability. It may not help you much, depending on how things go, but as I said already, you shouldn’t get into a PhD program for the money anyway. You should get into it because of your passion for research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-graduate-student-to-postdoc&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From graduate student to postdoc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, you’ve now made your way almost all the way through graduate school and the end is in sight. Should you continue and search for a postdoc position? Or should you jump ship and look for alternatives? At this point, I think it is justified to ask about earnings potential. You have obtained the most advanced degree you’ll ever get. From here on out, you’re not in it for the education, you’re in it for the experience. You have to ask yourself: Would I rather make money, or would I rather do nothing but research for a few years? For most academics, the postdoc time is a uniquely rewarding and free time. A time during which you can (mostly) freely pursue whatever research you care about, on your own schedule. You have completed your 10,000 hours of science by that time, so you can hit the ground running and do interesting stuff. For poor compensation, mind you. If your mindset is “I don’t really know what else I’d want to do anyway” then go ahead and do a postdoc. But if you can see a clear alternative path, and if that path looks attractive to you, then that alternative path may be the better choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Importantly, though, it is still not time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member. Plenty of graduate students don’t do that well, only to recover spectacularly during their postdoc. And others do well as graduate students but falter as postdocs. Generally, the former group does much better than the latter on the academic job market. I’m part of the former group, and I made out alright. I like to say that if you erased from my resume every single thing I did during graduate school, nothing of consequence would change. I got a job as a faculty member anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You do have to make an honest assessment, though. Where do you stand relative to your fellow graduate students? Would you say your performance is comparable to most? Better? Worse? After five years in graduate school, you may not yet have made an earth-shattering discovery, but you should know by now whether you’re cut out for science or not. In particular, do you have one or two papers to your name for which you did the majority of the work, including the conceptual work? (I don’t care how good they are, just that they got done.) If after an honest assessment you find that you’re not really cut out for science, then don’t do a postdoc. Find a different occupation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One word of hope for finding a postdoc position: For as long as I can remember, the job market has been in favor of postdocs. Any capable graduate student who wants to can find a decent postdoc position. So don’t ever worry about not getting a postdoc position. If you want one, you’ll get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;from-postdoc-to-faculty-member&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;From postdoc to faculty member&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you’re two to three years into your postdoc. Finally it’s time to ask yourself whether you’re on track to becoming a faculty member or not. Take honest stock. Where are you, compared to other people in the field that you’d be competing with on the job market. Ask some senior scientists about an honest evaluation. Hopefully your postdoc adviser will be able to tell you where you stand. In my opinion, if you’re three years into a postdoc and you’re nowhere near ready to apply for a faculty position, then it may be time to consider alternative careers. If you’re three years in and you’re ready to apply, then go for it and see how it goes. If you’re three years in and you’re getting close but you’re not quite there yet, then it’d be reasonable to wait another year. But don’t keep saying “I’ll be ready next year.” At some point, if things don’t work out in academia, you have to cut your losses and move on. Where that point is is a somewhat arbitrary and a bit of a personal choice, but I’d place it around five years. After five years of a postdoc-level position, you should find something more permanent. And if that job is not a tenure-track faculty position, then you may have to settle for research scientist, lecturer, administrator, or whatever else you can make work for you. There are plenty of reasonable career paths for a scientist, just don’t become a career postdoc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, you can’t expect things on the job market to work out the first time round. You may not be quite ready, the big paper you wrote may not yet be that well known, or it may just be a bad year for academic hiring. If by your own and by your senior colleagues’ assessment you are ready to get a faculty position, then don’t despair if it doesn’t work out the first time round. Try at least two rounds. Also, if you changed your field after your PhD, or if you didn’t really do much of consequence as a graduate student, you may need a little more time as a postdoc. I was a postdoc for five years, and I think I needed that time to be really ready for a faculty position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;summary&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As undergraduate, follow your passion. If you have a passion for figuring things out, get a graduate degree and see if you still like it five years down the road. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As graduate student, if your passion hasn’t disappeared, and if you can stomach another three to five years of being poor, go for the postdoc. Don’t worry about not being good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As postdoc, do an honest assessment of where you stand. If you are competitive on the job market, go for it. If you’re almost competitive, do what needs to be done to eliminate the “almost.” If you’re nowhere near competitive after about three years, start thinking about alternative options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why graduate students get a reasonable deal—A response to the anonymous grad student in the Guardian</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/31/atqeelrnfeyb3e03sycsdpl7p5zc83/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/31/atqeelrnfeyb3e03sycsdpl7p5zc83/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This morning, an article in the Guardian is making the rounds on the academic twitter feeds. The article is written by an anonymous graduate student, and it argues &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.theguardian.com/higher-education-network/2013/aug/30/what-does-phd-stand-for&#34;&gt;that graduate students are underpaid and that their salaries should be doubled.&lt;/a&gt; When reading the article, I couldn’t help but feel that it lacked the careful analysis, logical reasoning, and deep thought befitting of a graduate student. The author is either not aware of or willfully ignores how graduate students are paid and why. I am willing to give the author the benefit of the doubt, though. I recently had a conversation with a senior faculty member at my institution and she also didn’t really understand how graduate students are paid. So here’s the quick summary: per hour, graduate students are compensated better than most postdocs and lecturers. After tenure-track faculty members, graduate students probably get the best deal in academia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few caveats up front: I’m speaking only for natural sciences. Also, I’m speaking primarily for the US system. However, I got my PhD in Germany, and most of what I’m saying here applies to that system as well, as far as I know. I am aware that in absolute terms, graduate student salary is low. I think most professors are aware of this. In fact, our department is currently going through a strategic planning process, and the number one issue identified by our faculty was low graduate student salaries. However, I suspect that most people are thinking about a ~10% increase in graduate student salaries, not a doubling. Finally, I completely agree with &lt;a href=&#34;http://anothersb.blogspot.co.uk/2013/08/lets-pay-phd-students-more-and.html&#34;&gt;this blogger&lt;/a&gt; that everybody in academia is underpaid. In fact, when I meet with high-level executives from industry and tell them how much I make, they just stare at me in disbelief. So keep that in mind. Nobody is in academia for the money. With that, let’s have a look at graduate student compensation, let’s consider for what work they actually receive it, and let’s see how it stacks up compared to postdoc and lecturer compensation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate students are enrolled in a university degree program. As part of that program, they are expected to take classes and carry out independent study. The independent study component is basically their research program, and the final demonstration that they have completed their independent study is the PhD thesis. Note that none of this effort is compensated in any way. It is a fundamental principle of university education, not just in the US but in most places, that you don’t get paid to participate in a degree program. In fact, in most places you have to pay tuition to do so. In the US, tuition is quite substantial, and ultimately the graduate students are responsible to pay it in full. Now, in most reasonable graduate programs in the natural sciences, graduate students don’t actually pay tuition, and they do receive a stipend. How does this work? One possibility is that students can receive fellowships, but I don’t want to address fellowships here. The more common scenario is that graduate students are being paid as either Teaching Assistants (TAs) or Graduate Research Assistants (GRAs) or a combination of the two. In this scenario, the stipend graduate students receive is for their TA or GRA work. Generally, TA or GRA appointments also come with funds to cover tuition. So on top of their stipend, graduate students receive substantial additional compensation, on the order of $10,000 a year at my institution, and amounting to much higher levels at other schools. Because graduate students are paid for TA or GRA work, not for their studies, TA and GRA appointments are generally half time, 20h per week. I remember, when I did my PhD in Germany, that my GRA appointment contracts always contained a clause to the effect that my supervisor was required to leave me adequate time outside my GRA duties to carry out my own, independent research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how much do graduate students actually make? Typical salaries are around &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;2000 per month. Lucky graduate students make a little more, maybe &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;2200–&lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;2300, while the unlucky ones may make only around &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;1900. Remember, though, that these amounts are for a 50% time position. If you extrapolate to an annual rate at 100% time, you end up somewhere in the range of &lt;span&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;50,000, give or take. Almost no postdoc and very few lecturers make that kind of money. (Postdoc and lecturer salaries are closer to $40,000, and often below that.) And remember, that’s without tuition remission, which goes on top of the salary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, when graduate students are employed to do research (as GRAs), they are paid more per hour than postdocs are. And when they are employed to teach (as TAs), they are paid more than lecturers are, for a comparable workload. In particular, when a graduate student works as TA for a lecturer, the student makes more money than the lecturer does for that course, even though the lecturer has more responsibilities. (At my institution, one course pays for 33% of the time of a lecturer but for 50% of the time of a TA, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the TA has the higher base rate!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate students that work in well-funded labs generally get employed as GRAs rather than TAs, at least a substantial fraction of the time. Strictly speaking, the work they do as GRAs is separate from what they are working on for their degree, but most professors will try to give students work assignments that align with their own research plans. So if you’re a graduate student, are employed as GRA, and have no assignments beyond working on something that will count for your thesis, you’re getting a really good deal. You’re basically given the option to double-dip, to use the same work for both compensation and education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, as a thought experiment, what would happen if we actually paid graduate students at 100%? It’s simple. Most GRA positions would disappear. Already, if you do the math, you realize that a graduate student and a postdoc are comparable expenses. One year of graduate student salary plus tuition is comparable to one year of postdoc salary, in particular at schools where tuition is high. (As faculty member, if I want to employ a student as GRA, &lt;em&gt;I have to pay the student’s tuition from my grant.&lt;/em&gt;) I know many colleagues who say they’d rather hire a postdoc than a graduate student because they get a better deal for their money.&lt;a href=&#34;#fn1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If you now increased the annual cost of a graduate student by another $22,000, nobody in their right mind would ever hire another graduate student. You’d have to double the salaries of everybody, graduate students, postdocs, lecturers, and professors, to keep some sort of balance among the various compensation levels, and to prevent professors from hiring only postdocs. I’m personally not opposed to doubling the salaries of everybody, but realistically the money is just not there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize: Of all the things we can (and should) worry about in academia, high undergraduate tuition, low funding rates, poor job prospects for postdocs, tenured professors who’ve turned into dead wood, and so on, paying graduate students at 50% effort is the least of my worries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn1&#34;&gt;&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, in computer science it’s the other way round. Because most PhDs in computer science can go to industry and make a lot of money, postdocs can command a much higher level of compensation in that field, and hence professors are more likely to hire graduate students than postdocs.&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-back&#34;&gt;↩︎&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to approach professors by email</title>
      <link>/blog/2013/08/23/how-to-approach-professors-by-email/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Aug 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/2013/08/23/how-to-approach-professors-by-email/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/header-attrs/header-attrs.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Today’s advice is written specifically for undergraduates, even though graduate students and postdocs may benefit as well. (I certainly didn’t figure these things out until I was a faculty member myself.) What is the best way to approach professors by email, in particular if you want or need something from them? I’ll give you the most important advice up front: &lt;strong&gt;Be absolutely clear about your intentions.&lt;/strong&gt; Tell me exactly what you want or need from me, and why. This will save both of us a lot of time, energy, and frustration. (Frustration would be mostly on your part, though, when I silently ignore your messages.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a professor, I am constantly being inundated with requests, propositions, recommendations, and demands. And most of them fall into the category of spam, or at least not very high on my priority list. Almost daily, I receive requests from people who would like to join my “esteemed laboratory.” They usually come from overseas, sport a long list of qualifications in the latest experimental techniques, and seem to have no knowledge of the fact that my lab is entirely computational (it says so &lt;a href=&#34;http://wilkelab.org/#about&#34;&gt;right on our homepage&lt;/a&gt;). I’m also constantly asked if I want to participate in this or that activity, survey, or committee. (Do I want to be on the university committee that decides on the color of the men’s changing room in the new gym? No.) Over time, I’ve gotten quite good at deleting or at least ignoring these emails. Usually, I don’t need to read past the first or second sentence before I send the message to the circular filing cabinet. If you want to reach me, you have to somehow make it through that noise. Your message has to be clearly different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, reaching me through this noise may seem a daunting task, but it’s actually not that bad. The truth is, I want to interact with you, I truly do. For example, I have over 10 people in my lab, from undergrads to senior scientists, and almost all of them got there by sending me an email at some point. They all got through to me. In order for me to be able to help you, though, to consider your request, I need you to help me. I need you to be crystal clear in what you need or want. Do you need to see me before Friday because you want to drop my class before the deadline? Say so. I’m not going to chew off your head. (An aside: Students seem to be extremely shy about requesting a drop. I really don’t care. If you want out of my class, I won’t be in your way.) Would you like to meet me because you’d like to work in my laboratory? Say so. If you’re an undergrad, say whether you are looking for a paid job or are willing to volunteer/work for course credit. If you’re a graduate student, tell me why you are interested in my lab and what topics you’d like to work on. In general, the more clearly you can spell out what it is you want from me, the quicker I can decide whether I can be of help or not. And if I receive a clear, well-formulated request that I have to deny, I’ll generally respond quickly with a “no,” and possibly with suggestions where else you could go. By contrast, I’ll generally just ignore or delete any messages whose intent is not clear to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you would like to request a meeting with me, please suggest possible times that would work for you. Don’t just write “I would like to meet with you.” Write “I would like to meet with you. I’m available this week Wed. before noon or Thurs. after 2pm.” This saves us one round trip, because I can immediately suggest a time that might work for both of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, if I ignore your message, don’t take it as a “no,” try again. I may simply have overlooked it. Or I may have had the best of intentions to respond to you, but then I got distracted by something, then I had to teach a class, and by the time I was back in my office your email was long forgotten. So if I don’t respond to your message, send me another one the next day, or maybe two days later. In general, I think you should try at least 2-3 times before you conclude that your message is being actively ignored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; I wanted to add some thoughts about how to address professors in email. If you’re an undergrad, I think you should write “Dear Dr.” + last name. In my case, that would be “Dear Dr. Wilke.” If you’re a graduate student or postdoc in my department, first-name basis is fine, so “Dear Claus” or just “Claus.” If you’re a graduate student or postdoc at a different institution, I think the formal “Dear Dr. …” is the better option, in particular if we’ve never had any interactions before. (If we hung out at a conference over a beer and talked until 2am about everybody and their dog, “Claus” is probably fine.) If you choose the formal address, pay attention to the response. If the response is signed just with a first name, you can assume you’re on first-name basis from there on out.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
